us richard anik
and michael and the logo being made by
simuloid
as we're saying the logo was because
there are many magnets but not many
magnets
with zed so i think we can stick with
this
um from now on
uh usually the seminars are 25 minutes
um
and then after that we usually have 10
to 15 minutes
for questionable discussions uh text
questions are always welcome you can
you can have them in the text box um and
we can read them up for you
it's an informal environment so if you
need to go you can you can go
and after the seminar is finished
we will be here for a not recorded time
uh to catch up if you're interested
so the the youtube uh
the youtube uh video is gonna be hosted
by earth reference magic team which for
which we are
very grateful and there's gonna be
uh also uh do i associated with that
the schedule for now is today we have
frenzy milanese
and in october 14 we will left sayona
cantonsano and on 25th of november
at the atema in december we're gonna
have a christmas break
i think that's the plan so far we always
looking for new speakers for the
following year and any if you have any
idea criticism to
where to improve this series of seminars
they're all welcome
so for now i'm gonna have i am gonna
leave
florencia to her presentation
which you can you can start sharing your
screen
sharing mine
we are still not seeing it okay yes are
you seeing my screen now
yes no yes okay thank you
okay and i will
so you're seeing the whole
screen presentation right yes thank you
florence yes
good okay so hello everybody thank you
for
for being here um this presentation is
based uh on the results of my phd thesis
uh so it's pretty much an already
finished work
so here i'm going to summarize all those
results
and and actually the last paper coming
out from it was
published at the beginning of this of
this year
and and it's very classic of um max trap
uh job and many institutions cooperated
for this work to be done uh the
i did all the writing and analyzing
and the roadmap analysis at the buenos
aires uh palu magnetic laboratory
the institute antarctic argentina
provided the
logistics for the field work and i
processed all my paleomagnetic samples
at
caltech's laboratory and this is the
people that cooperated
with a whole or at least with part of
the of the work
i organized the presentation in four
sections
so at first i will give you a summary of
the
stratigraphy of the generos spacing
then i will point out some interesting
aspects
or some of the problems i i think
uh it will be the problems i think will
be solved
with magnetostratigraphy then i will
show the results
and then the conclusion or the or the
final
chronostratigraphic framework coming out
from the magnetostratigraphy
so here is the james rose spacing it is
located here at the northeastern tip of
the antarctic peninsula
and and going from from bigger to
smaller
the literature refers uh to to
everything
to the sedimentary cover below the
waddle sea
uh as well basing then
uh when we are speaking about the
offshore
uh antarctic peninsula platinum platform
basing we
speak of larsen basing
and the gangster spacing is basically
the outcropping
part of the larsen basin
and and the outcrops that that form the
gemstone spacing
are in this archipelago from james ross
island and
smaller surrounding islands plus
a few southern smaller outgrabs here but
basically gems were spacing is this this
this archipelago
so the spacing started as a backer basin
with an active arc
uh place here at the antarctic peninsula
and and has more than
six kilometers of sedimentary thickness
that
span from beramin to eoc
and the target of our work
is the cretaceous infield of basin
which is divided in two mega sequences
the first one is from from it goes from
the option to connection and
it is the deep marine sediments uh from
the gustav group
and and this group is it was the
positive during
an an active uh faulting environment
an extensional environment
and any and it is coarser than the
marami group which is our
specific target uh and and these fine
sediments from the mrambi group
are interpreted as the deposits of a
grading shelf developed during
an inversion stage of the basin
so um there are many many
characteristics for this spacing to be
important but
i i put the the three i believe uh
the most notorious uh this basically is
extremely phosphorous there are a lot of
faucets here
uh a lot of there so a lot of
bibles ammonites um
gastropods uh many vertebrates
palinomorphs there are dinosaurs
marine reptiles birds everything so and
fossils
they they have this very well state of
preservation
there is also the cretaceous paleogene
boundary there uh at
marambi or simone island and it has
citrocarbon producer potential not many
oil exploration has been made in
antarctica because it is not allowed but
it's another aspect we are not of course
talking about
this in this presentation so so these
characteristics may
make a make this spacing like a like a
reference
a reference section because it it
records everything that happened
uh after a breakup so it's a very
continuous sedimentary record from
boramian to eocene and and it is
also a very interesting place to to
study
biodiversity patterns and extinction
patterns in polar regions
before and after the mass extinction
uh but there are there are some problems
and and and this this problems that
that hamper the the quality of of being
a reference section for the spacing
uh they are the
the diagram is uh in the extinction
patterns
and the endemism of these species so so
many
species are are from antarctica
exclusively and they are not in
in the rest of the world so it's very
difficult to correlate
uh to correlate them in in
several funnel groups uh they
die earlier in antarctica than in the
rest of the world
so the the intra-basin correlation was
was based on on ammonite assemblages
this guy
did the the main the main job
and and what we see in the james ross
infield in the cretaceous infant is that
uh
for the early companion many ammonites
groups many ammonite groups disappear
and also these bibles and ceramics and
many organisms disappear
early during the early companion but for
example these bibles
they are found in south america in
tierra del fuego
they are found even in the early
restriction
so um oh
and and the other one that happens here
is after the early companion
uh cosmetics they become a very dominant
uh with respect to the rest of the
funnel groups
so so this diaphragmism and endemism
makes it difficult to
for this placing to be a correlated
level
uh here is uh an uh current station
graphic framework
and and it is divided in two areas so
the the norway
the northwest james rose space scenario
it involves uh the the most proximal
facials
which is logical because the the magic
arc is here
and also the older species so that this
uh gustaf group it it only aircrafts
here at
northwestern chambers island and the
southeast area of the basin
includes um all the distal phases
and also the the newest units and and
the same units
uh reaches more thickness in the distal
area so basically as we move to the
southeast
we go for from older and proximal
to younger and and deeper
so this this mag strat work
i i'm going to present it separated into
in proximal and and digital area
and here in green uh what we have is
is the different it's a summary of the
different
age models proposed by
by different paletologists so depending
on on which
organism they base their biostratigraphy
on
uh we have different h models so from
planomorphs and ammonites
declinations and tonium boundaries is
placed
in the gustav group and morambio group
uh boundary
the and and a little higher according to
energetics and strontium stratigraphy
so what the first the most is the
centonian companion boundary because
according to
olivero's ammonites it is at the base of
santa martin formation
here and according to energetics and an
instruction
isotopic stratigraphy it is pretty much
higher in the in the beta member
so we will try to and there is no
much difference between the companion
restriction boundaries so we will try to
sort
these these discrepancies with
magnetostratigraphy
so um in the proximal part of the basin
we sampled uh these units so that the
upper gustup group
and santa marta and the lower snow hill
is formation
and this is a detailed uh geological
scheme
so this this composite
uh stratigraphical column
was was made by oliver like 20 years ago
and and the correlations between partial
sections
was based on ammonites and mythology but
but mostly on ammonites and sandwiches
so here is hl section here is hl section
here is mot here's mlt within the
the center marked formation and so on so
so as we move southeast we go
we go higher stratigraphically
so this is for you guys to see how is
the
field work done there is an
there is an argentinian antarctic base
here and it drops us
by helicopter to every year
field area field work area so we set
these campsites in the place for one
month one month and a half
depending on how many hours we have to
sample and and
we eat here we we put our stuff here
we sleep in this pyramidal tent and we
go to the bathroom here
and the sections were measured with with
jacob's stuff
and and we drilled so all all samples
were
oriented uh there most of the samples
the problem with them around the group
sediments is
that they are very unconsolidated so so
this was not the rule not many harvests
to treat so most of the times
uh we had to find concretions in in the
unconsolidated
sediments and sometimes we had to
take block samples
sorry it's not okay so these are these
are views
from the outcrops this is the a view of
hl
here hidden like formation
this is a view looking to the cell from
g
120 section within the alpha member
this is a picture of heartbed but
definitely not
the rule f16 which is here beta member
still santa marta formation and and this
is a picture of
uh it's no helium formation this this a
long short section
i did not take these samples this these
two sections were sampled
by call tech group like one or two years
before i
got into the project but but i analyzed
the data
i used the data
so some rock mag i usually bore
geologists to death with rockman inside
your body diagrams and now that i have
the public
i won't because i don't have time but uh
what would be in fear from from from
rock mags we have titan magnetite
uh 36 cycles show that
samples saturate about a 200
and 300 milli teslas uh
passivities are about tens of million
teslas
and and from lori fewer tests we
we see that arm is harder to to wash
than irm when applying alternating
fields
so for us it's tetano magnetizer
the magnetic carrier
and and paleomagnetic behaviors for for
this section and it's
it's pretty constant for for the whole
basin for the homoarami group
so most of the time uh
demagnetization could not proceed
further than
than 300 degrees maybe
450 if you were lucky samples just went
crazy about
the temperature probably because of new
mineral formations
uh most components were isolated
using principal component analysis in
some cases we applied
brain circles and and the main
demagnetization process was
thermal with a
with a low temperature low fill
cycle so some sometimes when during
those
first steps of two nitrogen cycles and
naf until 69 nanoteslas maybe we obtain
a viscous component
most of the time yeah i mean samples
just died uh before we could delete all
the magnetization this is an exception
but i wanted to show it
anyway in which by 550 degrees we still
have the
40 of the magnetization so probably some
magnetite is present here too
um and these are the results for the
for the norwest area so
this is declination this is inclination
and and
and the dots are for uh vgp palliative
latitude
the angular distance between bgps and
mean value
so what we see here is at the base
uh a more or less continuous it's
everything normal at the base so
until g 120 until here
everything is is normal right
and from g 120 and up
everything becomes reverse
except for for one two
three normal levels but everything is
pretty much reversed
until the upper half of f16
here within the beta member
and from then and up normals
start again and everything is pretty
much normal except for these two
these two levels so putting all these
partial
sections together why it's not moving
sorry just frozen
okay so putting all these partial
sections together we built this
this composite column
and we know for sure that that this is
normal cretaceous upright because every
fossil says
so it can't be anything else so
and and all this reverse it it is it has
to be c
33r and and from and and we know
for sure that this boundary here it is
c33rc33n we don't know how far
we reach in c33n and
and if if you see here that there is not
there is a lot of sedimentary thickness
uh covered so not very continuous
uh record here so so we did not
correlate these two levels with anything
and
and we did not make any correlation with
um
the the global polarity time scale for
for this in thermal but but we know
for sure that this is cf34n
and this is c33r
so we found or or yeah we found a
centonian companion boundary
here uh we think alpha member
around here and and there are two
proposals for
for for the age of this of this boundary
so according to
to all and collaborators the the limit
agrees with the base of c33r
and and according to the international
commission on stratigraphy they adopt
this um this last apparent datum
of this crinoid for for for the
centonian companion binary but of course
we are on
on team base of 33 hours so
so this is the the boundary we take
so now we've been uh moving to the
digital part of the basic
um there are there are many isolated
sections here
to to put together so we will start with
with the vessel
rubber formation which is partially key
valium to santa marta so it's slightly
slightly younger and what we have for
rabbit formation
it has three overlapping sections so
these
three sections they they record more or
less the same structure graphic in
variable
so these are views of of the sections
this is a view from
base to top from from hamilton north
this is a view of of uh of robot from
from redonda point and and here at the
top
there are this uh mayas implies in
volcanics from the generous island
volcanic group
which are in at the top of many
cretaceous outcrops
uh there is more rock back here um
so from from low temperature
thermomagnetic susceptibility curves we
see
much paramagnetic contribution
um from a high temperature
what we see is all curves are not
reversible
so probably new i mean new minerals form
during heating and another thing i i
infer from from these curves is that
there is no
uh blocking temperature
there is no mineral with a blocking
temperature below
500 550 degrees celsius
and these are the magnetic parameter
parameters which are
very similar to the proximal or this is
not only for the rabbit formation these
are for the whole southeast area
and again creativities are are around
tens of milli teslas
so that the three columns put together
it was it was very easy to over uh to
correlate them i mean
i mean besides uh the ammonites
assemblages there is this
green volcanic plastic bed very obvious
very notorious it was in
in the three sections so what we see
in the three columns is a a basal
reverse and an upper normal
in thermal so the the
their version is within assemblage
ammonite's
assemblage six and we also found this uh
this reverse synthetic in all three
columns
but but this is the only possible
correlation because this reverse has to
be
c33r because of the ammonites
so uh about the rabbit formation we have
the the hamilton
point member there's no hilal
information
and we here have three sections too
but these three sections do not overlap
they are one
about uh the other
so these are our views from from from
from the sections this is hc from base
to top
base to top and mechanics of the
generous island
this is a picture of the sample all the
mirami group was
unconsolidated but that hamilton point
remember is the worst
it's it's just not healthy it's terrible
to work there
and this is the middle section this is a
view of the middle section another
another view from from base to top from
base to the top
h e section and this is the upper
partial section h d from from base to
top
base to top and then the volcanics here
up here
so so putting all the results together
what we see
in this in this three section is
everything looks pretty much normal and
and one thing i forgot to say when
when you see solid symbols is because
uh directions were isolated using a
principal components analysis
so empty symbols were obtained from
from great seal groups so except for
this level here
and maybe this one here but pretty close
to a horizontal and
this one and and this one
most of the of the sections are normal
so we will see the the correlation
together so
so crossing the sea uh the the last part
of
our outcrops are uh here at
cerro nevada or snow hill island so
central eclipse member
it outcrops here in this moon attack
it's a very um it's a very particular
place
you can attack because you're surrounded
by
eyes and you're here and on this spacing
and all you see around you is eyes it's
pretty it's pretty depressing sometimes
and well here at the back is the center
eclipse member
we were just we we were just dropped by
the helicopter here so we were setting
up
the campsite so this actually clicks
here and this is a view of the section
taken from some point around here and
and this is the section we
we we sampled
and these are the results for for the
sun for eclipse member
so um normal at the best uh
a short reverse in thermal and into
normal levels again and then everything
is
is pretty much reversed until the top
and behaviors well they they
they are pretty similar to the rest of
the
group units so there is one one off
level here
and above the sanctuary cliffs number so
one thing i didn't
tell you our our principle to define a
polarity
it was you you had to you have to have
more than one level in a row that's why
we
i i do not consider this as a different
polarity level
so another sanctuary case member we have
this spa peninsula perhaps
from uppers no helium formation hustle
and crack formation and and
base of lopez de vertadono
so this is the map of the peninsula and
and this is
the section we walked we we had to move
laterally here because we ran out of
of concretions to treat here and um
this is a view of the of the snow hill
island and haslam
contact yellow and and green
taken from the helicopter this is the
same
uh contact from from another point of
view and
and here are the dame raw asylum
volcanic group
uh dykes and and they basically cross
all the
all the penis line and they reach to to
seymour or marambi island too
and this is a view of the castle crack
uh lopez of berlin contact yeah green
and gray
and this is a picture of the concretions
we
we drilled oh
and there is a hut here in historical
hat from a
from a norwegian expedition uh
that happened in 1901
so this these guys uh were supposed to
stay
one year here at cerro nevado at snow
hill
and they built this this this hot that
now is like
falling because it's built on a on a
nice court um moraine
and these guys were supposed to stay for
one year but the
boda that should have uh picked them up
didn't make it through the ice so
they have to stay two years there but no
food so that they had to
hunt seals and penguins to survive
and this is the 2016 crew emulating the
norwegian
expedition and you barely can
distinguish which one is the original
so these are the results for the spa
peninsula
and everything is reversed here so so
the first time i saw this i
i i thought that i don't know maybe it
is
magnetized maybe this this this myosin
dikes
burned all the cretaceous and but it is
not we we actually compared uh mean
directions we did a sort of
of baking test and and no there is no
remagnetization and
and behaviors are very similar than to
the rest of
of of the group so
everything is reversed except for some
isolated levels everything is reversed
from
from base to top
okay yeah i'm almost done so
uh this is the the correlation we did uh
so this is c33n and and this is
definitely c31r
so uh so what is in the middle has to be
c32 and and and we apply the polysecular
variation filter
and and this one we would put it as a
question mark because
uh well it is just one level and and
it's pretty close to
transitional so so
so this is the correlation we did so for
for
for seeing everything together like
putting
all sums together to to to build the
puzzle
what we found here is that uh normal
cretaceous super crown
uh we found here
at northwestern uh james ross spacing
we found the centone companion boundary
there in within
alpha member we found this
uh c 33 r c
33 and reversion both in proximal and
distal phases of the basin
and and it's a this is a very good thing
because you have an extra correlation
tool
besides the ammonites and
we found the the companion restriction
boundary
somewhere here at the base of central
eclipse member
and and oh i'm sorry i forgot to say
this this
top call was was realized by tobin and
collaborators at
2012 it's not a part of my job
but what is striking here is that this
c31
cron is is too thick right
so so comparing we calculated
some sedimentary accumulation rates and
and and this c31
in thermal yields like five times the
the sedimentary accumulation rates than
the rest of the units
and it makes sense i mean those values
are
are within the reasonable values for for
these transitional marine environments
this
this stratigraphic inferible was
interpreted as as
delta deposits uh hustle
crack samsung actually it is a a forced
regression
sun package the positive probably in a
very
short amount of time and then estuarine
deposits so it is
reasonable but it's still like five
times the rest of the
of the calculated values so the
explanation we
we we seeked for for this
increase uh had to do with
uh at the time that there was closed the
black
uh roxburgh spacing in south america
and the antarctic peninsula and south
america were pretty much closer
than what they are today so we
believe that this uh increase of
sedimentary accumulation rates
uh has has something to do with
with um with an organic uplift
in the angus yeah that's because there
is this um
magazine is fallen thrust built and and
people that work there in theory
they have found several uplift pulses so
probably
that have something to do with the this
increase in sedimentary accumulation
rates
so these are the conclusions this is the
the chronostatiographic framework
that came out from magnetostratigraphy
so from sedimentary rates we
extrapolated the carnation centronium
boundary
to the hidden lake formation and
our centonian companion boundary agrees
pretty much with the with the ammonites
from olive oil
and the compendium restriction well it's
pretty much lower than both uh
ammonites and ionoceramides so that's
that's it thank you very much
thank you very much uh let's give
florencia a good
round of applause
thank you florencia okay i stopped
sharing now
i know leave it in case maybe people
have some questions
if that's okay yeah yeah no problem so
um
so there was a question by um
by lisa and i was regarding one of the
pictures that she posted
and and she asked if
a sample i think 79 is in situ
um i don't remember the name of the
formation but
so it is questionable one sample
yeah i realized that you you were
drilling um
concretions later it just looked like a
it wasn't
it was a little wobble right it
i was just curious how did you orient
these with magnetic compass presumably
compass and solar when we have sun
so this one or i think i know what
you meant first one where you showed
a drill it doesn't hurt this one yeah it
looks pretty wobble
realize if you're drilling concretions
and they probably are in situ
so i mean so no i i mean maybe
concretions moved when drilling but but
they
they were in place okay all right
yeah they were in place also i had one
more question if
um or comment uh and very nice
presentation by the way thank you
um for updating us on this i i
i feel pers that it's much more
convincing to show
an equal area project of all of the
directions
rather than all that rock mag stuff
because
um uh it tells you a lot more about the
reliability of
the directions which is what max lies on
than any of those other things so i just
thought you should
probably stick one there yeah well yeah
i mean i i do have them i didn't show
them because i
i felt like it didn't have time
all the other stuff which is really
irrelevant
okay okay so no no much
uh rug mag more directional data
because what's the rock mag tell you
yeah it doesn't do anything about the
directions
that's just the way between if you have
one time
so show us the equal area there they are
nice so and these are for the nor
west and these are for the southeast
and what happened in the southeast
is that when um including
cerro nevado it's not hill island data
it didn't pass the reversal test i mean
every everything has
the same polarity pretty much here
so what we did was treat
separately data from from cerro nevado
and
data from south east timbers and data
from norwest
and brussels and serenova island mean
direction was a little tilted
like rotating so that there is like
another
issue about directions here
so this is the the mean directions from
from many
you can measure this tilt right so
right so so this is our
direction and it was moved
so we compared it with the
dykes mean which is pretty white alpha
but
it was the data we have
so what we proposed it was in a
different paper
not in the magnetostratigraphy this is
these are other
myosin dykes data
is that there might be a rotation in
cervical
because the this separately the
distribution separately it makes
sense but when putting everything
together with the rest of some of this
data
it didn't so we had to separate
populations so this is
this is the directional data
i don't know if so why do you expect the
cretaceous
directions to be the same as the myosin
one
was that maybe i misunderstood you
oh because the first time we saw
this open direction i thought there
might have been a remagnitization
and i have something to do and
now i was just looking for some for
uh sources that had modified that
directions that were not a tectonic
rotation
but i didn't fight them so that's why
i think it is potato