cool so thank you all
uh very much for um joining the magnet
seminars
and we've had quite a successful run and
today we've got another
uh popular session so it's really good
that we're getting
a lot of support for these so thank you
all very much for for coming
um just a brief reminder for the formats
of the seminars our talks are
about 25 minutes or so so could you
please keep your microphones muted
during the presentations was not to uh
disturb the
the presenter um after the the
presentation will have time for a 10 to
15 minute uh
question and answer session if you don't
want to
unmute and ask an oral question we can
read out any questions that are sent to
the text
and either myself or anita or one of the
other
co-hosts will read out the question for
you
and you know we've all got life going on
in the background so as always if you
have to go halfway through
please uh just go don't worry about it
um and at the end of the seminars we
will have um a chance to have a bit of a
social
a bit of a catch up with everybody um as
to make sure everyone's all doing good
in a bit of a friendly chit chat
um but that part of the seminar will not
be uh recorded
uh and so without further ado i will uh
hand over to
uh yael englert who is a phd student in
our lab in liverpool
and she will be talking about anomalous
field behavior in the south atlantic
over multi-million year
time skills so i'll pass over to you
y'all
yes thank you let me just share my
screen
can people see my screen right now yep
so you've got your
um powerpoint window
which is right in there
okay uh thank you for having me uh
i would like to talk to you today about
the recurrence of the magnetic field
anomalies in the south atlantic on a
multi-million year time scale for this
research we performed the paleomagnetic
study
at st tavena which we just
published in our paper in pnas
um the
st elena is the star in this image wait
let me just
switch to a laser pointer
everybody can see it and so in this
image of the field intensity
uh in from 2015 from igrf you can see
the blue star
being saint elena in the middle of the
south atlantic anomaly
and this talk is basically a short
overview of the information that is
given
in our paper and and yeah
we hope you'll read it afterwards
so the current field uh the current
medic field is not a perfect eyeball
and the weakest part of being the
southland economy
is a popular topic of discussion
at saint helena the field is also weaker
than expected it's about
29.1 microtesla
where if there was a two-centric actual
dipole
field we would expect the field to be
33.8 micro tesla
but actually at this island the
directional normally is
even larger with an uh
inclination of minus 57 degrees where we
would expect
about -30 degrees if there was a
gadfield
um so to show this directional anomaly
we created this plot
showing a contour map of angular
deviation of the
present-day virtual geographic
geomagnetic poles to the
geographic bowl um and where you see
dark blue areas is where there's hardly
any
angular deviation or zero angular
deviation and then
where the colors get lighter or to
yellow and orange
there's a large angular deviation
between the virtual geometric pole
and the geographical and especially
the south atlantic anomaly is shown here
where there's a deviation over 20
degrees where st
lane is right in the center of that
so why is the size of land economy such
a popular topic
uh currently and why is it important
well obviously our
magnetic field protects us against solar
winds
and where the south atlantic economy is
there's less protection which is why our
satellites and international space
station actually get damaged and this is
a reason why nasa has been very
interested in tracking
the current behavior in the south
atlantic uh for us two physicists it's
more important to talk about
the features of the magnetic field and
how they are connected to lower most
mantle features
uh for instance john tarduno and others
presented this paper in 2015
um where they suggested that the edge of
the large low shear velocity province
uh coincides with this reverse flux
patch on the cormensal boundary
that possibly causes the south atlantic
anomalous
features uh here's the paper then
there's scientists who suggest that
the southland economy is a very recent
feature and
actually might be coinciding with the
total
drop of intensity of the field and
therefore might be
caused to believe that there's a
reversal coming up
and people suggest that if the south
atlantic region has been anomalous for a
long enough period of time it actually
defines the idea that our field averages
to a geocentric actual
dipole so many reasons
uh for scientists to publish so yeah
make many publications about south
atlantic
anomaly here's a couple of them from the
last five years or so
and then now our paper can proudly be
added to that list
um so i'm sorry
all these studies that i mentioned in a
previous slide except for our own
study uh the last 300 000 years either
with data or with models
but if you want to really make a
suggestion about the time average field
and its connection to the
lowermost mantle features we would like
to discuss at least 10 million years
time skills
and saint elena comes in because the age
of the rocks from saint-elaina vary from
eight and a half to
eleven and a half million years uh
another helpful guide for us
is that the two years ago psv10
was published this paper about a
database for all the directional data
from the past 10 million years
which we used to compare our data to
which makes it possible to really
comment on the
field for the past 10 million years oh
um here is a data distribution for that
data set so the red dots are all the
paleo locations for
sites in the psv10 dataset
which is plotted again on this contour
map for angular deviation
that we showed before as you can see the
south atlantic and only
region doesn't have any data points
in psv10 um there is tristan bakunya an
island in the south atlantic
that does have so it's a green square
here
that um does have a paleomagnetic study
uh since then by shaw and others from
uh which is not covered in pc10 and then
there's
saint elena which is even more important
because
uh tristan de cunha is only about 90 000
years old where saint elena comes in
with a very long time scale
so we went there uh january 2018
and the vegan and i went on field work
to saint elena which is uh
this beautiful island about 2 000
kilometers
left of the west coast of africa it's
about 122
square kilometers in surface and the
geology of st
elena is quite straightforward it
consists of two
shield volcanoes and one being the older
shield volcano
is exposed mainly in the northeast of
the island which you can see here on a
geological map so the red and orange
is the older is the exposure of the
older northeast volcano
the younger volcano is exposed in three
different shields
uh in these blue purple areas where
the upper shield is here where we
sampled
with the yellow squares and then the
main shield is in purple
and the lower shield is here in
turquoise
and the yellow uh symbols are where we
actually perform field work and as you
can see we sampled
all the different shields or times of
eruption so
we sampled the oldest northeast volcano
here in the banks valley area
where we took 10 sites and then the
youngest as i said
at prosperous bay it's called
then the main shield of the younger
volcano was trampled here at ladder hill
which was a very
very large section and we took 28 sites
from that section along a road cut and
then the
lower shield of the younger volcano we
took at two different locations
porches gate and sandy bay where both of
these locations had a dike intrusion
which we sampled to perform a baked
contact test
we sampled a lot in two weeks we took
over 50 sites
and 362 samples each site
generally represented a cooling unit or
a flow
and we sampled five samples minimum per
cooling unit
usually between five and ten samples per
site and
the flows varied in thickness from about
20 centimeters to
10 meters where possible due to exposure
uh we sampled the top the middle and the
bottom of the flow
and it was usually very obvious to see
where the flow began or
ended here are a few photos from our
fieldwork here in the top right photo
you see me
sampling at banks valley so the oldest
rocks of the island that we
took as you can see it's not the most
comfortable
sampling location it was quite steep and
we feared our lives a few times ah
that's exaggerated
here in the bottom left you can see the
youngest material that we took with us
aside from the bike intrusion so here's
prosperous bay and also one of the
thicker flows
and then here in the bottom right photo
you see andy
drilling in one of the dykes at sandy
bay so
in the younger volcano a dike intruded
which we sampled for a big contact test
which actually turned out to
be a lot less straightforward than we
imagined
and if i do have time at the end of the
presentation i prepared a few slides
about this
intriguing diet intrusion
so we demagnetized all of our samples
either thermally or
in an alternating field using a rapid 2d
magnetometer
or sorry or a jr6 spinner
and our results were very clear
all the directions were straight to the
origin
or if there was a larger overprints like
in this sample
uh the characteristic remnant
magnetization was still very clearly
interpretable
so overall our maximum angular
deviations were very low
if they did exceed 14 degrees we left
them out of the results
um the mean directions per site were
also very coherent so we
took a selection criteria of k over 50
and n equals over 5 and that left us
with 34 sites
and then we had two positive big contact
tests and a positive reversal test that
also
convinced us of the fallacy of our data
here is a summary
equal area plot of all of our sites
combined
and as you can see we both have reverse
and normal polarity in our sites
and you can see that there's many orange
sites which are from the latter hill
section that i mentioned before was a
very very large section in the
main shield of the younger volcano and
you see
uh a lot of green sites that have normal
clarity they are from the banks valley
section that was
in the oldest volcano and then you see
that uh
blue sites actually have some
transitional results
and this section showed us a reversal
where this is the bottom flow and it
goes
to the transitional flows and the top
flow actually has a normal
reversal and this is more
obviously uh clearly seen in this rough
magnetic polarity stratigraphy that we
created
where again you see all the sites here
all have a normal clarity from banks
valley
then the very large section in the main
shields
called ladder hill have three reversals
within that section
and then the youngest section prosperous
bay shows
a reversal in the actual results
and you can see that in our timeline we
have
we capture six different reversals which
is very reassuring of
our data set spanning a long enough time
timeline to say anything about secular
variation
when we plot our virtual geomagnetic
poles as we do here
after normalizing the reverse data and
we can yeah see a few notice a few
things
one the most important being that the
scatter of this data set is very very
high
so there's a lot of outliers um and yeah
the dispersion that we calculated is
21.9 degrees
which is very high for the latitude of
saint elena i'll come back to that later
on
uh second thing is that even though
there's a lot of outliers and the
scatter is very high
the actual average of our data set isn't
that far
from the geographic pool so
even though we see a lot of anomalous
behavior
the actual average still gets close to a
geocentric actual dipole
which is reassuring for the paleo
mathematic
uh community so then we also plotted the
pool for the current situation so this
is the present-day field pool
for st elena which is noticeably uh not
much of an outlier compared to the rest
of our data from saint elena so although
in the current geomagnetic field
obviously the south atlantic
is uh showing very anomalous behavior
over time
the pull for the current situation isn't
an outlier for saint elena
compared to the rest of our data set
um so this 21.9 degrees vgp dispersion
that we calculated
um is very high for our last for our
latitudes but obviously we want to make
sure that it's not dependent on either
the fundamental cutoff that we used
or on the selection criteria that we use
like
in our case k being over 50 and n equal
or over 5.
so in this bar plot i present the other
scenarios that we tested and calculated
the vtp dispersion for
in all scenarios we use this equation to
calculate the vtp dispersion where we
also
accounted for the within sight
dispersion calculated from k
and in the bar plot you can see green
and blue
bars where the greens represent
scenarios where
we use the fundamental cutoff and the
blue
bars represent scenarios where we used a
45 degree cut off
and then the dark green is the scenario
where which is our preferred
selection criteria with k over 50 and n
equals over
equals or over five and then on the
right hand side of the plot you can see
all these
diagonal stripes through the bars which
represents that we
corrected for serial correlation how we
did that
is that we calculated uh over checks for
flows that were
right on top of each other and we
calculated or tested if they have a
common true mean direction
if they passed that commentary mean
direction test we
uh yeah took them as being serial
correlated so
uh deposited in such a short amount of
time that it captures only one moment of
the field
so we combined those two results and
then uh
took only one of the like the
combination into the
calculation for the vgp dispersion
so what you notice if you look at this
bar plot is that it does vary a little
bit our result is right here at 21.9
degrees and it goes down to
the lowest vgp dispersion is 18.4
degrees
is when we take k over 100
um and it goes up a little bit if we use
a 45 degree cutoff for instance
however even though it goes down all the
way to 18.4 degrees when we compare it
to
the predicted value at um
our paleo latitude of 19.8 degrees south
it is still uh statistically high so
here is a purple line or
pink line which represents the value for
model g
and to calculate basically the expected
ptp dispersion
at this latitude and multi is a
relation between latitude and vgp
dispersion in this case we took the
values for
a and b uh that are based on psv10
uh which are published by the ravine at
all in 2019
and i'll show you the model the
relation in the next plot as well where
we took all the data from
these v10 from the cromwell paper and
divided them into latitudinal bins of 10
degrees
but separated for the pacific hemisphere
in blue
and the atlantic hemisphere in green and
as you can see it follows the trend very
nicely
especially in the northern hemisphere
and again this trend is
uh mology but then our saint elena data
point right here the red star is
a massive outlier um
so and yeah that's the main thing to
take away from this plot really is that
just the vtp dispersion
at saint elaine is substantially higher
than expected at that latitude
and expected from the model g
calculations
then another thing to notice is that the
green bars
so the latitudinal bins from the
atlantic hemisphere
plot above this model g prediction a lot
more often than the blue
pacific bins so 64
of the atlantic bins plot above the
model g trend where
only 27 of pacific bins plot above this
trend
and another thing we noticed is that uh
like i said before
the data actually follows this model g
trend a lot better in the northern
hemisphere than in the southern
hemisphere
but that might be due to these bins uh
being
under samples which makes them under
represent secure variation
when we look at our ps v10 data set in
localities
instead of in latino bins st elena is
still an outlier it's again this red
star
um but there are a few other outliers as
well that don't follow the trend as
nicely and that weren't visible
in our previous plot the main one that
we want to
focus on is this outlier right here
which has a
vgp dispersion of over 25 degrees and
at that latitude again that is very very
high
so we looked at that beta point which is
um
the island of martinique which lies in
korean
and it's right next to the island of
guadalupe and they're only about 150
kilometers apart
and similar in age as well which makes
us
agree with the author of the
paleomagnetic study that was performed
at martinique
who say that the high secular variation
or the high gtp dispersion
from their data set is due to the low uh
amount of sites
that they sampled and not due to a low
to anomalous behavior in that location
because then obviously there would also
be very high vgp dispersion
at the island very close to it
and we can also show you the secular
variation or future dispersion assist on
the cunya which is the green square
here um which is as expected higher than
the trend
uh because it is in the south atlantic
um however it's a very young island and
therefore also
they didn't sample as long of a time
span as we did so that explains why it
isn't as
as much of an outlier as saint elena and
possibly also because it's a bit further
from the
center of the south atlantic economy
so um i think we've established that
there's a high
secular variation in the area around
saint helena but what causes this
anomalous region to
to have higher secular variation than
elsewhere on the globe
well there's many different theories and
as we mentioned before there's a theory
from john tarduno and others
that they suggest a large low shear
velocity province and its steep edge
causes a reverse flux patch on the core
mental boundary
possibly causing the anomalous behavior
and then there's other scientists who
suggest that their existence
of this eccentric gyre in the outer core
um which reaches the core mental
boundary at the
right under the atlantic is caused for
higher circular variations so
uh there's a paper by oberon others from
2013 who show
uh with numerical models what happens
when they put in this eccentric gyre
which
they say is eccentric due to the
asymmetric growth of the inner core
which then reaches the hormonal boundary
right
under the atlantic and in their models
this also causes
higher secular variation for the entire
atlantic hemisphere
which would agree with our conclusions
that we saw earlier
in the in the peace v10
relationship of v2p dispersion and
latitude
but it wouldn't necessarily explain the
extreme outlier that saint elena is on
that plot
so possibly it would be a combination of
both of these
scenarios
but the conclusions that we actually can
take out of our data set
out of our study is that vgp dispersion
for saint elena is
significantly high compared to the rest
of the globe for the last 10 million
years
which uh does support the existence of
an anomalous uh geomagnetic variations
and anomalous behavior in the south
atlantic for the past 12 million years
which is potentially linked
to the interactions across the
governmental boundary and the existence
of this
anomalous behavior for such a long time
scale makes the chance of it being
connected to the mantle
all the higher then we can say that our
mean pool our average
result uh actually isn't that far from
the geographic pole so it doesn't
necessarily
suggest that the time average field
columns reflect
a geocentric actual dipole and the fact
that we have a positive reversal test
agrees with that as well and the current
poll
for saint-elaine other current gp is
actually not an outlier compared to the
rest of the data from the past 12
million years at st toledo
um thank you very much that was my talk
well thank you very much jahl that was a
really good talk
i think we can all uh show our virtual
uh appreciation with our virtual round
of applause
um thank you very much that was really
good um
we can now open the the floor to to some
questions if anybody has some
there we go i can see lisa has uh elisa
talks has raised her hands
um if you'd like to unmute
yeah i had a couple questions um very
nice talk thank you
um yeah um
i i just was curious about two things
one is
that in the psv10 data collection
uh they uh or i should say we
collected for um plate motion
and um in because
over the last 10 million years if you
just restrict it to
a couple million years you don't have to
worry about it but
uh 10 million years you do
and um africa the african plate has been
moving northward
and it should be about a five degree
um correction for that from african
plate motion
um that's one thing so i was wondering
if you corrected for that
and the second thing is that uh ron shar
i'm sorry he didn't show up today uh he
he sho we published a paper recently
from the golan heights
and uh from from the levant
and he said which shocked me
uh that and but it's true if you use
tighter selection criteria like you're
mad of 15
is is very very loose
we always use five and
um he suggested that if you use an n of
six
and a cap of a hundred that the scatter
in our uh israeli data set
went way down and so we did the same
thing
in our reanalysis of the antarctic data
of lawrence and found the same effect um
and so i'm just curious how much
uh data scatter contributes to
your vgp scatter
okay so first the first question is uh
about the the movement of the plates
which we corrected for in the exact same
way
uh we basically copied it from p310 with
the nnr
marvel uh model that we used so it is
indeed
about six degrees even i think that
saint elena
moved um so the current latitude is
about 12 degrees
and we looked at the latitude which was
then was
about 19 degrees south okay so that's
the first thing
and then the second thing is uh yeah a
very important point
um i didn't actually look at the maximum
angular deviation
average for instance i think ours are
overall
lower than like a lot lower than 15
degrees
um so that would be interesting to see
what happens what is left
if you kick out more but i think it
would have a very small effect except
that your
end would then be a bit smaller if you
would have to
already small i mean you need a hundred
but
yeah and then um with the k value
obviously we did look at the
k over 100 situation which brings it
down to 18.4 degrees as i said in my
talk um
which is lower than 21 uh for the
4k over 50. but then yeah our n
value is only 19. so it's weighing the
ideas but i think the most important
thing is that 18.4 degrees would still
be statistically
a lot higher than than the expected
value
uh that we see from the trend that psv10
follows
and then i think if you would take our
data set and only look at what happens
with k over 100
you should reanalyze the psv10 data set
as well because maybe the whole trend
would then
absolutely i think so i probably have to
go
back to all these methods and do them
again and then yeah there's this
issue of not having enough yeah stamp
sites left and
it being quite difficult to go back to
saints elena especially current
situation together more but i think
i am definitely convinced that showing
that with k over 100 the
ptp dispersion is still statistically so
much higher
that there is something going on there
causing this high secular variation
yeah i think you're right i think your
instincts are correct
okay i do think we should go back to all
those islands
like an exercise and keeping keeping
ourselves on a job
you know i mean we prove this now but we
need to go back to get even more
a very good idea um so i think uh kathy
constable has a a question
uh in fact you're telling it yeah um
sorry first of all i've got a actually
i've got two questions
um my first question is actually about
numbers of data and uh whether you think
we really have enough
if you look at the psp 10 data set uh
there's a sort of there's an assumption
that the temporal sampling across all
these globally distributed sites
is somehow equivalent but we don't
really know that
for the past 10 million years and if you
look in the the 5 to 10 million year
older than 5 million year
interval you know there's a there's 166
sites in psv
10 and then if you correct for serial
correlation there are actually less than
a hundred
and so this is kind of a delicate issue
right because you're arguing that you
can
pick distinctions between ferran
fernando diranha and other places
and that in some cases you're arguing
that
small numbers of sites means you
overestimate the dispersion in other
cases as an argument that it
underestimates the dispersion and you
can't have it both ways
so the first question is you know are
there
how many sites do we really need in
order for you to be able to say this
and my second question well just get it
out there well
so you so you have a chance to forget it
is if you look at the um
south atlantic anomaly today there's a
significant low in
field and strength and so i'm wondering
if you have any hope at all of looking
at the paleo intensity
and uh using that to support the idea of
perhaps low intensity to support the
idea that there's a significant anomaly
there
and by the way it was a nice tool well
thank you
um the first question i find very very
hard
very difficult to answer because you're
right the data
is mainly focused on even the last
million year not so much
exactly specifically last five million
years um
so i think we could have a very lengthy
discussion with the entire community
about
what what is enough data and in the end
you do what you
do with what you have and i do think for
saint elena specifically we have enough
to show that
that is high sector variation um
and even i would say
that we could make that you know
comparison to
to the rest of the globe with psg 10 but
yeah we have to keep in mind that these
v10 might be
mainly actually ps35 plus a few extra
locations
um yeah i mean you if you look at the
distribution
for the older than five million years
it's you know it's like
i don't know eight or ten from
spitsbergen
uh less than ten from france uh you know
brandon
aren't a couple of from patagonia and
none of these are really large enough
samples to get a statistically
meaningful average
so you don't really know whether you've
got the contrast or whether it could
actually just be
that psv was overall very high at that
time
for example and that would be uh
that would also be an interesting result
would actually also be very interesting
yes um yeah i wouldn't know where that
boundary would be
exactly but i mean
i guess we'll just have to find a lot
more sampling locations that have
samples of older than 5 million years
and that
yeah in the south south southern
hemisphere specifically would be nice
and then your second question is yes we
are definitely working on gradient
density data
however uh currently the last four or
five months nothing has happened
so uh yeah hopefully very soon i can get
back to liverpool and
back to that we have some results but
it's very limited so far
and actually those are very varied as
well so
it's it's uh it's not yet good enough to
uh
share with the world yeah okay
thankfully i have time in the rest of my
phd before uh
yeah i'm done the covet situation
excellent thank you um do we have uh any
any other questions for y'all
oh we've got uh this might be a bit of a
plant but we've got a question from andy
biggin
hi um so yeah i'll do i'll just
weigh in on the as it's a comment really
just um we're talking about how many
samples you need so
can um i can't share my screen so i'm
looking at a plot now from a
monte carlo analysis that uh i published
in a 2008 paper
and basically yeah this is about right
though if you
the other 100 is ideal if you want to
get to
um you know dispersions that are likely
to be accurate to
to a couple of degrees uh but anything
sort of 25 up you should be down less
than five degrees sort of
out so on this on this level of
discrepancy that we have
a global data that's i would say that
we're kind of we're into getting into
safe territory there
so yeah i think you're in safe territory
the question is whether other people are
uh i would say below 25
yeah and certainly below uh 15
then you could be all over the place and
also to come back to what you said
um they can be both high and low
so there's no bias at least from this
from the simple analysis that i did that
they could be
for ten for an end of ten you can be you
know
easily up by uh uh yeah seven or eight
degrees or down by the same amount
i think what we're really saying is we
should re-analyze the psv10 data set but
then
instead of looking at localities with
minimum of nine we should look at
localities with a minimum of 15 to 20
let's see what's left and then you need
a
we need a taffy 2.0 where we get
actually what you need which is 100.
there's that's a lot of work so i'll see
you
the years nice
good excellent um we have time for
another question before we come so close
so i've got one last question um that is
uh
did you sample everything that's
available
or could you actually go back and get
more
um there is more available but we
definitely sampled the highest quality
flows that are
uh there then so for instance
ladder hill had like 50 sites
the ones that lived uh either you know
low quality or very altered or something
and then there's different outcrops that
are still uh available but like a
two-hour hike
so we didn't have time and so we also
don't know the quality because we never
made it there
uh so there is there is still
opportunity it's just a matter of
whether it's
worth it then considering
how far that travel is i would be up for
it but
right because they just need to be paid
to go there
one lava flow in yanmayan
i think uh anita has another uh anita
has a quick question
sorry i wrote it in the chat sorry i was
wondering y'all what's the
what was the uh situation when you went
there
i see you have a already nice george
grandma
i was wondering about dating constraints
they were already some dating done or
did you do it
oh and so the dates that we use
for our study have been uh published by
hanyu at on 2014
so that is the most recent and that's
the only argan iron dating that has been
done
uh but it's not the exact locations that
we sampled
some some are but most of them are from
quite different location so we had to
um either interpolate like between
the this age that we knew that was
younger and
older um and then we are currently busy
with uh
another argan argon study and go out a
collaboration of the
scotland glasgow i think
thanks cool excellent thank you very
much shal
i would like to just ask everyone once
again to give iel another
uh virtual round of applause for a very
good uh presentation and
um a very good uh question session
um before we all
um come to a complete close um
i just like to to to remind everybody
that
um all of our magnets uh presentations
are
going up onto youtube it's a very long
link there uh i'll send out a url to the
um to the mailing list and i want to
thank the
earthref and magic team for for hosting
us um
and for um setting up a system so that
these presentations
are citable uh objects um a reminder
that we've got
um our schedule uh for the next
few weeks we've got most of it filled
until the end of the year
um we may have a slot uh available in
december
but i think that given that egu is
looking up looking to basically take up
the entirety of of december um we will
probably not be
hosting uh a seminar uh in december
um but we'll be we'll be back uh
properly in the new year
um but as always um feedback and
criticisms
are welcome just drop us an email and
thank you all very much
for uh joining uh magnets today thank
you