thank you everyone for uh joining the
magnet seminars this week
um and it's another another uh good
turnout so thank you very much for the
community support and just a very quick
reminder
about the uh seminar formats we have a
20 25 to 30 minute presentation i kindly
ask that everybody keeps their
microphones muted so it's not to
interrupt the presenter
um following that we'll have a 10-15
minute
uh question and answer session and we'll
invite you to on your microphones and
ask an oral question
if you don't want to to ask a question
um
in person you can add the question to
the chat
if you just simply put no mic then
either myself or one of the co-hosts
we'll be able to uh read out the
question for you
um and as always if you have to just get
up and go halfway through the seminars
please
just get up and go we've got life going
on all around us
and at the end of the session we'll have
time for a bit of a catch up with
everybody
and that part of the seminar will not be
will not be recorded so it's a
bit more of a relaxed environment and so
today our speaker i'll hand over to our
speaker adrian
[Music]
who will be presenting on diagenesis and
magnetic
signals of hydrocarbons
good hopefully you can see my screen now
um okay so major maxwell from piro
college
um i run the natural magnetism group and
i'll be talking about work that we've
been doing over the last decade and it's
something i've not really talked about
personally with this community some of
my students over the years have done
that but i haven't
given a talk on this particular topic to
uh this of the paleomonetic community or
geometric community
um so this is works been done with um
alfresa who's
worked for bp for i guess about 30 years
in exploration and now he's works at
university
uh mark sefton who's a organic
geochemist
and with a range of former and
current uh phd students your names are
up there on the screen you might have
met some of them at various meetings
over the
last few years so i'm going to be
talking about the magnetic signature of
uh hydrocarbons
um now we're not the first people to do
that and i guess the sort of first
motivational paper came out in 1917 i'm
not going to spend too long talking
about the history of this but just a
little bit to give some
idea of the motivation um
the first paper came out in 1979 where a
paper by donovan who did an aeromagnetic
survey
over an oil field called cement field
i'm not quite sure why it's called
cement field in oklahoma and
they detected magnetic anomalies so
i've got the sort of mineral or rot
magnetism interested in what might be
causing
that and over the last few decades a
number of
academics from various places around the
world particularly people like doc
elmore
groups in venezuela they've looked
trying to link
magnetic anomalies trying to understand
these magnetic anomalies
and trying to tie them to hydrocarbons
so here we've got this study from
from 2000 from the group in venezuela
and they've got
three cores um
the two on the left are above
hydrocarbon reservoirs and the one on
the
one on the the right is not and you can
see there's these
these spikes in the susceptibility and
the the values substability are much
higher
so there's clearly sort of some kind of
link going on between
the presence of hydrocarbons in in the
ground
and the magnetic uh magnetization the
magnetic signal of rocks
um it's been documented for a long time
now there's a picture from dog elmo from
987 you get these
wonderful framboids of iron oxides and
iron sulfides
and he who's we've got a picture on the
right taken by a former student
of mine stacy emerton and this is on the
on the one of the riders of a nice
framboid of
of of gregite um
and this is another sort of uh magnetic
uh
response that we kind of see in
association with hydrocarbons
in addition to that uh uh hans mackel
who's one of our collaborators
and liz burton did a whole bunch of
thermodynamic modeling
in the early to mid 90s where they
looked at
iron oxides and sulfides and cellulite
in the presence of various hydrocarbon
systems at a range of depths and
pressures and they showed how the
different minerals
would form and change depending on the
conditions so there's a whole
wealth of background um
in literature before we started looking
at this
problem okay so i'm not starting from
scratch or
one of the things even though there's
been a lot of work done there wasn't
really a
clear link between the magnetometer and
the hydrocarbons have been various
studies but they're often
related to various kind of aspects
of uh you know being case studies so see
some trends in one place but we can see
in the other place and we want to try
and
make something a bit more unified and
then can we use these magnetic signals
as a proxy to understand hydrocarbon
systems
so we're going to talk i'm not going to
talk too much about sort of background
geology but just a little bit here
um what how does oil form if you have a
sediment that's full of
organic material it gets buried when it
gets down to about
three kilometers or so starts to form
into oil if you go deeper it forms into
gas
of course oil and gas a light molecule
so they want to
go up so they try and escape from where
the deep places and go
go upwards towards the surface so they
then migrate
along through typically um
porous rock plastic rocks like sandstone
until they get trapped by an impermeable
layer
and you get a range of different kinds
of traps you can have anti-klein's
faults there's a whole range of
different types of traps and of course
the
the gas is lighter than the oil so you
tend to get gas on the top and you get
oil
and underneath you typically get maybe
get some water so you get these
different types of contacts and i'll be
talking about contacts a little bit
later on so this is the kind of system
we're looking at
we also have to worry about
biodegradation of the oil because this
has been shown to affect the magnetic
mineralogy so
as the oil gets towards the surface so
as the temperature drops below about 80
degrees celsius and impossible for
bacteria
to live they they quite like this
hydrocarbons and they
they essentially destroy it they degrade
the quality of it
and in the process some of these
bacteria can produce
magnetite particles as in this picture
here and some of them
can destroy the magnetization so it's
something else we need to consider when
we're looking at the magnetic response
of a hydrocarbon system
now i'm going to talk about some
examples of some work that we've done
and i
i didn't this is only the second time
i've been to one of these talks and i
haven't realized it's only supposed to
be 25 minutes so i might
just cut off just do the first three
bits and
take then go on to the end okay so
all these are the things that we these
are the sort of things we've been doing
over the last 10 years at imperial
and what we're going to do is we're
going to start off with the oral kitchen
this is the part
where the oil um
forms okay so if we're going to use
magnetization as a proxy we need to have
some kind of idea
um how these magnetic particles are
being formed are they being formed as
the fluid
uh passes through the rock some sort of
so that minerals are formed
in situ in place or are they actually
transported
with the oil itself so we did a series
of paralysis experiments to see if oil
if
when oil forms where the magnetic
particles form as well and whether these
particles
are small enough to be transported with
the oil so paralysis is essentially what
we're doing is
we're reproducing what we see in the
environment we're creating pressures and
temperatures which are
enough to generate um oil so we're going
to essentially going to make oil in the
lab
and this is this process is called
paralysis and to do that we need
we need a source rock so we're quite
lucky in
london which is just about here that
we're about two hours drive from the
wessex basin which is the
probably the best example of an onshore
um oil
uh hydrocarbon system in europe so
people not just people from uk but
people from elsewhere
will come to this this area to study
hydrocarbon systems
and if you go down to the beaches all
the way along the beach here you get the
sandstone outcrops
and you can see you can see all this
all this uh the sand here the sandstone
and if you look at this you probably
think this is
wet and it is wet but it's actually all
oil if you actually go there the oil is
literally just
dribbling out of the rocks at the side
there it's so rich and all now
clearly if we wanted immature sauce walk
rock we want some of the rock that
hasn't actually been buried or isn't
contaminated by the oil so obviously
we've got our immature sauce rolled from
somewhere else but
it's this famous kimridge clay and blue
lyrics and oxford clay which are full
of organic content and we made oil in
the laboratory
now we haven't got geological time
scales so we have to cheat a little bit
and by cheating
we have to speed up the reaction to
speed up the reaction we go to higher
temperatures so
in nature this would typically be
happening at 100 degrees say or
something like that
we went up to 200 degrees to see what
happens to the magnetization
to generate magnetic properties on a
time scale
which is uh more you know more human so
we can
three or four days is typically what
we're looking at so
here we have hysteresis loops of a
sample so we've taken the unheated
sample as a history
you can't really see it because there's
nothing to see it's completely flat
there's no magnesium whatsoever
then when we did the paralysis
experiment at 250 degrees
we generated this curve here so we've
generated all these ferromagnetic
minerals
and when we did it at even higher
temperature we find that we had
even more uh well with different type of
magnetic minerals we're at slightly high
temperature now i should stress that
these are at artificially high
temperatures so that potentially the
minerals that we're producing
might not be exactly the same as what
might happen
in nature because we're doing these at
artificially high temperatures but the
idea is
that magnetic particles can be generated
so here we have a graph
of saturation magnetization from the
hysteresis loops
and this is the this is the unheated
immature sample
this is ms for three different source
rocks immature rocks
and this is the the response and these
are the temperatures at which we did
the paralysis and so here we have these
iron sulfide minerals when you go to a
certain level at 300 you're going to
drop to zero but then
above that we start producing iron oxide
minerals so clearly
we can produce this um
produce lots of magnetic minerals and
when we try and measure the magnetic
properties to try and get an idea of the
grain size
we see that we have lots and lots of
very very small
eliminated particles of the order of 30
nanometers now you might think we've
only got small particles
because we've done these experiments
very quickly and in nature because
you've got more time you end up with
much larger particles
but as you'll see later on these very
small particles of the order of 30
nanometers or less than 30 million are
very very typical in the natural systems
as well
just to verify that we have these very
small particles we did some transmission
electron microscopy
and we managed to find quite a lot of
these little
uh nanoparticles is 20 nanometers i
think this was a
an iron sulfide
mineral so this was part of uh
a piece using red used phd thesis and
then we showed this accelerated
paralysis produces these nanoparticles
and these nanoparticles importantly
are small enough to pass through the
pore spaces
in a typical sandstone so typically
you're looking at things less than 100
nanometers so 13 less than 30 nanometers
is much less than this critical limit so
the potential for the the magnetic
particles to be generated in the old
kitchen actually to migrate with the oil
itself
later on another phd student of mine
shopping was keen to test the idea that
the
oil part these magnetic particles
actually within the oil so he got a
he got some samples from the the north
sea and this is an area i'll be talking
about a little bit
uh further later on we'll talk about his
phd work
um but i thought i'd just bring this in
now so we had a pure oil
sample from the north sea he wanted to
mix it
in something so we could measure it so
we mixed it in this kayla night clay
and you can see this is the background
signal and when we put the oil in the
can like clay measured
on a on a squid magnetometer and did low
temperature magnetometry
you can see we've got these different
minerals but the main thing to see is
that the magnetization is significantly
higher we've got values of
roughly 100 times higher in the oil
sample so the oil samples are able to
actually contain
the magnetic particle phases when you're
off this size
okay so one of the main things we've
been doing over
the last um five or six years is trying
to see if we can use
this magnetic signal to track migration
now micro hydrocarbon migration in oil
reservoirs is actually something that's
quite hard to do
and a lot of actually all companies and
et cetera they're just more interested
in fighting with the oil is they're not
always that particular about how the oil
actually gets there
now if you want to increase yield from
mature
oil fields and then it's
probably a very good idea to understand
the migration so rather than
having to explore and exploit new oil
fields and new parts of the world
you can keep um extracting oil from
existing oil fields so
understanding migration is quite a key
uh
problem uh to try and tackle so we've
kind of shown that nanoparticles can
probably migrate
and also there's lots of uh literature
to
suggest that the hydrocarbons themselves
as they pass through
create a diagenesis front which also
causes the formation
of magnetic minerals so these thromboids
that we see are obviously too big
to be uh transported with the
hydrocarbons
so because this um
got a bit longer here i thought i would
just talk about our first attempt to do
this which wasn't particularly
successful
and i'll tell you why i wasn't
successful then i'll talk about more
successful
study so this wessex basin which i
discussed already so this is where
london is and this is slightly down to
the
the west of uh on the south coast of
england to the west of london
and what we're interested in doing is
can we
take cores so can we take material from
this hydrocarbon system determine the
migration path independently using the
magnetics
and then try and determine the migration
path using
uh 3d seismic sorry
3d basin modeling based on 3d seismic
data that's the kind of idea so we get
an independent
estimate of migration can the magnetics
match up that's what we're trying to do
right so the first thing we need to do
is to get a location with core
and we was working we were working on
the wessex basins that was obviously the
first place to
that we thought we would try and we're
very lucky in the uk that
i don't know since when it's the 60s or
70 every single core that's been drilled
anywhere in the uk
on land or offshore half of it has to go
half of the core has to go to the
government and it's stored at the
british geological survey in nottingham
and as an academic we've got free access
to all of this so we can just
go up we can take samples it's a
fantastic resource we're very lucky to
have it
i know some other countries have this
but not all countries have this
this resource and so we have a picture
here on the left we have some sandstorm
which was from
not uh it's a water wet so there wasn't
any oil on this and you can see here
we've got oil stains you can see it
looks very very different
okay so this is uh so we go up there we
have all these different
um these where the different cores and
we get all these different materials
allows us to do
look at the uh the magnetism we also
have to
find an area where they've done the 3d
uh seismic data has been collected in
here just showing you the 3d seismic
data for this particular area that we're
interested in
now later on i'll be talking about how
we get to the magnetic results but we
use a suite of magnetic tools low
temperature high temperature and for
this particular study i just want to
jump straight into the results now this
was a particularly
it was quite a hard hard kind of study
and trying to interpret the data it was
quite complex and
in places it was uh quite difficult to
interpret but um
just taking the average of each of these
particular cores we're able to
kind of get a trend for the general
behavior now we'll be talking later on
about
how you get variations of magnetization
along the core but right here we just
talked about this
average behavior so we we think the oil
is coming out we know the oil is
formed that kim ridge is coming up and
then migrating to which farm
and we was kind of sure from the
magnetics that it doesn't go through
bushy farm that was previously thought
and actually kind of went around it
over in this region here we have so this
is the magnetite signal the yellow is
the
periodic signal the green is this mixed
response
over here it was quite complex and
difficult to interpret
but anyway we kind of thought for the
magnetics even though the result wasn't
clear that there was some sort of
migration power so the idea is could we
tie that
in with the uh 3d basin modeling
and this is the upheaval map for the
area and
some of you probably not very familiar
with these things i'm not going to go
into great detail on the 3d basin
modeling but basically
it's not a particularly uh it's not a
particularly great example of an
upheaval mate just it was very complex
and it was very difficult to do the
modeling
and even though there's a hint of a
migration path here
so this is the king ridge where it's
come up and this is the this is the
which farm where
we think the with the oil reservoir is
um it wasn't very clear from the
modeling and unfortunately it wasn't
it wasn't good enough to be a control
and the reason for that is not so much
in rabbi who is a phd student it was
more the fact
and his supervisors chose a location
that probably wasn't the best place to
test the theory on so here we have the
wessex basin
this is the area we're working in around
about here and it's very very complex
lots of uh inversions anti-clients
inclines it's a very difficult
place to work and probably not the best
place to test our migration
theory using magnetic so we decided to
try
simple locality and this is where
shoppies
phd is and we choose a place in the
north sea
and we've chosen this locality the tay
fan which has a very linear system so
the oil is being formed over here
and then it migrates along in a straight
line along this direction so we've kind
of got
a relatively simple geology we think and
we've got a nice linear simple system
it's a fill and spill chain this is kind
of what we
thought we go to and we've also got
access to lots of 3d seismic data and
good core coverage so that was our
reason for
attempting this area and so here just in
slightly more detail here this is the
oil is coming here here on the side and
moving along
in this direction and this is the
schematic of what it originally looked
like
so we're starting down here in the oil
is migrating up
the upper along this upper tail fan up
through here
okay and these are the various names of
various oil fields
in the north sea
okay so i'm going to show some seismic
data which
you probably don't you guys probably
don't really look at very much i'm not
going to talk too much about it it's
more just to show this is kind of the
system we're looking at
and we started we thought we had a nice
linear system so we started off looking
at the 2d seismic models
um the idea is the oil forms over here
and it moves up and migrates along here
unfortunately it was all getting stuck
on this salt dome
and of course the world isn't a 2d model
it's a 3d model
and rather than we couldn't in the model
get the oil to go over the salt dome but
of course in real world it just goes
around it okay so
using a 2d model doesn't always work so
we had to resort to 3d models
and the 3d models is really quite a lot
of work this is
the work the students have done with
their other supervisor alfreso
i'm not going to talk about the the 3d
basin modeling in great detail
just just going to show you the results
there's a lot of work going on to these
models
and here you can see this this is
the final model i'm going to be talking
about this later on but this is just the
starting point
so here we have the tay sandstone
here we have the predicted oil
accumulations and here we have the
migration pass this is what the 3d
models allows us to do
and we are running these solutions now
on the hp
just to show they look quite tricky to
do we're running them on the hbc
facilities
to actually get these uh solved
so that's the that's the basic modeling
aspect and of course we want to tie that
in with the
magnetics and we do the whole range of
the usual experiments low temperature
experiments
um now the low temperature experiments
students have limited access to mpms
because we
don't have an mpms we managed to get an
npms in january 2019
and yesterday our the engineer from
quantum design was there and he said
it's working but we've not had any data
from
in 18 months so it's been one big
disappointment getting the npms
luckily other people have been very uh
other places around the world be very
helpful in letting us get access to
their npms systems like
anu and the irm etc
so that the low temperature data is
really crucial to try and understand
what's going on
but as we all know magnetic data doesn't
rely on one particular measurement
relies on a whole range of different
types of measurements so
we we do a lot of high temperature
measurements high temp receptability
measurements which can be
difficult to interpret because the
minerals are altering as we
heat them up we also do a lot of
electron microscopy now the
the magnetizations are relatively weak
they're down at um
parts per hundred thousand maybe parts
per million so we can't really do
electron microscopy work
on the samples as they are we have to do
a magnetic extraction which obviously
potentially leads to issues because you
may be not extracting all the magnetic
minerals of interest
and then we're able to do some electron
microscopy and we're able to try and
differentiate between greg atom
or peritonite and identify minerals like
pyrite etc
so this is just we've got hundreds of
these uh examples of
measurements we've also been doing for
measurements but as the samples are
particularly weak it's quite difficult
to get
four measurements along with relatively
incomplete data sets for the fork data
but just to show the kind of typical
behavior that we get
and for this particular study shopee was
able to
summarize all the data these are the
different minerals that we
found um we identified the origins
whether they're the trital so
they're originally whether they formed
in the presence of hydrocarbons
um and whether so essentially whether
they're a background signal
or product of the hydrocarbons we also
get quite a lot of machemite
as we suspect a lot of the magnemite
comes from the cores being stored in air
for
potentially 30 years so those little
magnetite particles
get oxidized okay so those are the kind
of systems we're looking at so the
minerals that are particularly of
interest are the
cidarite and the gregite as we'll see in
the next couple of slides
so when we plot them on a map so this is
uh the area that we're looking at before
the gray area marks the area where we
have the 3d seismic data that's just why
that's just showing
the 3d seismic data area we have the the
wells and each of the wells has
different colors so the dark red is the
hydrocarbon producing wells
the the the slightly brighters of ready
orange ones here
these have got oil in them but maybe not
enough to actually go to full production
then we have the dry well core we've
only got one of these this
gives us our background signal this is
particularly important
because we need to know the background
signal of our rocks now
unfortunately oil companies don't drill
many background
cores because they're looking for
hydrocarbons so generally speaking you
don't get many
sort of dry wells we do get these
drywall cuttings sometimes like up here
this yellow one
unfortunately these cuttings tend to be
mixed up with drilling modern stuff so
it's they're often contaminated so you
can't really rely
on the drywall cuttings you really have
to rely on the drywall core
to get a fairly good background so we
think our background signal here is
magnetite okay so this is
then here this is magnetite here so here
we have the oil coming upwards and we've
kind of got
sharpies kind of colored this according
to the main mineralogy so this area here
is all kind of
mostly dark green so this means it's
cinderites mostly
and as we move along here we kind of
start getting so
equal numbers of of uh iron sulphides
and cellulite and then here we've got
much more iron sulfides so that's kind
of our
our trend now
let's just jump back to the 3d model
so our 3d model predicted these oil
accumulations
now it didn't actually match what we see
in the real world
and there was kind of a problem there so
um sharpie was trying so choppy was
doing this at the same time so it's kind
of iterative process they're not
supposed to be done independently but
it's done by the same person so clearly
the person has got both data sets in
their head
and what he noticed was that we a lot of
pseudoright where we potentially might
have
vertical migration so he associated
the sidorite with this protocol
migration so essentially when oil
as it rises up you get decompression
that releases
bicarbonate which has the potential
potential to
to form then they've got all this extra
carbon oxygen potential to form with the
iron
to form pseudorite you don't get that
when you're doing lateral migration so
he associated with this with vertical
migration and this
iron suffers with with um horizontal or
lateral
migration but there wasn't really in the
model itself there wasn't really
anywhere
for this vertical migration to occur so
he went back
and at the same time another student
mary was just starting her phd
and she had in her course in a similar
region very close to here
she had lots of injections essentially
bands of sandstone which are kind of
have gone through um the impermeable lab
above which allow the oil to migrate now
here's a picture of these injectors in
the cores
okay and you can see the scale here
these are 10 centimeters or so
right so the scale of this is probably
less than a meter or meter or less
now the depth of the depth we're working
at the seismic resolution is about
10 meters so essentially we've got all
these little injectites
that are too small to be seen with the
size mix but you can see them in the
cause and the mineral magnetism is
suggesting they should be there so
there's gonna a link there
and choppy went back and he had a look
at his seismic data in detail and he got
hints of potentially some injectites
in his seismic data and that only came
about because of the mineral magnetism
so the idea of having this independent
technique
we ended up using the magnetism to help
interpret and fully interpret
the 3d model so he put the injection
built his 3d model so put the injectors
into the 3d model
and lo behold they got something that
matches more what's going on in reality
so that was rather than using the 3d
basin to test
test the the mineral magnetic migrations
theory we ended up using them in my
mineral magnetic migration sort of ideas
to fine-tune
the the basin model which was
very pleasing for me um so here's kind
of a summary of what was going on
back to our 2d case so here we have the
the injectites over here we have this
migration going up here this forms
all the side right we saw the
predominant magnetic signal
signating all these cores and as it
transports along
we tend to get less sederites more iron
sulfide so we get all the way over here
the oil creeps through here we end up
with a a much more gragate or iron
sulfide like
signal now
you might say lateral migrations purely
gives an iron sulfide signal but also
we're running into this eye area where
it's getting quite shallow so now we
need to start thinking of fire
degradation
so as i said before biodegradation
happens due to bacteria at relatively
shallow
depths so relatively cool temperatures
below 80 degrees celsius
so over here we've got the oil vertical
migration forming
our acidorites and as it comes through
here it's coming into the zone where
we're starting getting lots of iron
sulfides but we also
this red here is an indication of the
so i should mention this this map here
is a is a graph
is the api gravity and the api gravity
is very strongly correlated with the
level of biodegradation so here we've
over the blue we've got
no uh biodegradable very low by
degradation and where it's red we've got
lots of biodegradation
it's a very crude way of getting the
biodegradation level
and you can see that we've got lots of
iron sulfides when it's lots of
biodegradation so
is it due to lateral migration or is it
due to biodegradation
now fortunately before that we had
another student
stacy who looked a lot at by degradation
in her
in her thesis and
she got samples from various places
around the world
um so we've got the alberta
tar sands columbia colombia indonesia
and the uk
and she did the usual magnetic analysis
i know running over time here a little
bit
uh but she also did a lot of organic
uh geochemistry so looking at
um fourier transform infrared
spectroscopy
and gas chromatography to try and
quantify the oil in these samples and
trying to understand the levels of
biodegradation
these graphs for some reason never have
units on there's always response versus
retention time i've asked
the the organic geochemist why they
never put units on is well there aren't
any units and i've never got a
clear answer to what the units are but
so before anyone criticized me for no
units i
would also like to know where the units
are on this particular graph
um this allows us to
plot the samples and sort by degradation
plot there's various ways of measuring
the
biodegradation we can see there's
various samples from the various
localities from over here where there's
almost
no biodegradation that very high levels
of biodegradation
uh the analysis uh of so for stacey for
her work she did a lot of
election microscopy we saw a lot of
these fanboys we also saw
evidence for microbe activity i mean she
associated this with
biodegradation and there is is some
evidence work but i think the
biodegradation is really happening on a
much smaller scale
than we're looking at in this particular
crystal here which is quite a large
crystal
and she was able to come up with a very
nice graph so we've got the two graphs
two independent ways of measuring by the
by degradation and these graphs are
essentially
the same even though they're plotted we
look
contrasting so the levels of
biodegradation on the left
one are going up as we go this way and
on the the right hand side is going down
and along here we have the magnetic
acceptability
so we just look at the one on the left
here so as biodegradation
increases this log because this is minus
is 10 to the minus six ten to the minus
five
the magnetization is decreasing right so
higher
biodegradation um lower magnetization
and she was interested in tying this in
to
the uh to this idea of doing
aeromagnetic surface so
she uh the idea that we came up with as
a biodegradation
leads to preferential removal of the
smaller magnetic particles so what we
found was that the grain size
distribution
also shifts so even though we reduce the
magnetization it's the very small
particles
are the ones that are removed first
preferentially leaving
the larger particles
now in the work that she does she came
up with lots of
all her work suggested that the
particles were left over with magnetite
and in the work that was done by shoppi
it came we came across that we actually
ended with lots of iron sulfide so it
seems to be a little bit of a
contradiction there however i think
this probably depends a lot exactly the
depth of which the biodegradation is
happening
um as you can see here from a paper from
andrew roberts
you can see that depending exactly where
we're on this graph
where they're in the soft sulfide
reductions on the iron reduction zone
we're going to get a different response
so i think with in the light of the work
that of shopee's phd thesis we need to
go back and revisit the biodegradation
work we did
with stacey so many years ago
so to be continued now i realize i kind
of run over time so
um i'm just going to skip this is no
point also quite so important this is
just about some of the micro related
modeling we've done on framboids that we
see
and then i also we also find this at the
fluid water contacts so the oil
water contacts and the gas contacts we
often get the spike in the magnetization
um so you're going down the core you get
these spikes and we're able to identify
the contacts using um
other techniques like looking at things
like porosity and we are still trying to
kind of
come get a coherent method for
explaining how
uh why you get this enhancement
so i'm just gonna go through those so
just to wrap it up so normally i would
leave a slide with conclusions but i
thought i would leave
the finishing slide to talk about
the work that we're currently doing so
still got three phd students i should
still
we've got three phd students working
this area so we're trying to look at can
magnetic migration work the analysis
that we've done does it work on a
reservoir scale so we've kind of
done it on a large scale hydrocarbon
system but can we do it on an individual
reservoir scale that's something
mariam's working on
we have another ph.d student joe and
he's looking at um
in the murray firth and he's got oil
from different sources and can we use
the mineral magnetism to try and
identify
where the oil has come from now we've
done a lot of work
looking at classic systems for
sandstones
and we want to see if we can apply some
of the things we've learned to
carbonates
and then again there's this all water
content thing which i touched on it was
very
and can we use this these are water
contacts
to identify paleo contacts if there's
been tilting of the reservoir and things
like that can we
can we use our knowledge of the magnetic
signal to do that
okay thanks very much for that that's
the end of the talk thank you for
listening
excellent thank you very much adrian
that was a really really interesting
talk and we can all thank adrian
uh via our virtual applause button um
that was really good um i'm sure we
probably have a few
questions um i can actually jump in
uh now with the question that we got in
the chat
while you were talking and this was from
uh william harbit orbit
um who asked how could reactive
geochemical processes including these
magnetic phases
impact and change the formation
permeability
so i think the so the formation
yes essentially i think i suspect that
most of the
magnetic minerals will not make much
difference to permeability
the only one that might do is is the
cineride because the ciderite tends to
cement and
we're trying to get a handle on how much
soda right there is there so most of the
magnetic minerals that we see
um the concentrations are very low
they're down in parts 100 000 parts per
million
whereas the ciderite is a slightly
higher concentration we think maybe it
may be one or two percent so
that could you're right that could
reduce the permeability of the rocks we
haven't actually something we haven't
really looked into but
yeah that's potentially an effect that
you should consider with the
and how prevalent are the thromboids um
with respect to
the smaller particles
um they are
it's one of those things you look at an
electron microscope and you get drawn to
the big fancy fanboys because they look
nice and a nice picture
but i think and it's hard to do proper
quantities for analysis on
on the electron microscope because the
concentration of the magnetic particles
is so low and we've done a magnetic
extract as well
so it's really hard to quantify them but
i would say they're not particularly
abundant i would say we do
see there's more individual particles
just kind of
dotted around and the framboids though
they are pretty a nice look at
um there's probably less of them um
yeah so they're probably not that common
yeah and one thing we did with the
modeling was to show that you really
need a lot because they
essentially give a multi-domain like
signal they you really need a lot of
framboids to actually
dominate a magnetic signal of a sample
you know you don't need that many single
domain particles or single vortex
particles individual particles to
dominate
the the the response in a fork diagram
cool so we have time for a few more
questions
well i'll write one one more um
on the uh the part where you did have to
go over
a little bit quickly we see this spike
in the magnetization at the
the interfaces um this is the oil water
interface i assume
yeah that's the oil yeah watercolor what
um what do you think is causing that
uh spike well if i just share my screen
again actually we've got a model uh
let me just so
um when we did fork analysis across
that i mean we have a very few samples
and we did pca analysis and if they've
had stocks listing you'll probably tell
me off for
doing pc analysis with so a few points
but
um you can you don't really need to do
pizza you can see quite clearly the fork
diagrams actually at the
contact themselves are very very
different to the sort of background
signal so i know it's not the best fork
diagram but
because the samples are very weak but um
you can see there's a quite distinct
population of slightly larger grains
than
what you see in the sort of general
background
signal and we came up with some models
and one of the models we came up is that
the particles
are formed at the top and then they kind
of drop down and they
drop down and kind of get stuck on the
on the oil water contact layer and it's
not really a sharp contact it's more of
a
zone um another idea that's not actually
in here is i i kind of
i'm quite in favor of the idea that
there's um
at this particular zone you've got lots
of hydrocarbons and you've also got
suddenly mixing with all this water so
you've got a different chemist
from different kind of chemistry and
we're quite keen to do some
thermodynamic modelling of the exact
conditions that you get at this
context i think it's something that's
just being formed
due to you know these optimum conditions
at the particular
at this context or something being
formed in situ rather than
in this model here where we've got these
little particles essentially falling out
onto the contact itself
excellent so we have uh
time for another quick question from
anyone okay well
i've got a quick question uh if i may
yeah richard so um yeah adrian at the
start there was all sorts of nice things
about
how this was going to help in the
utilization of you know
mature oil fields um
so do you think you really have
something to say on that
uh i think so i think um
the stuff on the wall water contacts is
quite new
i think that might help i think this
vertical electric migration is something
that hasn't
really been uh has never been done
before
and if we can use the techniques to do
that
to identify to help the basic modeling
then
um there is a potential to link up
with various companies and we have
given these presentations to
a number of oil companies and they have
shown interest
to a certain degree but it hasn't
been taken up fully but there is an
interest in the sort of work that we're
doing
um so yeah i mean especially in places
like the north sea i think there's a
scope for this yeah because it's a very
mature
um system but yeah we haven't made the
jump yet between what we've been doing
and actually implementing it in
in a commercial sense and
a lot of the stuff that we've just done
with the i think the most exciting thing
is the difference between the vertical
lateral migration
um this work has only really come out
and you know it's not even
published yet it's still accepted or
impressed
so yeah
sounds like an industrial case student
to me
yeah uh well we have we are i mean as i
said um al fraser is one of the guys i
work with
he has been working industry for 30
years so he has a lot of contact so he's
quite he's very well connected and knows
um who to talk to about trying to uh
use what we've learned and actually
apply it rather than
just to you know publish papers well
publishing papers is not bad either but
some of this stuff can actually uh can
eventually
can benefit uh recovery and things
it would be good to get our oil from
um as you said areas which are already
being explored and
not have to go and dig up new places
yeah
as we have one one other last question
that's
in the chat from sue and she was just
asking is there enough magnetite
for a magnetic signature at the surface
and
um is there how does that compare to
this or 4d
gravity surveys
is there enough to get at the surface
signature we would love that to be a
magnetic anomaly but we're talking about
samples that we are struggling to
measure in a squid magnetometer
so the answer is not
really significant levels
you know some of the nuances that we're
seeing not getting these very high
levels that would lead to clear magnetic
anomalies at the surface um there might
be scenarios where you
do have that but in the systems we've
been looking at
the concentrations have been quite low
um
how does this compare with 40 gravity i
could also these seismic surveys um
i don't really have an answer to the
gravity surveys
um as i said the magnetization
the concentrations looking at so small
so even though we've got magnetic
particles there that the concentration
is so small it doesn't probably really
add
significantly to any density that you're
going to pick up in a gravity survey i
wouldn't have thought
um we've been trying to we've you know
we've not been thinking the gravity of
seismic surface we've been thinking of
can we actually
um relate this to you know an
aeromagnetic survey would be the obvious
thing
but then we were thinking more if this
was going to be used
it would be used more at the level of
people collecting um
cores and analyzing cause that's the
soft level we're looking at just because
the concentrations
are quite low i
i'm not sure is my mic working
can you hear me oh okay sorry no i was
talking about the
the 40 gravity surveys where people are
tracking the migration of the
oil interface and i'm just wondering if
that
um has been i guess it hasn't been
looked at with the mag because the
concentration is too low but i'm
thinking of the squid magnetometers that
were
you know we're using in south africa on
airborne flights
um
it's just very speculative so in
imperial we do a lot with big group
working with 40 sizes so i guess it's
very similar to the
4d gravity service and they do see the
migration no we haven't
we haven't tried to link that together
and that's something we probably
could do uh working with people and yeah
who do do
the well do 40 seismic but it's a
similar sort of idea
trying to track migration we haven't
tried to link that together we've been
doing
this 3d data and then using um a suite
of schlamberger
programs to predict the migration path
that's have been our policy but yeah i
think maybe
trying to tie this in with some 4d data
would probably be
a good idea and something we haven't
explored yet but maybe we should
do i still sounds very interesting yeah
yeah i mean i i i yeah i mean i really
would like it to be able to you know use
a squid and
switch magnetometer and fly it behind uh
a plane and pick up the magnetic
anomalies due to this and
maybe on very large scale features you
can see that but there's sort of
the kind of smaller features that we've
been looking at you know there's great
depths looking at features
which you know these inject types which
are you know quite small
um we're not i the magnetization really
is quite low
i think it's going to be difficult to
apply this routinely to
um in in some sort of aeromagnetic
survey or even a
a drone survey which is you know
obviously much closer i think
it obviously depends as well on the
depth of the hydrocarbons of course
a lot of the stuff that we've been
looking at in the north sea is um
you know it's under several kilometers
of water under several kilometers of
rock
so you know we're quite a long way from
the source
if we're you know doing a survey of some
sort of
of some sort of survey excellent
um well thank you very much adrian um
we'll wrap it up
for today so i wanted to uh thank adrian
once again
um for a really interesting talk and
just before we all go just a quick
um a quick reminder
that the seminars um are available
online
um through the youtube channel the magic
youtube channel so thank you again to
earth ref and the magic team for hosting
that for us
um and in the coming weeks and months we
have uh
several several more speakers lined up
so i'm looking forward to
seeing you all again here uh in the
coming weeks
um and as always i want to uh you're
welcome
any feedback uh comments and criticisms
uh please just drop us an email
uh with any thoughts and thank you once
again everybody for
joining us today for another magnet
seminar
thank you thanks