okay thank you everyone to um come to
the
magnet uh seminar uh
today is gonna be um it's gonna be
um by saya arquero campunzano
she's going to present the evolution of
the germany field for the last three
millennia
from the iron age and shock 2k
reconstructions
from valentine iron age and south
atlantic anomalies
sayo is she's based in madrid
as a seminal format as usual we have 25
minutes presentation
um then we will have about 10 15 minutes
for question discussion we're always
flexible
you can always write your questions in
the textbook
uh it's an informal environment so if
you want to go
don't worry about it you can go the
seminar recorded and there'd be some
time at the end of the seminar to catch
up
this will not be recorded so for now i
would like to
give sayoah the the ball
start the presentation okay
okay did you see my screen yes thank you
okay and the pointer yes perfect
okay
so thank you very much uh hi everybody
and thank you for this opportunity to
present our work
about the emergence and evolution of the
geomagnetic field for the last three
millennia
and the this this work is about
emergence and evolution of two uh
magnetic anomalies
the eleventh in iron age anomaly and the
south atlantic anomaly
from global reconstruction of the
paleomagnetic field
this work has been developed for the by
the group of palu magnetism of the
completeness university of madrid and
i'm going to present the main results
so first we have to know
who our principal actresses are the
levantine iron age anomaly is a large
positive anomaly
related to very high values and fast
variation of the humanities field
intensity
at the earth surface between 1000 bc and
700 bc
in the levantine region according to
2016. in the
in 2017 sar ital observed
prominent high virtual actual moment
values in the chain frame of the
levantine ironate anomaly
in orange in these figures not only in
the 11th region but also in caucasus and
for many times but much lower values in
greece
and bulgaria in the period between
500 bc and 200 bc
in green in the figure we also serve as
a compiled intensity height
you know in all regions and
related in this case with a fast
circular variation in europe
so um so and at
the continental scale regarding the
first height that is to say the eleventh
in iron age anomaly
they conclude that a non-vital feature
is required to explain the pile
intensity difference
in the interval between 1000 bc and 700
bc between kaukasu levant
and the balkans also in this year
in 2017 davis and constable
proposed a spike model to explain these
high values at their surface
in a very quick way they insert a spike
into the radial component of the
geomagnetic field at the cormenter
laundry here in the a
figure in the 11th region and in
the texas region and in this spikes
modeled like
um fisherman misses probability
distribution
and they model the geomagnetic field
with these characteristics
the model shows that instantaneous
surface expression this is intensity
at their surface the model shows that
the instantaneous surface expression of
high
intensities must extend over abroad
geographical area estimated to be around
60 degrees of longitude they also
suggest that the levantine
magnetic spike reflects an intense and
localized
neuroequatorial flux patch on the
current
boundary emerged from within the core
and subsequently the cage
in the same place or grew in the
equatorial region and migrated northward
and westward for that part
of the for your part the south atlantic
anomalies are region with
low values of geomagnetic field
intensity
at the air surface it covers the most
part of south america
south atlantic ocean and south africa
its internal
origin is associated with the presence
of reversal flux
patches at the cormental boundary from
1840 but they could be older
here we can see the intensity at the
earth at their surface
and the radial component of the radial
of
the magnetic field at the core mental
boundary
in january 2020 from cow's model
so from a model derivative by
satellite data and instrumental data the
white line control
gives an idea about the aerial extent of
the south atlantic
anomaly at the present days and with the
black square
we see the two reversal flux patches
here and
here located beneath seoul america and
south africa
commonly associated with this or
internal origin of the south atlantic
anomaly
in detail we can see this movie uh
with the evolution of the intensity at
the air
on the its surface and the radial
component of the geomagnetic field at
the cormanter boundary from 1600
a.d until our days
the present days and we can see very
well the relationship between
this anomaly their surface and this
reveals
reversal flux patches at the core mantle
boundary
but the question here is what is the
real age of this
reversal flux patches and in tour of the
south atlantic anomaly
in the few last in the few years in the
in the last few years sorry several
works point out that
they could be older than we thought
um in this presentation i'm going to
talk about the results provided by our
group the last year
which proposed this is a spoiler that
the reversal flux patches
cause emerge around 950 a.d
so to understand better uh
the nature of these anomalies the the
live element in ionic anomaly and the
south atlantic anomaly
we must start from palu magnetic data
we can see here this partial and
temporal distribution of the
archmagnetic and volcanic database
coming from
your media 50 the last version for the
last
3 000 years and we see for example in
the time distribution
panel shows uh this panel shows a
decrease in the number of declination
and inclination
values during the first millennia before
chris and not so important in the case
of the intensity and in
space we can't see very well that the
data are greatly
concentrated in the northern hemisphere
but there is an incorporation of
intensities from africa and from south
america
[Music]
improves the spatial coverage in the
southern hemisphere
inhibition new data coming from the
ivarian peninsula prior to late ironic
times an epoch very poorly constrained
up to date
and very interesting because the
levantine iron 8
anomaly times have been also
incorporated in this database
from this figure we can also see another
effect the effect of
applying quality criteria on the data
light colors
represents quality data and dark colors
represent
the rest of the poly magnetic data so
we can see that the intensity is the
parameter most affected with a very
scarce number of quality data in light
course here
but what means quality data for us
we use a quality criteria based on
uh three three principal aspects
the first one is the type of material
analyzed we choose uh ultramagnetic and
volcanic material for the analysis of
these
um rapid anomalies in the case of the
levantine especially in the case of the
levantine iron h anomaly
the number of specimens that we consider
is a minimum of four specimens and the
laboratory protocol
used for the estimation of the pali
intensity is also considerate
we we required that the quality that the
quality data correspond to intensity
values coming from experiments
based on the teleetellier type methods
including ptrm sex and
in the case if they were obtained from
potentially highly anisotropic
archaeological
objects such as pottery or ceramics
the trm anisotropy correction is also
required
this is not the case for example for
volcanic data
so unfortunately there is currently not
enough quality data to obtain a robust
global reconstruction of the geomagnetic
field using only the quality data
for the last three thousand years for
this reason we propose the use of the
complete database
not only the quality data but we use we
propose to use an appropriated within a
scheme
to do that the most difficult problem is
to establish the relative ratio between
the weight of the quality data and the
other parliamentary data
to quantify this radio we constructed
different geomagnetic field
models using different waviness schemes
from 1 to 100
with ratios from these models
we calculated declination inclination
and intensity data at the same location
than those corresponding to the quality
data in the original database
we then compare the prediction of the
model with the real data and we
calculate
the the root mean square error
for different regularization given by
different damping parameters alpha and
tau
here we can see different traits of
curves
and and we see very well
in this knee point in the trade of cars
around 10 so
this this uh wasting scheme
this means that the quality data waived
times more than the rest of the
parliamentary data is the best
compromise between
the modeling fitting and the proposed
wasting scheme
so with this consideration um
we generate two different reconstruction
of the magnetic field
for modeling purposes we followed
the same approach as the work of corte
and constable
2005 and the spherical harmonic analysis
technique in space
and the penalized cubic via splines in
time
we select the maximum degree of the
harmonic expression
equal to 10 and we fix the temporal note
points every 25 years in order to
estimate model and certain things that
was how technique is
used following curtin concept on
constable
2008 and
we calculate 5 000 models
by perturbing the input data with two
random distribution
allows and distribution centering the
mean directional and intensity values
with a standard deviation equal to the
uncertainty of the
data and a homogeneous distribution
center in the main age
of the data with an amplitude equal to
their certainty
so the inversion was regularized also at
the current mantle boundary by means of
the damping parameters alpha
and tau and with this consideration we
have generated these two reconstruction
of the geomagnetic fields
though ionate from 1300 bc to
0ad and south2k
from 100 bc to
1900 the first one is
uh it's generated
to a study the levantine ionization
normally and the second one
is generated in order to study the
south atlantic and normally the
emergence and evolution
so from south carolina we see
maps of intensity at the air surface in
different years
during the first years of the model we
see moderate values of the intensity
around over the 11th region around 60
microtesla
around 900 bc
high values of the intensity are around
micro teslas are observed with an
apparent migration
and northwest was from 700 bc
and 550 and around 300 bc
we see lower values again
so
the observed high intensity at their
surface uh
corresponding with the levantine
ionization normally can be associated to
a flux patch of normal polarity here
of the radial component of the
geomagnetic field at the cormenter
boundary
and we see we see
at about 1000 bc an isolated normal flux
patch is located below the eleventh
rayon here
that grows up in c2 and then
it expands towards the northwest the
northwest
while decreasing intensity i try to
put in the movie again so
we see this section expansion
towards the northwest while decreasing
intensity
at around 700 b speed center is located
in europe and from 300 f
300 bc the then our normal flux path
is vanishing in c2 so due to the
non-dipolar nature of the
levantine iron age anomaly we have
also analyzed the non-dipolar terms of
the magnetic field
and we observe more or less the same
evolution
of this normal patch normal flux
patch at the cormentel boundary with
immigration northwest were from
1000 bc to 700 bc
okay for salk 2k
reconstruction we can see the emergence
of the
reversal flux patch related to the south
atlantic anomaly
here we can see the evolution of the
radial component of the hormonal
boundary for different times
as we can see an area of reverse
polarity located beneath
india penetrated from the magnetic
equator
and move away south west
from 1080 to 100
1380 and
in mil in 1700 kd
it was isolated beneath south africans
50 was worth until reaching the south
atlantic ocean in 1980 so
here according to the international
humanitarian reference field
the south reversal flux patch
is divided into two different uh
reversal patches one located in
patagonia
and the second one located under south
africa here
and here so return studies indicate that
nowadays
the patagonian er erase p is vanishing
and the south african era is p
is reinforcing this is we can
see this feature here
our new reconstruction does not have
enough resolution to establish if the
strong
westward movement of this thousand
reversal flux patch observed between
to 1900 ad
corresponds to a real movement of a
single or too close reversal flux
buckets
in addition to the this reversal flux
patch related to the south atlantic
anomaly we can see another
reversal flux patch located in the
northern hemisphere
here with this n
in the in the figure so
this uh reverse efflux patch was also
identified by another author
by other authors terranovital in 2015
around 1500 a.d and our studies suggest
that the emergence of this n
r a p occurred between 1080
here and
1 4 180
here when a tongue of reversal polarity
penetrated from the magnetic equator
towards the north atlantic
and this um this n earth hp
drift northeast and appeared clearly
isolated
around 1680
we need the united kingdom and the
scandinavian region
where it's remaining up to the date up
to now
uh this uh this north reversal flux
patch is vanishing
at present times as we can see
with uh with these figures given by the
international humanitarian reference
field
so this intriguing asymmetry
antisymmetric evolution of the
north reversal flux patch related to the
south reversal flux patch
to be investigated in more detail in
future
and finally in order to evaluate the
non-diaper contributions to
these uh reversal flux patches we have
also calculated the
the royal component of the magnetic
field at the core material boundary for
different order so
consider dipole quad adding quadruple
octopul and we saw maximum degree equal
to six
in this figure we saw the results
obtaining
four one thousand seven hundred kd when
the
south progressive flux patch is isolated
so we can clearly observe
that both north and south patches are
mainly due to harmonic degrees greater
than three
but in the case of the south reverse and
flux patch it's very important also the
quadrupon octopus contributions because
they break the symmetry of the dipole
venezuela africa in the case of the
north reversal flux patch
is exclusively due to non-dipole terms
of higher degree as we can see here in
the in this figure
so to conclude
yes to two points or two thoughts
the first one is that it seems to the
use of an appropriate
appropriate waiting scheme based on data
accuracy
seems to improve our understanding of
the path of the geomagnetic field
and the second one is something that we
know very well
is that we need more data more data to
analyze features of our
magnetic field and in particular to
analyze in detail the emergence and
evolution of this
of these anomalies so thank you very
much for your attention
thank you sayo let's give her a good
round of applause
um so we have
a couple of questions already in the
chat box
one is from lisa and she is concerning
the data selection she's asking what do
you do
about cooling rate corrections when
you're selecting in this case we don't
use the cooling rate corrections only
the anisotropy correction because it's
not very
clear the the real
uh influence of this uh of this um
cooling rate correction in in all the
time
i know in all type of data so in this
case we prefer to use
only the the this other earth
this other criteria
lisa do you have something to add
oh i mean if if you look for perfect
data you'll get
maybe one data point so i understand
it's just
it it can be a larger effect than
anisotropy and it's just
we don't know how to do it so i was just
asking
thank you okay um so that we have
another question from
andre kosterov and he asked can you
estimate
a deviation of field direction from the
expected type of values due to the
levantine anomaly
uh sorry can you repeat anita yeah sorry
can you estimate a deviation of the
field direction from the expected dipole
values
due to the eleventh time renegot
normally
in this case we we
center our study in the intensity
so yes we analyze also the directional
part of the
geomagnetic field but in with this
detail i
am analyzing the the intensity
but it's interesting because in the last
year
um new directional data
from from germany um
has been published so
it's interesting also to study the
evolution of the direction
in these elements
okay thank you
any other questions from the audience
andrei says
thank you
no more questions
well then thank you very much for your
presentation oh you have a question
i guess this is just a a comment really
in terms or a question in terms of
how do you think that the uh the
resolution of the data
uh that's available in in the levant
region and the surrounding areas
how does this spatial and temporal
resolution how do you think that
actually influences
uh what you're seeing in your models and
you know how much of an effect
does the model smoothing have
yes this is an interesting question in
the case of the
south south
2k we use
only the arcmagnetic volcanic data
also in the last year in 1980
and if you compare with the data with
the
model with the international humanities
reference field
that use only instrumental data and
satellite data we see
that it's very similar so yes of course
in the in earlier times
this influence is very important and
this is the reason also
to do this kind of criteria quality
before the model in
the modeling procedure and we also
filter
considering other statistical parameters
not only the quality of the data in
terms of
number of specimens on number or another
type of material
or laboratory protocol we also filter in
observe for for example the the alpha
95 and they were associated with
the intensity so yes
yes it's it's important this kind of
analysis
previews the the generation of the model
yes
but this is interesting the comparison
between
these two plots i think that's very real
i want to obtain the same result with
the archaeomagnetic and volcanic data
with instrumental and and satellite data
so
so i have a question um because you're
using
geomegea you don't don't even
have the most recent most of the data
for the levantine
irony which was published later
including the georgia
you refer to so um
maybe you should supplement those data
with the stuff that's in magic which is
much more
complete um uh and secondly
i would love to put shaw q into
pmagpi but i don't have
access to elsevier journals because i'm
at a university of california
and i believe it must be in your
supplemental
um is it is it in the supplemental uh
um material i can send you
if you want i can send the paper and the
supplementary material
and everything you want yeah put it
someplace where it's
open like in yes yes also in the
in the white side of the paleo magnetic
group
i i think that it's a good place to put
these these models and these
this code urda where where kathy
puts all of her models um
just to collect them somewhere so we can
have them
use them um uh and uh nice work thank
you
thank you very much lisa
thank you lisa for the for the question
it's really important
for all of us to share the data so yes
of course we can collaborate in the best
and
more consistent and clear way possible
we can
um so we have a question
in the chat from anik maybe any sugar
i don't know i i saw some differences
between your maps
of br at the corman's boundary
and those published by teranova
teranova do you think do you have some
explanation sorry
yes because in this case we include
uh more data than in the terranovital
2015 uh publication
so especially in the south atlantic and
the
in south africa and so in south america
so this is a different this inclusion of
new data here
okay thank you
uh kathy has a question
you can go ahead and meet yourself
yes a nice presentation hi i'm curious
if you made a model where you
didn't down weight the data that you
considered to be of low quality
and how that would compare with what you
ended up with
uh where exactly cathy sorry
so um you you showed us this slide where
you
evaluated what down waiting the data
that you could
low quality yeah and and i'm wondering
if you
looked at the results from not down
weighting
things and yes with what you ended up
with
yes we we generate also a model
considering
this wasting ratio equal to one
that is the absence of this quality
the weighting scheme and we
we we see we saw
difference in the especially in the
south atlantic
part in the in the emergence of these
in the observation of this evolution of
the
reversal flux patch because the south
africa
and south america data have
uh our quality data and they
are very scared so the the influence of
the
this quality data increase a lot when
you consider
this weighting ratio and you observe
better this this evolution but we
we can see also the evolution with the
with the the other model but
it's not so clear that when we consider
the
this weight in a scheme so
advent we in yes if
i i i can share
all these um models and also
this this other model is present in the
supplementary material of this paper
so so yes in the
next future i want to share
all the coefficients gauss coefficients
in order to
put all free and
yes and share with the community
that would be great and so just to be
clear the waiting is the only way the
weighting of quality versus not good
quality is the only way that you
include the uncertainty in the
observations you don't weight them by
the uncertainties assigned by the
original data providers yes
we consider the uncertainty of the data
only in the bootstrap method and
and we when we filter the data
uh after this waiting scheme in the
sense that
we we have uh done this waiting scheme
in order to
classify the quality of the data but
based on different a different way
and in the classical filters that we use
for example consider the
error of intensity data we filter in
order to
not underestimate or overestimate the
some data and these kind of things we
also do this before the
the the modeling process so
we include all these and the waiting
skin is included in the
story because he is having that
here we include the weighting skin like
a waste
mattress
[Music]
with ones and tens
depending on the on the quality data
thank you thank you thank you
we have another question in the chat box
it's from joe stunner
and he asks how do you test these
reconstructions
what predictions might you have make
that
we as data producers could try to check
i can repeat so
how do you test these reconstructions
that's the question
so what prediction might you make that
we
as the data producers could try to check
okay
the test of these reconstructions
are okay
for example no here no
we usually they calculate the estimation
of the root mean square compare
in comparison for the the model uh
data with the original database and we
calculate the root mean square
and this is the test that we use
if this um this a root mean square
error is very close to one
we consider that the model is uh
is doing a well work
okay thank you joe do you want to
ask something else
well i was just yeah curious if we
you know can can use these i mean
obviously we can get predictions at
different locations and try to see
how well different types of data might
reproduce
what you expect based on these
reconstructions
um if there's things in progress
especially data that's not say um
within the model so you know can we use
sedimentary records as ways of
testing what you might expect
yes yes i understand yes i i see your
point yes
we can in this case we don't
um calculate this kind of
test so we only calculate the root minus
query like
the previous way that i mentioned
but yes if you with new data
you can see if these models
works well it's for me to be honest i
think that for example if you uh
increase the number of data of quality
data in variance for example
here in the mediterranean region
where these data are not very quality
data
and it's possible that this model though
doesn't work very well here but
depends on the on the date this is the
reason why i
i think that it's very important to
increase the number of aluminated data
and also equality
equality data so
yes okay thank you
i just wanted to follow up on joe's
comment uh
if you want to make a comparison with
the sedimentary data
one of the issues that uh would be
important would be for the sediment
data gatherers to provide an estimate of
the
temporal resolution in the sedimentary
data
because if there's smoothing as a result
of the
uh remnants acquisition then you
wouldn't expect these models to agree
that well
because they just make predictions that
will be scattered about the sediment
curve so this is something
that uh that we actually tried to
incorporate we incorporated in the gtf
100k model
uh the idea that once you when you make
a prediction you have to take account of
the remnants acquisition process
in order to get some kind of accurate
result and we actually built that into
the modeling process
uh to allow for that in there so
uh sediment data collectors that we
really need to know that
sounds like a challenge
thank you for for uh this point i would
follow up also on lisa's uh comment of
before that
another good thing that we as data
producer can do
is make the original data available so
that yeah
you can you can have for instance as a
sedimentary sequence you have depth
your age where the age
came from in centimeter wide can in the
near future of
far future we can always reconstruct
uh maybe a new age model compared to
what we did 10 years ago or something if
that makes sense
yeah yes yes so we i completely agree
with you
hi i would have a question too hi
for this nice presentation i was
wondering somehow you have controlled
the quality of the dating of your data
i mean how reliable is the dating
because very often we have very
high quality data and excellent
laboratory results but the dating is not
so reliable
i am afraid that's often the case for
both volcanic rocks and
um magnetic material so i don't know
the way to control the reliability of
the dating yes
in the in this model i
i must say that we only
use a filter of the uncertainty of
the age consider a 2050
years like the maximum uncertainty
of age that we consider well so
for us then the data that we
use in these value magnetic
reconstructions
only consider the data with an
uncertainty of h
lesser than 2 500
years yes of course then
the best solution is to see to
prove to to see in detail
every day every day and
yes and if the the dating is
well or not or what problems
there are yes of course but in the case
of the
these models we use only this filter
thank you thank you thank you thank you
thank you we have one uh
one uh question from elisa in the chat
how does the shop compare
to the chinese data of kaya
from china we use the kaiata
data in these in this
reconstructions so it's included in fact
if we see
going to 2015 so there's more from china
and so it would
okay but we can see for example this
this patch
at the cormantel boundary that's
interesting because
we don't see if there is some connection
between these
two normal flux patches so
in the case of the levantine iron age
anomaly
so it's something that we we want to
to investigate in detail in the future
and this is due to this
kinetic data
it's tsai not kai i'm sorry
sorry i i cannot
speak in chinese
okay well thank you very much to all
i think for today we can wrap up
and um another big round of applause for
sayo for representation
thank you very much i'm gonna share the
screen
with you for the last
[ __ ] okay can you see my screen
sorry okay so just to uh
conclude our um our seminar today
uh we have some uh um information for
you
the video this recording and pass
recording are now available
on this website at this link which we
shared already with you it's on the
airdraft magic database you know
it can be citable through f as well
as a schedule we have the next uh
seminar will be the 25th of november it
will be by
abdul kiyatema and
and then december we will have to have a
break there is
going to be agu for about 10 days and
there's going to be christmas
so we are going to take a break and and
then for 2021 we are looking for
speakers
so if anyone wants to volunteer or
volunteer somebody else it's
um everybody is welcome um feedback
ideas criticism are always welcome to me
greg um
yeah and then thank you very much to all