for coming uh to today's uh magnet
seminar this is the
fifth in our series so we're going
strong and we've had some
uh fantastic support from our community
so uh
thank you all very much and today we
will have
uh kathy whaler from the university of
edinburgh
talking to us about the uh 2016 pacific
jerk and core mantle boundary flows
derived from
uh swarm data but before we begin that
just a a quick rundown for those of you
who haven't attended one of these
seminars
um our presentations will be about uh
20 to 20 uh 25 to 30 minutes long
and i kindly ask that you keep your
microphones mediated so that
background noise such as babies
screaming and crying
doesn't interrupt the seminar um
at the end of the the presentation we
will have
10 to 15 minutes for questions
you can raise your hand via zoom and we
can we'll invite you to unmute and ask
your question
if you don't want to ask an oral
question
please just type it into the zoom chat
and add the no mic uh quote to it
and then either myself or one of my
co-hosts will
read out the question uh for you
and as usual we're always busy so um
please just uh leave if you have to and
we all have life going on in the
background
and at the end of the seminar um we will
have a small chance to catch up and
socialize with everybody
and i should state that at the end of
the seminar when we have this little
networking socializing
uh the recording will be stopped so it's
only the seminar
and the um question and answer session
uh that will be recorded
um and so without further ado i will
hand over to our
uh presenter for today which is kathy
whaler from the university of edinburgh
[Music]
thanks very much greg um i'm hoping i'm
sharing my screen now
and you can see my presentation is that
right
uh not at the moment right
um
[Music]
share screen aha let's try this one
is that any better
yeah that's that's perfect you can see
your screen now okay
right first of all thanks very much for
the opportunity
to speak today secondly this is really
just um
a brief update to a presentation that i
gave at the
virtual eg meeting so apologies to for
those of you
who were present at that and
just one other small update um i'm
informed my co-authors that the jerk is
actually very specifically in 2017
so i've just changed that uh date from
2016 that was in the abstract to 2017
here
so let's see if i can there we go
outline i'm just going to cover where
we've got to
fro to be at this point um
in the research i'll talk a little bit
about the data
then i'll talk about the inversions that
i did
to obtain core surface flows in terms of
the models and how well they fit the
data
and then i'll move on specifically to
the pacific jerk
before including and just to say that
this is
uh really quite a nice um
i mean related to the very first talk in
this series by chris davis when he was
looking at very rapid
changes in field direction and looking
at the
field dynamics itself and i'm going to
do something slightly different look at
all three components of the magnetic
field from current
observations and think about the core
surface flow
that might explain them
so what i'm going to use is virtual
observatories or vos
and these are a way of reducing large
quantities
of satellite data to estimates of
magnetic field quantities
at a set of target points and as a
function of flight time
so what we're trying to do by this
process is to mimic the time series that
you obtained from
ground observatories so what
one uses to produce a vo estimator are
data within a vertical cylinder whose
axis
passes through the target point and then
those data
are reduced to values at the target
point using a potential representation
of local
potential representation i'm not going
to go into any of the details of that
here
um but just to comment that the dtu
group my co-authors have made several
key improvements to the
vo methodology this includes
and this is going to be the focus today
producing spatial gradients of the field
in addition to the magnetic field and
time derivatives of both the field and
the field gradients
so previously i've demonstrated that the
surface sv gradient as well as the esv
vo estimates can be used to infer core
surface flow
and uh shown that the residuals are less
biased including in
sorry indicating less contamination of
the data by external fields
this was definitely a problem with some
of the earlier
vo estimates and by doing a lot of work
the dtu
group have overcome a lot of those
issues
and i've shown that the resolution is
better for gradient data so i will show
um that we can use these gradient data
to produce the core surface flows and i
will i have got a slide to show about
the resolution but i'm not going to talk
today about
the residuals because of lack of time
so these vo estimates are derived from
sums and differences of the observations
along
and across track from the satellite data
and they're reduced to a central point
using a cubic potential description
which is one of the enhancements that
dtu group have made and
rather than producing monthly values
which is what we typically get from
observations they're using they're
producing four monthly values so that
each virtual observatory volume
is well sampled so we don't have biases
from the satellite orbits during the
period that's being studied
and then simple annual differences of
the field estimates provide
secular variation estimates and
alongside all of this process you can
get
reliable uncertainties so the inversions
that i've been done again
i've done they're going to be weighted
by the uncertainties
and the optimum arrangement of vo's
turns out to be something like 300 so
i'm going to be using
300 equally spaced vios and in fact i'm
going to be using 298 because we don't
use gradients from the
polar um positions and then the
search range i the the diameter of those
cylinders
is 700 kilometers and the correction
that have also
helped with improving these estimates is
to remove the crustal field
remove the external and its induced
field
and reduce um remove the ionospheric
plus its induced
field estimate as well as part of the
processing chain
and here is an example from these 300
virtual observatories
of one of the secular variation gradient
time
series so this is the time derivative
of the radial component in the radial
direction
and you'll be seeing the other five
independent components
later on so the red dots on the screen
here
are the positions the virtual
observatories they don't look equally
spaced here but that's just the
projection that's been chosen
and the blue dots either side of those
red dots are the time
series so you can see the kind of
variation and then in the bottom left
here
is the um scale so this is 20 pico
teslas per kilometer
per year and the time span is 2014 to
about 23
20 19. okay and as i said these are four
monthly estimates
and the black ellipse here we're going
to be looking at the fits
to the data at this virtual observatory
a little bit later on
um the 2017 pacific jerk
um i should have pointed this out of
course you can see that there's really
quite a sudden
change in this particular component in
the pacific region
at about the middle of that time series
which means it is about 2017.
okay and you can also see that in the
secular variation data themselves so
here data from
honolulu observatory the radio
the north south and the east-west
component of the magnetic field there or
sorry the secular ocean there
so now in nanoteslas per year and again
you can see this very
sudden change in around 2017
and certainly these two components and
in some extent also into the
in the fight components as well as the
second variation
so this is a locally um well-defined
feature
and i'm showing just the observatory
data here but you can also see in the
secular variation
vo data as well
so what kind of flows do we need to
explain
these changes the way we do this is we
assume the magnetic field is frozen into
the fluid at the top of the outer core
that means that we are assuming magnetic
diffusion is negligible
and as a result the field lines track
the flow which i've tried to illustrate
in this
little slide so we've got two times t1
here
and t2 here this black line here is the
core mental boundary
and we're looking at a cross section
through it so here's the out liquid
outer corner here's the mental above
and these red and blue lines here are
the field lines that thread the core
metal boundary so here the field is
leaving the core here it's entering the
core and i've imagined
a flow pattern underneath so because
uh field lines are tied to the parcels
of fluid
um on the core side as the fluid moves
it drags the field lines along with it
so if we've got a simple flow like this
it's just going to move
the pattern around so it's going to
drift the pattern between
time t1 and time t2 in the lower half
here we've got a different kind of
scenario where i'm imagining converging
flow at the core surface and that
results then by dragging the field lines
together in a local field
intensification so this is the idea
behind
using the objective flow assumption to
derive
the core surface flow so the equation
that derives that is here
so it says the rate of change of the
field or the secular version they give
pardon
too many clicks um is an interaction
between the flow
acting on the field so what we're going
to do is we're going to look at the
radial component of this
equation here at the core surface treat
it as an inverse problem
for the flow which has no radial
component at the core surface
because it's a material boundary so
we're going to look at the north south
and the east-west components
and we're going to derive them from the
secular variation but in fact we're
going to derive them from the spatial
gradients and the second operation of
those
satellite virtual observatories and we
assume within this process that the main
field is perfectly known and i've just
chosen to specify it like the chaos
model at the time instant each time
and i'm going to get a time series of
the flow by
minimizing the tempo and the spatial
complexity of the phone i'll talk a
little bit about that more about that
later on
so what we actually do is we expand
everything the field itself
the secular ovation and potentials
representing the flow in terms of
spherical harmonics
and that allows us to seek solutions for
the coefficients
of these potential expansions of the
flow which are linearly related
to the secularization of the secular
variation gradient data
so i said a little bit more about i said
earlier we're going to minimize the
spatial and the temporal correct
complexity of the flow so the way we do
that or regularizing it is we minimize
the epoxy
crop flow changes in each of our flow
coefficients
and either minimize one of these three
measures of the spatial complexity
of the flow so the first choice possible
choice is to
minimize the kinetic energy the second
is what's become known these days as the
strong norm
we're going to minimize the root mean
square second spatial derivatives and
i'm not going to be
more explicit than that and the third
choice this was um
a regularization i derived when i first
started looking at flows for a
completely different reason
but what we can do is say right i would
like to minimize
the amount of secular variation that the
flow generates when it interacts with
the field
so what i've actually chosen to is in
fact to minimize the root mean square
radial circulation so three really quite
different measures of spatial complexity
but what i hope to convince you of by
the end of the talk
is that they each require the same kind
of flow accelerations
to fit the data and in particular to
explain that
pacific junk so
very quickly moving on to the results i
was able to
obtain a minimum normalized misfit of
1.2
and the flows presented here have that
value so obviously that's slightly above
the
optimum value of one but remember that
we are neglecting diffusion
and so on and so forth so i was fairly
content with a
normalized misfit of 1.2 now i'm going
to show you
a movie of the flow globally in a moment
it shows the usual features
such as the band of westward flow
beneath the atlantic ocean
slower flow beneath the pacific ocean
because in general secular variation is
uh weaker there and the eccentric
planetary
gyre and what you'll see is that few
globally
very little flow changes are required to
achieve this misfit
over the um five years or so of swarm
data that i've
looked at so here is the flow and
uh this was actually obtained with the
minimizing the kinetic energy in the
flow
and just to give you an idea of the
scale the root mean square
flow speed is about eight kilometers per
year so
here's the eccentric planetary gyre
here's the band of westwood flow in this
sort of western hemisphere of the
hemisphere
centered on greenwich longitude and here
is the
lower much weaker flow slower flow in
the pacific hemisphere
and this is the rather boring movie that
puts that results from that i'll just
play it one more time
okay but we'll see later when we hang in
on the pacific that there is a little
bit more detail to be seen
there okay so before i do that i'll show
you how well these data
fit um how did well these models predict
the data
so we're going to look at the six
independent gradient components at that
virtual observatory i
marked with the black ellipse earlier
and
look at the predictions by the three
flows that
um using those three different spatial
regularizations and again
units pico teslas per kilometer per year
vertical scales you'll see vary from
plot to plot
okay now the predictions of the
differently
spatially regularized solutions feel fit
equally well globally
but they differ a little as you'll see
at the virtual observatory location
and you'll also note that regularized
flows under predict the amplitude of the
signal slightly
and relaxing regularization doesn't help
in any substantial
fashion so this is the component we were
looking at before in the top right
we are our component of secular ovation
um again 2014 to 2019 the blue dots here
are the data themselves and then the
three curves in orange grey
and yellow are the predictions of those
three different spatial complexity
norms so this is the strong norm the
strongest regularization
the kinetic energy norm you've just seen
the flow for that and the radial second
ovation norm
which i'll also show you flows for later
okay
so you can see that we're following the
trends in general as i say here
here for example you can see how we're
under predicting the amplitudes
this scale is here is a little bit
smaller but then you'll see these are
rather scattered data as well
and here and that is another example of
where we're under predicting the data
but those three flows do roughly equal
jobs in
fitting the data so i hope you can
believe that globally
they fit to it at the same extent
okay so let's look at the pacific jerk
in 2017
and i'll try to convince you that
there's a localized increase
in eastwood flow speed particularly in
the western part of the pacific north of
the equator
and there's a westward acceleration
south of the equator
and these flow changes are inserted in
sensitive to the form of spatial
regularization the flows themselves are
really quite different so
i was quite stunned when i found that
the changes themselves
are very very similar
so this is the pacific region here um
and this is the strong norm flow and
again i'm going to show you a video i've
put lots more arrows on here to look at
this small region
and i hope if i play it again you'll see
how this
eastwood flow here is intensifying at
around
jerk speed time okay there are some
other
notable changes over this side as well
but to explain the pacific
uh jerk you know in this region um we're
probably looking at these kind of
pictures here
i'll play one more time okay
so that's really quite a pronounced
feature
now these are the flows for different
spatial
regularizations i've just chosen one
epoch from within that you've seen how
little temporal variability there is so
this is the kinetic energy norm
this is the strong norm so you'll see
that we're more strongly regularized so
we're allowing
less spatial structure than within the
connect with the kinetic energy norm
and this has got a reference vector on
which applies to all three
and this is the flow that minimizes the
amount of radial circular evolution
when it acts on the magnetic field and
you'll see it's quite a bit stronger
um certainly there's no real sense of
weaker
slower flow beneath the pacific um in
general
although there are some places where
that's true and the
the eccentric gyrus is less well-defined
i would say and there are some other
really quite strange
rapid sorry small scale upwellings and
downwards so
i'm not suggesting that that's
necessarily a physically realistic flow
but it's again one that fits the data
and we will again we will see
shortly that the changes that we need to
explain the data with this flow are the
same essentially as with these two
planes as well
okay so the way i'm going to try and
show you that is
by calculating the acceleration and i've
just done that as successive
flow differences so i'll take i've
subtracted
the epoch before from a given epoch and
use that to define the acceleration
and i've not done any smoothing or
anything like that and you can also see
these same kind of differences
these um features if we look at the
differences from the mean and i do have
videos of those at the end
and they're slightly less noisy than the
acceleration as you can imagine
okay so here's the flow acceleration for
the struggle
i apologize the scale vector is uh
factor three too large which you can't
really see it very well anyway so i'm
going to play
this movie okay
and you can see around the jerk time
this start this feature starts to show
this eastwood acceleration and in fact
there's a counterbalancing
um westward acceleration to this and
slightly off to the southwest and these
features also seem to be robust
between the three different workflow
regularized stations i've chosen so i'll
play this
one more time okay we'll see some other
circulations giants
in the acceleration show up here as well
as we as we go through the time sequence
but that's the strong law here's the
kinetic energy norm you'll see there's
slightly more energy in uh converging
and diverging
accelerations which is slightly
difficult to get your head around
your mind and again we see at the end
an eastwood acceleration here westward
acceleration here
south westward and here northeast here
as we saw in the last one with some
other features that are consistent
in between but it's hard to stop the
video reliably to
to show you those and finally the um
the norm that produces a slightly
strange flow
uh that minimizes the amount of
predicted circulation and again you'll
see the snapshot here showing a very
similar feature
acceleration at the start and as we go
through
very similar acceleration the end south
westward here
north eastward here eastward and
westward there
so i i would claim that we've um
identified features of the flow or
changes in the flow that are required to
fit
those circulation gradient data so we've
produced satisfactory flow models
derived only from the gradient data i
haven't put
any actual secularization data in
themselves
as we've seen globally very little flow
changes required
um to start these temporally and
spatially regularized flows
slightly under predictable jet amplitude
in these
uh gradient data and that's certainly an
experience i've had before
where they are they under predict
secular variation day to themselves
and what we've seen i hope is that 2017
jerk involves an eastwood flower
acceleration
in the central pacific near the equator
and i will stop there thank you
excellent thank you very much kathy um
so we can all give
kathy a virtual uh applause uh through
zoom
it's a really uh interesting talk thank
you
and i will open the floor now to um
anybody with some questions for kathy
well i guess i'll kick off
uh the questions um when you're looking
at the
the um different regularizations
you know you're seeing very different um
globally speaking very different flow
patterns
um are there any consistent features
other than what you're looking at in
pacific
that that that would be robust features
in these different
models let me go back to showing my
screen
and um
so you know how they say beauty is in
the eye of
the beholder and all that so
i mean i would say that the gyre is
identifiable in all three so here's this
pacific gyre this is the enhanced
feature in the um
sort of above the bering strait at the
cormental boundary that uh
bill livermore's looked at with chris
finley from swarm data
down here round back up again they've
all got
a band of westwood flow
across the hemisphere centered on
greenwich
here a little bit less obvious and
the gyre is kind of a little bit
different in this case but
uh i suspect if you filter that flow
just to look at these spherical
harmonics that were
most representative of the gyre you
would see those same features
um i haven't looked at a comparison
between the power spectra to see if
there are any sort of shapes that are
similar there but
um you can you can identify
some features that seem to be consistent
i mean there's
another one here would be this small
um eddie okay
less well resolved here because of the
um
increased um damping or regularization
of small scale features so
there are some features that are similar
but it's perhaps harder to
um identify them particularly in this
play
um constable has a question
yeah uh i have to confess i'm a little
uh struck by the fact that uh the
jerk occurs in the place where the
secular variation
is weakest and um i'm wondering
if this is telling us something about uh
changes that are coming in the pacific
hemisphere
potential i would have thought there's a
good chance that it is
yes um i mean it's certainly
maybe i should have prepared a slide
also of the virtual observatories
throughout the
region because obviously people were
arguing oh well you don't see the
changes because we've only got a few
spots where we can actually
measure the field at the observatories
but once you do look throughout the
whole of the pacific using virtual
observations you do see very very
consistent features with
in general as you say low secularization
but now this
certainly this well-defined jerk seen
first in honolulu but certainly
throughout that local area very well
resolved in the
virtual observatory data so yes i'm sure
that it is telling us something about
that
do you have any further questions for
kathy
so i guess i have a question i don't
know if you have
seen it um there was a recent paper
in neutral geoscience which was
inferring
um high quantity high conductivity
mantle
under the pacific which is explaining
this low secular variation
given the fact that we see a jerk
uh what does that suggest then about the
conductivity
in the mantle in that region
um the simple answer
to that question would be you know that
that i mean
connectivity will screen out the changes
will stop them propagating through but
um as george backus showed back in 83
you can get a combination
of field changes um that that will
propagate and be seen
as a as a rapid change a jerk like
feature at the surface
regardless of the actual conductivity of
the mantle
and in particular and there's very
little screening if your connectivity is
um
concentrated close to the the core
mental boundary
indeed double prime for instance then
this
is very much weaker and i think that
tends to be where people want to put
high conductivity you know with things
like post-cross sky and iron in the
elemental
so it it's not a barrier to having
rapid circulation at the surface
so we've got some a little bit of time
for any more comments or questions i see
uh richard holm leaving his hands
hey kathy so i was struck by your
vertical
virtual observatories by just how sharp
these features are in the data and
these features are not measurements of
secular variation they are
annual averages in effect of what the
real secular variation is
and yet they're very very sharp now
you can't invert them directly and i've
been just trying to do some this is
related to the stuff i did on rotation a
few years ago
um you can't invert them directly but
you can come up with some kind of ideas
and the field changes don't just have to
be sharp
they have to the second version has to
jump in order to get the average coming
out of such a sharp v
shape anything it's not an average it's
just
two annual differences there's two
differences of values
yes that is the equivalent of if you're
trying to plot secular variation that's
equivalent of an annual
annual mean yeah yeah it's close to an
annual meeting
yes and then if you have these really
sharp changes
that's quite a strong change
yeah i mean this this is a problem we've
been looking for ages but just your
data are quite so sharp and of course
your flows don't come up
dtu's data not mine i've just been
inverting them but your group status
your talk statement unless niels wants
to argue with me he was
there somewhere um but nonetheless
these things are very very sharp when
you think about how they're constructed
in terms of first differences
and any thoughts on that no and that's
one of the things that the
dtu group are looking at in terms of
their um
their virtual observatory
calculations so that they've been
producing these as part of these swarm
disc um enterprise as it were
so they've looked at uh and
clearly what you get is um a spatial
temple trade-off
so you can make smaller vo you know you
can average over a smaller
area if you're willing to take longer
times or if you want a shorter time
scale then you need to take a bigger
volume
to get a meaningful average so there's
there's some kind of trade-off
there and so you could optimize
to look at the temporal variability
i suspect
even without doing it they are very very
sharp
they're they're pretty sharp yeah and um
i haven't you know what i should
should have done and what we've been
encouraging the dtu group is to put on
the error bars as well so
as i mentioned they've calculated um
variances of each of those data points
so you can actually see
that they they are well resolved within
you know them
those are bigger changes than the
uncertainties well me being me i don't
worry too much about error balance but
the fact that they shot so consistently
looking like that
says no there's something there yeah
yeah i agree with you
but i can't offer any further insight
i'm afraid
cool thank you um we can have time to
squeeze in
uh one more question if anybody has one
no i guess not um so thank you very much
kathy that was a
a really uh interesting talk and a lot
of uh
valuable and interesting questions here
so um everyone like to thank kathy once
again for
for her talk um
before we all disappear
um i would just like to to make a quick
announcement for the
uh upcoming seminars uh in in the coming
weeks
uh so in two weeks on august 12th we
have
uh courtney sprain from the university
of florida uh giving us a presentation
um but as we come to the end of summer
we still have some some open slots
so if anybody is interested in
uh giving a presentation please um
get in touch with us and we can schedule
something up for you
in the coming weeks um and as always
uh feedback uh thoughts ideas and
criticisms
criticisms are always very welcome for
these seminars so
just drop us an email if you have any
suggestions there
and thank you all again for coming out
for
another uh successful uh magnet seminar
so thank you