so um thank you everyone for uh joining
us for our next
uh magnets talk um which is going to be
given today by
courtney sprain um and before we begin
i just want to remind people that we'll
be talking for about
20 to 25 minutes so please keep your
microphones
muted during that time so it's not to
disturb the speaker
at the end we'll have a 10 to 15 minute
question and discussion session and so
please
raise your hands through zoom and we'll
invite you to
unmute your microphone and ask your
question um but if you don't want to
ask an oral question we will take
questions through the
chat window and so please just add a
little
no mic to your question and either
myself or one of the other conveners
will
read out the question for you um and
since these are seminars we're all
saying at home
uh if you do have to go halfway through
it by all means
just go it's not an issue at all and at
the very end
we will have a bit of time to catch up
with everybody
and just have a bit of socializing which
uh will not actually be
uh recorded so
um without further ado i will pass on to
courtney sprain who will be talking
uh today about clinkers
yeah thanks for that greg can you all
see my screen
yep
pointer options excellent okay
um so today i want to talk to you guys
about a passion project that i've been
working on for the last couple of years
and that is trying to magnetically
characterize
clinker deposits by the end of this
presentation i'm hoping that you guys
will
a learn what a clanker deposit is b
believe me that they are reliable
recorders of earth's magnetic field
and also that they provide a really neat
new option for filling in some of the
gaps that we have in the paleomagnetic
database
um and so this work has been in
collaboration with a lot of different
people
andy biggin was kind enough to let me
start working on this during my post-doc
at the university of liverpool a lot of
this work was
done through a visiting fellowship to
the institute for rock magnetism
in addition to having an undergrad there
riley lammers
who performed a lot of this work for her
senior thesis
and now this work is continuing at the
university of florida which is where i
am today
so paleomagnetic data and
a large spot of paleomagnetic data is
necessary to capture
long-term variations in earth's magnetic
field through geologic history
and this can tell us some really
important information about the
evolution of the earth
from magnetohydrodynamic processes that
are occurring in the outer core
and then it also has important
implications for things outside
of earth including
it deflects the solar wind understanding
magnetic field has implications for
production rates of cosmogenic nuclides
and additionally has important
implications for the evolution of
earth's deep interior
and then also ultimately habitability in
my particular research i'm interested in
understanding long-term variations in
earth's magnetic field these are
variations occurring on the order of a
million years or longer
and how we can tie these long-term
variations
to processes that are occurring in the
deep interior
but in order to do this we first need to
have
a reliable characterization of the
recent field where recent here
is the past 10 million years and this
reliable characterization is necessary
because we need something to compare
these other data sets too to determine
whether or not
they're different than kind of this
known average
and so looking at what we have for
recent periods
in earth's history of magnetic data it's
kind of divided into two
two different groups so first we have
our global time dependent field models
and so these have
done a really great job of
characterizing the magnetic field for
much of the holocene and additionally
the study came out a couple of years ago
in 2018
the ggf-100k model which extends these
global time dependent field models
back to a hundred thousand years ago
this is a really big effort
um and really amazing seat by this team
and so this record does a really good
job of characterizing some important
features of earth's magnetic field
including excursions
but there are many ways in which this
record can be
improved and so one of them is we can
kind of look at this map of where the
data distribution is for the data that
went into ggf 100k
and what we can see here is all these
diamonds are sediment cores
the green dots are volcanic records and
then
the red dots are volcanic and
archaeological records
and so first you'll see there are quite
a few data gaps particularly in the
middle of continents
and then also we see even in the middle
continents where we do have data
basically beyond 10 000 years a lot of
this data is missing
once we move beyond the archaeological
record
this is also important for understanding
intensity
changes um so a lot of the intensity
records that exist in ggf-100k are from
these archaeological records
over 90 percent of the paleo intensity
data that went into this model
is from these archaeological records
that are less than 10 000 years old
and so we're really missing um a
big picture of what was going on with
intensity
um for much of this record because we
don't have high quality paleo intensity
data
from volcanic records um nicely
distributed throughout the world
now going back further in time we don't
have these global time dependent field
models instead we have global data sets
of time average field and so one
particular data set
that recently was published is the psv10
dataset which is a data set that
compiles
directional data only from volcanic
rocks for the last 10 million years
and so this is a map of where the data
is distributed and as you can see
there's
pretty good global coverage but we still
do have some gaps in the center of
continents
and then another important feature of
this is this data set is looking at
directions
only so we're really missing variation
in
intensity and in many cases or in some
cases that can
this can ultimately bias our view of
what was going on
on or for the magnetic field for these
time periods because we don't have a
full vector record
and so ideally we'd like to be able to
extend these types of global time
dependent field models further back in
time
we'd like to be able to connect between
the two we'd like to be able to fill in
these gaps
and we like to be able to fill in more
intensity data
but to do this we need more data i've
said this a lot during
this introduction there are a lot of
data gaps particularly intensity and in
order to
extend any of these models further back
in time
we we need more high quality paleo
intensity data
and so one opportunity to try to fill in
some of these gaps in the recent
magnetic record
is clinker deposits and so you're
probably thinking
what the heck is a clunker deposit
yeah exactly so clanky deposit clinkers
are a suite of metamorphic rocks that
have been baked
welded and or melted by natural burning
of underlying coal seams
um so there's this they're this special
suite of pyro metamorphic rocks
meaning they're metamorphosed by fire
and so basically what happens
is we're in this say here we have a
fluvial
deposit uh where we have this coal seam
that's exposed at the surface
this coal seam can ignite at the surface
due to processes such as spontaneous
combustion
lightning wildfires a human activity if
you're burning a cornfield for example
and then this burning starts basically
once it consumes this cold starts moving
backwards
into the outcrop and as it's moving
backwards into the outcrop it's
consuming that coal
it's reaching really really really high
temperatures and it's baking
all of the sediment and the material
around it and it is this baked material
this baked sediment that once was
overlying these coal seams that now no
longer exist
because they've been burnt up that are
what makes up
clinker deposits
and so clinker the term clinker actually
refers to
all products from this type of reaction
and so it's not just referring to a
particular clinker lithology
and so in general these types of
products can be divided into a couple of
different groups depending on
initial lithology and also depending on
things like temperature reached
and oxidation state and so
broadly there are three categories of
clinker lithologies we have our baked
sediment
these are parts of the planker that have
been heated to the lowest temperatures
around 300 to 800 degrees c
we then have porcelainite these are
baked to intermediate temperatures of
600 to 1400 degrees c
and then finally we have para lavas
which are effectively melted
rock so these are melts that have been
crystallized so these are basically
new igneous rocks and these have reached
extremely high temperatures of 1500 to
2000 degrees celsius
and so broadly these differ both by
temperature formation
but also baked sediment tends to involve
lithologies that started as sandstones
or siltstones generally these coarser
lithologies
and porcelainite generally started as
things like shtails
and within all of these different
deposits there's an array of oxidation
states
so you can either have really oxidizing
conditions and get really red
really orange deposits and you can also
have reducing conditions
that produce things like these kind of
dark purple to black
colored rocks and these parallels really
hot temperatures generally form in these
chimneys
which are regions where these hot gases
from the burning of coal are trying to
reach the surface and they're convecting
within these regions
and so why do um why might clinkers be
good for
for paleomagnetism so first clinkers can
be reliably dated
and so clinkers are not the same age as
the sediments around them you don't
normally start getting burning of coal
seams until these coal seams have
reached earth's surface
and so that's many millions of years
after the formation of these sedimentary
deposits
and so clinkers have been reliably dated
using
fission track also uranium during helium
dating and argon argon geochronology
and then clinkers also because they
don't start burning until
they're close to earth's surface these
coal seams tend to be
recent time and age covering the last 5
million years
to 10 million years and so in the powder
river basin alone
this is a basin that's between montana
and wyoming in
western united states clinkers cover
basically the last 4 million years so
there are coal seams that are still
burning today
and actually this whole region is called
the powder river basin from the powder
river
which was called the powder river
because when loose and clark came upon
this area
they thought it smelled like gun powder
because
of the burning of these coal seam
deposits
in siberia deposits range from 0 to 1.2
million years in age of the deposits
have been dated in china we have
deposits ranging through the pleistocene
and then in israel we have some of our
older clinker
deposits which are min myosin to
plyocene and age
and so an additional advantage of
studying clinker deposits is they also
not only offer an opportunity to kind of
study this period of interest this kind
of zero to five
million years in age um they also offer
the opportunity to
do this at high resolution so basically
a clinker deposit as it
is formed will start where coal is
burning at the surface and then it will
continually form as this fire extends
back into the outcrop
a single coal seam fire can burn for
thousands to tens of thousands of years
as is extending back into the outcrop
and so if we're able to obtain samples
all across this plateau
or we might be able to see changes in
the magnetic field with really high
resolution
for periods of about 10 000 years
an additional reason why these might be
good for paleomagnetism is they're wide
spread
so this is a map of modern coal seam
fires which are shown as red dots and
then clinker deposits which are shown as
these pink dots
and so clinker deposits have been found
in continental interiors this is
generally where we have these large
sedimentary basins which coal seams
and they have a wide geographic
distribution they've been identified in
at least 15 countries
and as you can see if we
bring back up the maps of where data was
distributed in
ggf-100k and also psv10 we see that some
of the distribution of clinker deposits
helps kind of fill in some of these gaps
that we have in the interior of these
continents
additionally providing some high
latitude sites
and possibly some new sites in south
america
and australia
and so why else might they be good for
paleomagnetism
and so one of the reasons they might be
good for paleomagnetism
is the process by which they're formed
is really really similar to the process
of the formation of archaeological
materials or these baked archaeological
materials
so it's basically the baking of
sediments and clays
to really really really high
temperatures which is basically turning
what used to be a detrital remnant
magnetization
into what should be a thermal or thermal
chemical remnant magnetization
if we look at the general ranges of
formation temperatures for
baked sediment to para lavas we see that
all of these have been reheated to at
least 300 degrees celsius
and considering that in a lot of these
deposits the primary
magnetic mineralogy is intermediate
titano hematite with low and blocking
temperatures
all of these products should be
reheating above
the curia temperatures of the mineralogy
that was originally there
and so at least resetting the drm and
whether or not it's a trm or a tcrm
i hope to show you by the end of this
talk
and another reason these might be good
is there have been past studies
looking at clinker deposit past
paleomagnetic studies that indicate
that they are reliable magnetic
recorders so jones at all and then a lot
of work done by rob sternberg and the
powder river basin and also in the
williston basin
there's been demagnetization work
showing that clinkers preserve
these basically univectorial
thyroid diagrams yielding really good
directional data
other work done by deborah in china has
shown that some of these products are
really thermally stable so in
thermo-magnetic experiments they don't
alter
there's been some work done for paleo
intensity on these types of deposits
in the czech republic these are
generally old studies so it's hard to
assess the reliability of the paleo
intensity results but looking at
this array diagram here we see it looks
pretty good this is a straight line
fitting these different components
whether or not there's alteration
will have to be seen because this didn't
use ptrm checks but it looks pretty good
and then also even in deposits in israel
we see that
they also found these kind of
univectorial directions
and they match expected directions for
the time of formation of these rocks
so these should be good for magnetic
studies
but one of the things the other studies
did not do is
look at a broad range of materials
within clinker deposits so clinkers are
really heterogeneous
so there's this wide variety of clinker
materials with a variation of oxidation
state
variation of clinker lithology we also
have variations in potential
temperatures of formations depending how
close you are to the old
coal seam um obviously hotter
temperatures are going to be closer to
the base cooler temperatures further
away
and so although these previous studies
have shown that clinkers have the
potential to be reliable recorders
it's still unclear which part of a
clanker
is good for paleomagnetic study and so
that's kind of the impetus and objective
of our work has been to assess the rock
and paleomagnetic behavior of clinkers
and this has been basically we've tried
to do this as a function of
lithology so focusing on variations that
we observe between
the different types of clinker
lithologies from baked sediment
porcelain to para lava
we also looked at this as a function of
distance from the coal seam
by collecting a few profiles we looked
at this as a function of oxidation state
by grouping our results based on color
where darker colors tend to
be indicative of reducing states and
orange and red colors
are indicative of oxidizing states and
then also of location
so where we collected our samples we
studied whether or not we saw variations
on
between our clinker deposits and also
between different coal seams that they
were
burning coal seams that they represented
and so where we collected these deposits
was from the custer national forest this
is in
the northeastern powder river basin in
eastern montana
um and so these were clinker or these
clinker deposits had formed in paleocene
fluvial sediments
we collected 101 samples across this
region
this is a map here one of the reasons
this region was
selected is because this is one of the
few areas where clinker deposits have
actually been mapped
so we have these nice reliable maps
where we can expect to
find clinker deposits and additionally
these clinker deposits many of them in
this region have been dated already
using uranium during helium and also
fission track and so we were able to go
here
and to have this nice framework of where
to find the clinkers of known age
that really aided our study so we
collected 101 samples
from four data clinkers and five undated
clinkers
and we additionally sampled two profiles
extending
from the top of the clinker down to the
unbaked sediment below
and then also from the base of a clinker
up through unbig sediment above
and so to do this type of analysis we
performed a range of rock magnetic
experiments
i'm not going to go list these um
you can kind of see them here
we're basically we're trying to assess
differences in mineralogy but also grain
size
between all of these different clinker
products
and so let's start with variations in
lithology
so to look at variations in clinker
lithology we were
or divided our clinker deposits and our
results into different groups
um so we did this into big sediment
porcelain and para lava did
three main types of clinker lythologies
we also divide it into weekly baked one
of the profiles we collected
was through a recently burned coal seam
fire that
seemed to have extinguished relatively
rapidly
we could actually walk out the start of
this
clinker deposit around the corner to
where the coal had not burned
whereas these deposits were where the
clinker like up here was at the top of
the hill
it had burned for a long period of time
and created these strongly baked
equivalents
and then we also collected samples from
unbaked sediment
to kind of provide a baseline of what
these things looked like
before they were baked and so let's
quickly summarize our unbaked sediments
so our unbaked sediments had one primary
remnants carrier
and so we found that this was
titanomagnetite or intermediate titanic
hematite
and you'll understand why i say or
intermediate titanohaematate shortly
and so this was because they generally
had low coercivity ranges less than 100
ml tesla
and unblocking temperatures below 400
degrees around 300 degrees celsius so
consistent with
a soft mineral
with titanium in it to get these lower
curie temperatures
our weekly baked sediment had two
primary remnants carriers
so the first was also this titano
magnetite phase so we still
saw the softer component with low
median destructive fields around 32 mil
tesla
and then also low in blocking
temperatures less than 400 degrees
and we also saw this new component of
hematite as one would expect these rocks
are now red
when they were not red when we started
moving on to our baked sediment we had
two primary remnants carriers
uh so now one of our remnants carriers
is magnetite it's not the titanium
magnetite
um this had generally both a low
and a high correctivity component one
that was less than 100 ml tesla and one
that was greater than 100 ml of tesla
with unblocking temperatures between 400
and 590 degrees celsius
and we additionally have this high
coercivity thermally stable phase
this hcslt phase so this phase had
coercivities that were above one tesla
and had curie temperatures around 220
degrees celsius
with relatively high magnetizations
and then we also had some minor carriers
observed in our baked sediment
including this intermediate titanium
hematite
and also regular hematite
looking at perselonite we also had two
primary remnant carriers
again very similar to our bank sediment
we had this magnetite with two variants
both low and high coercivity we also had
this hcslt
phase and then we had minor carriers
that were intermediate titanic hematite
and then also regular hematite
now moving on to pear lavas para lavas
were quite different they only had one
primary remnants carrier and that was
magnetite
um and so this tended to be our higher
coefficient component of magnetite
which are with um conversivity levels
less than 100 ml tesla
and also these had generally pretty
distinct unblocking ranges
around 575 degrees celsius so very
consistent with
low titanium magnetite we also observed
some minor carriers so we did see
evidence for the hcslt phase
in some samples that still kind of had
these blocks of baked sediment within
them
and then we also saw evidence for some
hematite
and we also saw evidence for a phase
that had an unblocking temperature above
700 degrees celsius
and considering the odd nature in which
parallels form
this could be a really interesting
magnetic phase
so now i'm going to walk through some of
the evidence that led us to these
conclusions
and some of the it's not all of our data
we had a lot of data
but these are the results that led us to
these conclusions the most strongly
and so the first one is we're going to
look at hysteresis properties
so these are some hysteresis loops for
different types of materials that
we talked about previously so we have
perselonate two examples of big
sandstone and then an example of
parallel
and so what we see is within our baked
materials including procellonite and our
baked sandstones
we kind of have this bimodal coercivity
range
so we have both evidence for this really
high coercivity
phase that was really really hard had
conversivities above one tesla and then
we also see evidence example of the big
sandstone that this phase has a very
high magnetization
which would be too high for hematite
in this example the bake sandstone down
here we have a really wasp wasted curve
which is showing our sharply bimodal
distribution between that magnetite
phase but also this higher coercivity
phase
and then in parallavas we don't really
see evidence for this hard component
we see this dominantly soft curve which
is indicative
of remnants being carried by mostly
magnetite
and so this by modality that we saw
in our baked materials both a big
sandstone and porcelain
can also be recognized by looking at
sigma values
where the high values are indicating a
more wasted curve
and so we say our pair of lavas are
dominantly kind of ranging around
zero indicative of having basically this
one phase
where baked sediment and our perselonite
have higher sigma values
indicative of this bimodality of
coercivity
of the minerals that are within these
samples and this kind of wasp wastedness
so moving on to looking at the day plot
and then also the squareness versus
coercivity plot we can see a few more
trends by combining all of our data
together
so on these plots the colors indicate
the different type of lithology
where blue is para lava green is our
baked sediment
orange is porcelainite and this pink is
unbaked
and they also have a brettcher component
which is we didn't collect enough of it
to indicate it as its own category
but we did sample one of them so we
included it on this plot
and so basically what we can see from
these plots is
first of all our bake sediment and our
porcelain generally have
really high mr versus miss ratios and
also
bcr versus bc so this really high
coercivity range they're extending
really far in this direction
and then also really far in this
direction and they're the furthest away
from
our magnetite mixing curves we see the
same thing looking at the squareness
versus coercivity plot
where we do have some falling in between
these
tm-60 and magnetite curves but a lot of
the data is actually plotting to
the right at higher coercivity values
our para lavas and our unbaked sediment
are plotting closest to these mixing
lines
not quite on top of them but more
indicative basically that these two
phases have more magnetite
that one would traditionally expect if
it's falling along these lines
so now looking at our results from the
arm acquisition and demagnetization
experiments
because we had this high coercivity
phase we could not treat
the arm data on its own and so instead
in order to calculate median destructive
fields
we calculated the vector difference sum
or difference
vector difference on the magnetization
vector for each sample and then from
this
calculated the median destructive field
and so this effectively was able to kind
of mask out the remaining high
coercivity component that did not
acquire an arm
and that was remaining after
demagnetization and then we also
calculated percent hc or percent high
coercivity
which is the percent of remnants that
was remaining after the 170 ml tesla af
step
and so looking at our plots uh this is
median destructive field versus this is
the
arm of the component that's already been
filtered out
for this high coercivity step um and
then we have over here percent hc versus
that same arm component
and so by looking at these plots again
the colors indicate the same differences
in lithology
we can see that the lowest median
destructive fields
are in our unbaked and weakly baked
samples
and also that these unbaked and weekly
baked samples had the lowest arms
so the lowest magnetizations whereas
our baked samples as we're moving into
baked sediment and porcelain
we start increasing our median
destructive fields
and increasing our arms so increasing
our magnetizations
looking at percent hc we also see that
our unbaked and weekly baked samples
have
really low percent hc so they don't have
this high coercivity phase and we start
seeing this increase in high coercivity
phase again
when we're looking at our big sediment
barcelonite samples
para lavas kind of plot in different
areas with both low and high median
destructive fields
and moderate to low percent hcs
and some of these moderate ones may be
biased by having some chunks of baked
material within them as well
and so in order to get a better
constraint
on what was actually carrying this high
coercivity phase we performed a modified
lowry test
and so what do i mean by modified lowry
test well by modified lowry test i mean
that instead of applying
that basically instead of doing a
thermal demagnetization of
arms we did an afd magnetization of trms
and so we applied three different trms
one at 700 degrees
uh one at 600 and one at 300 and then
af demagnetize them up to 170 ml tesla
and so in this way we were better able
to capture um
this this behavior between our
coercivity and also on blocking
and so by looking at the results from
this plot we can see that
our baked sediment we both have
dominant phases being this three
anything less than 300 degrees in some
samples it's
samples with remnants between three are
unblocking temperatures between 300 and
600 degrees c
so this would be indicative of kind of
our magnetite phase this would be
our hcslt phase
and then in the sample here this orange
baked salt stone we kind of see a mix in
between where we have both
remnants held in this intermediate and
blocking range and also this higher in
blocking range
and none of our samples did we see a
strong component of magnetization held
greater in the 700 phase so not a strong
component of magnetization held by
hematite
um and then in our baked para lava we
see that most of the remnants is being
held by this
greater than or the 600 phase so between
300 600 so this would be
indicative of most of the remnants being
held by magnetite
um and another observation that we can
make looking at this plot
is that this 300 phase does not fully
demagnetize by 170 ml of tesla
so this is indeed holding on to our
hgslt phase another odd observation of
these plots is we have this little
dip here where we start losing remnants
and then gaining it again
indicative of something acquiring a
field during these experiments in the
opposite direction of what was applied
and so this might be indicative of
intermediate titanium hematite
this mineral has been found in similar
age sedimentary deposits
in northeastern montana and so it's
possible that it's in these deposits as
well
and then was accumulated and acquired
into
these clinker deposits
and so i'm kind of going to brush over
some of the hot or the susceptibility
results
um but basically the things i want you
to take away from these results
are as with heating so we have unbaked
here weekly baked
baked perselonite para lava para lava
as we move with increasing temperatures
increasing degree of being baked
we start having curves that once weren't
reversible and altered
becoming more reversible indicating that
these are becoming more
thermally stable what we're also seeing
is we have some evidence here for this
low and blocking phase this is probably
alteration
and then as we move into our baked
materials we see evidence for this
magnetite phase
but we don't really see evidence for the
hcslt phase
where we'd expect to see so we don't see
this on blocking around 200 degrees
and then this is the example of that
parallava sample where we have
this weird high temperature phase
that still has remnants above 700
degrees celsius
and so in order to better understand
where we are losing our
remnants we performed high temperature
hysteresis
experiments where we measured hysteresis
loops
with increasing temperatures from room
temperature up to 600
or 700 degrees celsius and so what we
can see is first we have this transition
from these
wasted curves down to kind of these soft
curves
and then finally into more harder curves
which are hard to see here but you can
see it really here in the transition
of looking at coercivity we have
coercivity decreasing
through this 220 degree phase further
decreasing through the magnetite carry
temperature but then after we remove
magnetite it's steeply increasing again
which is indicative of hemotype we also
see here looking at this plot
looking at magnetization we do have this
nice
decrease in magnetization uh that
has this abrupt kind of change at 220
degrees celsius
and so this is our hcslt phase
and looking at the same thing and
susceptibility we don't see it here
indicating that whatever is causing this
change
um doesn't have a large susceptibility
and so the next thing we wanted to do
was constrain the um
grain size of these samples and so we
did this by
performing fork analyses and so we saw
these broad ranges of behavior of our
fork analyses so these are both baked
sediment this is porcelain this is para
lava
in our baked sediment and our
purcellinate we saw kind of two
different groupings
of behaviors so one was this kind of
grouping where we had these strong
coercivity peaks extending out to 5 to
40 ml of tesla
and then also these kind of inner weak
interacting
or interaction uh fields extending out
plus minus 20 ml of tesla
similar here in this perspective sample
but then we also had this other grouping
which had this huge high coverage detail
which is indicative of our hcslt phase
in the para lavas we also saw the strong
coercivity peak between 5 and 20
millitessa
but we also saw much larger interaction
fields
and so in general this kind of looks psd
like
probably slightly larger grain sizes in
these components
but it's kind of hard to tell whether or
not these are
the real behavior considering they are
generally this one is definitely masked
by this high coaster detail
and these ones might be biased by it as
well because we know that phase exists
and so to get a clearer picture of this
we decided to
run high temperature forks and so
what we did is we ran a fork analysis
preheating at room temperature
a standard fork analysis we ran another
fork analysis at 250 degrees c
and then we ran another one again at
room temperature post heating
and so what we can see here is after
this 250 degree temperature step
this high coercivity phase is lost and
so
so now we're basically seeing through
that high coercivity phase
and we can see evidence of what the
grain size population is
for this softer phase and so it's kind
of it's psd like
and then what we can also see is the
comparison between preheating and post
heating
and generally the fork diagrams look the
same there's
some shifting in this direction so it
might be slightly altering
but generally they're magnetically
thermal thermally stable so we did this
for a couple more samples
very similar behavior this 250 degree
temperature step is removing this high
coercivity phase
and so jumping into changes in color i'm
just going to
quickly run through this we broadly
divided our stuff into whether it was
red and orange oxidizing
black and purple reducing and yellow was
unbaked
and so looking at these results for
colors indicating the color
we can see our red and orange samples
have the higher mr versus miss and vcr
versus bc ratios
and also higher coercivity values
indicating that this hls
hcslt phase is in oxidizing conditions
we also have this black purple and
yellow samples plotting closer to these
expected mixing lines
suggesting they have more magnetite
this corroborated by looking at our
sigma values our black samples tend to
have the lower sigma values and our red
and orange tend to have the highest
indicating that they have mixtures of
different coercivity components
and then looking at our percent hc we
see our red and our orange samples have
the highest percent hc and the highest
amount of this hcslt
phase and also of hematite and then our
orange
samples have the highest so maybe orange
is
indicating the color of the space and so
to summarize our orange and red have
more abundance of this high coarsivity
phase
and purple and black are more abundant
in magnetite
so now looking at comparisons by
distance from the coal seam fire
um so what we did is basically we
collected two profiles one this is
through a
or weekly baked profile starting at
the base of where the coal seam was and
then extending multiple meters
up and this one we did the opposite
where we started at the top of the
plateau that had a strongly baked
clinker
and we worked down into the unbaked
sediments below
and so some of the things that we can
see looking at these
curves is first within
a clinker there does not appear to be
any
observable variation of magnetic
properties with distance
so we do see our percent hc
changing but it's relatively high
throughout uh same with our median
destructive field
um we do see however large variations in
unbaked coal or sediment below the coal
seam immediately below
we see these stark changes immediately
in percent hc and also in medium
destructive field
and we see a slight difference also
between weakly baked and
unbaked sediment as well but it's not as
strong
a slight shift in medium destructive
fields but it's not as well developed
and so moving on to location we broadly
grouped it into
just locality and then also different
types of coal seams so these clinkers
are formed and
mapped cool seams that broadly represent
primary sediments of a different age and
so first just looking at all of our
different sites
we don't see a broad difference in
magnetic properties as a function of
locality that's not already described by
clinker lithologies very similar ranges
in each deposit we collected
and then same for the different coal
zones we don't really see a variation in
magnetic properties between the coal
zones as well
and so to summarize our primary controls
on magnetic properties appear to be
clinker lithology
um so if it's para lava versus baked
material
and also oxidation state where it's more
reduced there's more magnetite
we don't see magnetic properties being a
function of primary lithology
so whether or not it was a mudstone or a
sandstone that you were making
distance from the coal seam which is
kind of shocking and then also location
and so one thing that we needed to
figure out was what is this hcslt
phase and we believe that it is epsilon
hematite
or lugo fungite which i am totally
butchering the name of
and so why is this so the observed
characteristics of the phase that we
identified on our deposits is they have
high coercivity
so above one tesla they have low on
blocking between 180 and 220 degrees c
they have high magnetization higher than
one would expect for hemotype
they are thermally stable and it's
really similar in properties to the
epsilon hematite phase that was observed
in baked archaeological
materials first identified by mcintosh
and then
later confirmed by lopez sanchez in
2016.
and so as we can see all of these
different properties nicely match this
epsilon hematite phase down here
just a reminder of time courtney yep no
i'm watching i'll be done in two minutes
but thank you and so we can kind of
summarize how do clinkers
get their magnetization so first we have
this change of drm into either a tcrm
or a trm due to heating we also see an
ingrowth of pneumatic materials that's
either going to be a trm or a serum
in our weekly baked clinker deposits we
have an ingrowth of magnetite
which is causing enhanced magnetization
this is possibly a trm but it could be a
tcrm
in our strongly baked deposits we have
more magnetite uh we start forming this
epsilon hematite phase
this epsilon hematite phase in both
laboratory experiments and also in
experiments forming this phase and
archaeological materials only forms at
high temperatures above 600 c
so this is likely holding a trm and
because we don't see
really any variation in where we're
finding this epsilon hematite phase from
distance from the coal seam
we find it as much as eight meters away
it suggests that basically this entire
thickness
of a clinker could have a trm
and then finally our para lavas these
are melted rocks they're mostly
magnetite
um because they're melted and we're
heated to 1000 c
they likely hold the tierra and so to
summarize what this means for future
studies on paleo directions
uh the primary drm should be reset for
paleo directions mineralogy and grain
size are amenable to
long relaxation times so they should
record the field from when they formed
her paleo intensity or grain size is in
this nice psd like range which is ideal
for paleo intensity
they're highly thermal or her thermally
stable and they're most likely holding a
trm
and so based on magnetic properties
clinkers should be reliable full vector
paleomagnetic recorders but we still
needed
or we still need to assess possible
complexities such as cooling rate
and anisotropy and so that is ongoing
work
that's occurring today we are running
these experiments i can tell you
um that they look really really good and
so more work will be coming out on that
soon
so thank you and i will stop there
wonderful thank you very much courtney
um you can all show our
round of applause with uh the zoom
little applause button
and that was really interesting um
so i apologize for the background i i
can open up
uh the the floor to questions and i see
uh
andrew kosteroff you have your honda
and if you'd like to on your microphone
you can ask the question
okay okay uh thank you courtney for uh
for this very very interesting talk
you mentioned the low temperature
magnetometer as a method
but it didn't show any pictures
so so basically two questions concerning
that
have you ever seen very transition in
any of your samples you did okay great
yeah
and uh did you compare
okay yeah oh
wow so so yeah
i would say yeah so we we have some
evidence of potentially
yeah this last this last figure looks
like a
very but i i don't i don't agree
with the left the left uh
it's only to do with this no no no
there's a separation it's probably not
the fur way
um but it's some sort of it's a traffic
point we need to
we need to discuss it but most important
most important
uh well from this data i i uh
maybe you also have the data where you
suspect this hc
slt phase yeah so it's in
these three samples okay but
the problem is that
you may know we started the the projects
concerning the archaeomagnetic
electromagnetic archaeological samples
with colleagues from sofia
recently and my
my impression concerning this
interpretation
of hclps epsilon is
we do have problems with this because
synthetic epsilon
iron oxide has a very distinctive low
temperature properties
and no nobody has it
has ever seen that in either
archaeological material
or in your data so no i agree yep that
is a problem with it
and if i may one last
uh short questions what is the range of
curious temperatures of your hclt
yes i was just going to mention that so
our range of curie temperatures for that
phase
are it's not distinctly at 220 or 222
which one would expect for
pure uh the pure phase um it actually
ranges from about 180 to 220
and so it's possible like the
conclusions of lopez sanchez that
their phase had some titanium
substitution
the other issue is at least in
laboratories
the grain sizes that they were able to
produce of this phase are very very very
small and the grain sizes that are
observed and archaeological materials
are much
larger and so if this
is that phase um it suggests that maybe
titanium substitution is making it
not ideal but it could also be something
else um
but whatever we have is very similar to
what's in the archaeological samples
um forming from
high temperature alteration yes yeah
exactly
okay and one more comment if if if greg
would follow us in in our
in our work with archaeological samples
we have
we had the unblocking temperatures down
to 120
for this phase so it's maybe even larger
larger range yeah okay thank you very
much courtney
again thank you thank you thank you so
we've got a couple of questions from
the chat so gunther is wanting to know
what is the
highest uh temperature recorded in
clinton deposits
oh so the highest temperature recorded
is around
1500 degrees celsius um
and so that's going to be within your
chimney deposit so that's where you have
hot gas that's being convected up
there has been quite a bit of thermal
modeling done on clinker
deposits because or at least on coal
seam fires
because they are a a pretty big hazard
because they raise a lot of gas
and then b are a problem for people who
want to mine coal
and so they are monitoring these and so
thermal models of basically temperature
profiles at the surface
do suggest that at the coal seam not
necessarily within these chimneys
you are still reaching temperatures of
at least 800 degrees celsius if not
higher
i have another question um from uh
quentin simon
and he's wondering if you've already
have some paleo intensity data
uh and what would you say about that i i
do um yeah so we've already collected
some paleo intensity results
and so this is them um
and this is kind of my slide on that uh
but yeah so we did thermal and microwave
izzy experiments uh and a few dht shaw
and basically what we're seeing is
really
nice straight arrived lots uh we're not
observing a difference in some of our
samples between
the epsilon phase and the magnetite
phase which one might observe
because they have different cooling
times
so really consistent throughout also
this is all from the same sample
and so we're seeing really nice highly
reproducible results
within the same site and then
these are consistent with univectorial
decaying
cider build plots um we do have some
that are showing
two different components and this could
be
because of grain size we don't really
know the grain size of the epsilon phase
but it could also be actually recording
differences in the magnetic field during
this time period and so this is kind of
also a direction of future work good
question
thanks very much and we have time for
one more quick question if anybody has
one
so i will i will throw it either to you
you flash past your
map uh showing the distribution of
klingon
and i mean at first glance it does kind
of look as though there's a bit of a
latitudinal band across north america
and europe
is that due to the distribution of the
clinkers or just the distribution
of clinkers that have been reported
uh let me go to that map
i should have gone the other direction
so i believe it has to do with the
distribution of clinkers that have been
studied
um so if you actually look at
the distribution of coal seam fires uh
it's a bit more spread out
there we go um so yeah so distribution
of coal seam fires
tends to be a little bit more broad um
where all the clinker deposits that are
on this map are ones that have been
studied
it's likely they exist everywhere their
coal seam fires
um and people just haven't studied them
uh because we know
these processes if there's been a coal
seam there have been occurring for at
least thousands of years
so i think this yeah this broad
latitudinal band is probably just where
people have studied
also my bad um like
movement of points onto a map might be
part of it as well
so plotting of data problems
well thank you very much courtney um so
i think at that point we'll
we'll wrap it up and i want to thank
courtney again for giving uh
a really good presentation and
discussing something that not a lot of
people know
a lot about so thank you very much
courtney thank you
oh you could all see me opening that oh
well
um before we all uh finish up i just
want to
make a couple of quick uh
mentions um before we move on the um
presentations are now being recorded and
we're making them available online
and through the magic
youtube channel and that's a link there
it's a very cumbersome and lovely
looking thing
but if you um just search
for a magic consortium um you'll be able
to find it
so i want to thank earthref and the
magic team
for supporting that um the videos are
actually going to be uploaded
also through the earthref um database
um and they're being assigned dois
so they're going to be uh citable
objects so if you do find
um anything interesting and useful in
the seminars that we present
uh you can cite them and give give the
authors credit for
for for all their hard work and their
interest in science
um and lastly we have a number of slots
um still to to fill um so if anybody is
interested in giving a seminar
um please just get in touch with us
and as always uh any feedback ideas and
criticisms
are always welcome so just uh drop us an
email um
and thank you all very much for coming
to uh the magnet seminar
and i hope to see you all in a couple of
weeks and i should say
say that we have a catch-up at the end
as well um which
we won't be recording so if you want to
catch up with everybody uh and have good
uh chin wag please hang on afterwards
thank you