okay
so uh thank you everyone for coming to
uh what will be
uh the last um uh magnet seminar
of of 2020 uh we've had a successful run
and a great turnout for everybody so
uh thank you all uh very much for uh for
your support
um for those who who are new to uh
these seminars uh we'll have
presentations that are about 20 to
25 to 30 minutes in length um i kindly
ask that you keep your microphones
uh muted um during the presentation so
that we don't interrupt
uh the speaker uh following the
uh the seminar will have us a 10 to 15
minute
uh discussion if you do not want to
uh unmute yourself to ask a micro a task
a question
we will answer we can take questions
through the uh the text chat
so just simply add no mic um to your
question
and either myself or anita uh we'll read
them out
um as always we have life and all sorts
of things going on around us so if you
do have to leave halfway through
it's absolutely not a problem uh just
you just need to go
uh and just a reminder for the record
that uh the seminars are recorded
um and at the end of the seminar we will
have time um
to chat and catch up uh with everybody
if you're interested in that
and this part of of the magnet series
isn't recorded
and so won't be made publicly available
we turn the recording off
and we can all just uh chit chat and uh
relax
um and so i'm very pleased to introduce
our speaker our last speaker for
uh 2020 erdo kia tima from the
university
of uh turin and she will be talking
about
archaeomagnetic research in italy so i
will head over to
iftakia okay thank you so much
can you see my screen
yes yeah we can
yes sir i can see your screen and i knew
it again
okay thank you so much first of all i
would like to thank
a lot greg and anita for giving me this
opportunity
to talk here today a little bit about
automagnetic research in italy
and my talk today will be a very brief
overview
of the available up to now
electromagnetic data from italy
presenting some recent advances
ecobritis with some future perspectives
i would like to say that what i'm going
to present is not just the result of my
personal work but is the work of a lot
of researchers that during the last
decades they have dedicated a part of
their research
on establishing promoting and advancing
electromagnetic research in italy
and also collaboration with a lot of
archaeologists that i would like to
personally
acknowledge a lot okay
as we all know already very well uh
reconstructing and understanding how the
earth's magnetic field was changing in
the past
is particularly interesting and
important from one part you can give us
information
indirect information about the processes
that take place in the corporate
boundary
and offer some insights about the origin
and nature of the geomagnetic field
while from the other part one we once
we are able to know how theirs magnetic
field was changing
in the past we can then use this
information
as a dating tool useful for different
fields of earth sciences of course in
order to retrieve information about how
the earth's magnetic field was changing
in the past and mostly in the time
periods where no direct
measurements are available it is
necessary to study
several kinds of well-dated material
such as for example archaeological
material volcanic rocks
lacrosse stream or marine sediments or
other kind of natural archives such as
failovers
for example i think that we can say that
among all these geomagnetic field
recorders
we can consider acid base lace volcanic
rocks as
quite freezing sources of information as
they mainly
present three important advantages
first of all they carry a quite strong
and stable film aroma and magnetization
acquired
during the heating at high temperatures
and subsequent cooling
in the presence of the ambient icing
field
they and that's of course the case of
volcanic rocks or
of archaeological materials such as big
clays
they can give us also very well dated
reliable sport records and as for
example the famous
vesuvius eruption that destroyed
at the same time preserved forever the
ancient city of pompeii
and we know very well that of 79.80
so this way we can have a quite reliable
very well dated sport report
and such kind of materials can also be
very useful
as they can give us information about
the full geomagnetic field vector
including both directional and absolute
intensity data
and that's of course the case when we're
talking about materials still found
in situ we can say that from this point
of view
italy is a quite lucky country is a
country with a very
rich and long cultural heritage with a
lot
and the important archaeological sites
that can be potential offer
a great large number of art magnetic
data
but at the same time italy is
characterized also by a long
and important volcanic activity made due
to the two
important and of course still active
italian volcanoes that
is aetna and vesuvius
so from this point of view and
since many decades a lot of researchers
have done
great work and we have a lot of uh
magnetic investigations coming from
volcanic rocks
well we can say that most recently a
great interest
has also been focused on the study of
archaeological artifacts
nevertheless even though these are among
the most reliable to magnetic field
recorders
still we can say that often errors or
problems
are related with the paramagnetic
records coming from
these records problems that may be
related either to their sampling or to
the
reliability of their rotating or
different to some
disturbances caused by local
and local problems as for example the
strongly magnetized
volcanic areas so for this reason
and in order to be able to collect the
most reliable data
very recently in italy we have tried to
combine
an updated data set uh including only
available up to now data come from both
archaeological material
and organic rocks actually what we have
done is a quite
crazy thing because we have not just
used the global data sets but we try to
retrieve one by one
all the original publications read them
carefully
in order to obtain all those metadata
information that would help us
to evaluate one by one the reliability
of the available data
and when i refer to the reliability and
quality of the reference data
i just i don't just refer to the quality
of the experimental techniques applied
but also the reliability the quality of
the dating
of such of such records we have paint a
particular attention
on their density protocols used
looking trying to understand and and and
find out if
necessary corrections have been applied
so from this compilation and this uh
careful investigation some interesting
results came out
as far as the data from volcanic rocks
are concerned as it was expected
we can see that most of the data come
from the two
active italian volcanoes from ethnic
venus
we have some records from strawberry
which means aeolian islands
and we have also a few data from the ski
eruption
however maybe the most interesting
result is that
we found out that only 57
of the italian volcanic magnetic records
come from well-dated eruptions
which means that almost half of the
available volcanic
data from volcanic rocks come from
eruptions that their traditional age has
been questioned or even
changed based on geological evidence or
automagnetic dating
as far as na are concerned the data from
archaeological artifacts
we can see the data directional data
mostly come
from in sea to bake clay structures
such as skins health ovens while we have
also some data coming from in sea to
burn to sentiments
some burnt walls or some um
validated moral paintings what is
however interesting
is that as far as the density data are
concerned that we know that for
obtaining acure density results it's not
necessary to collect in
situ oriented material still most of the
italian density data come
from in-situ structures such as skins or
ovals
we have some data from historical from
brics
from historical data while only 15
percent
of the available italian intensity data
come
from pottery shells
okay if we plot now the available data
from
italian archaeological sites that you
can see here illustrated with the blue
color
and together with the data with the
volcanic from the volcanic rocks
illustrated here with a red color we can
see that
we will have a quite good agreement
however we can also
very easily notice that most of the
available data
are concentrated the last 3000 years
while if we go back in time
the available data are extremely scarce
actually as far as the density data are
concerned they are extremely
few and for some millennia who have no
data at all
if you have a more careful look at the
data i would say these are
almost the only data available for the
last uh
time period before uh the first million
in bc there are some data coming from
a burnt sentiments published by copper
italia in 2014
well i would like to point your
attention to the oldest
full vector geomagnetic field data that
we have from italy and come
from this interesting archaeological
site of portunovo
i would like to spend some few words on
this
here is the archaeological site of
portonovo as you can see
it is situated in the adriatic coast of
italy and it's quite interesting site as
archaeological excavation
proteolyte a very large number of small
ovens
these are the small circular ovens made
by bay clay that you can see
here if i'm not wrong they were
excavated more than 20
such structures but according to
archaeologists and archaeological
evidence they were probably used for the
production
of food cooking or production
of the cooking of bread so actually one
of the reputation
could be that we have a very big
bakery of the neolithic period more than
7000 years ago
what is particularly interesting from
this site apart from the fact that this
is a very rare example of very well
preserved underground ovens from
neolithic period
the good thing is that archaeologists
have found a great number of
seeds and cereals there so
it can be this site has been very
precisely dated
and it belongs to the early neolithic
period between
5 600 to 5 300 bc
for ecomagnetic investigation we have
collected saints from three
of these ovens that you can see here
just to show you
some very briefly some magnetic
mineralogy results will have
a great low positivity mineral we have
the dominant sources of soft
components and we have obtained also
very nice a different diagrams
uh quite straight lines that
goes through the origin of our diagrams
that gave us also nice
mean direction as you can see here
from this side and we were lucky that it
was possible also to uh have a accurate
density determination thanks to the
collaboration of
my colleague pierre camps from the
montpelier university
that used the multi-specimen method to
obtain
argue density results so actually is the
oldest
full vector data that we'll have from
italy so far
okay going back to our data set as you
can imagine
we have concentrated our interest in the
last three thousand years as for order
periods
the data are extremely scarce to make
any further
considerations and we've tried to apply
some selection criteria in order to
collect
the most reliable data
of course there is a great discussion
which are the best selection criteria to
to apply definitely if we apply very
strict selection criteria that means
that we will keep the best
absolutely the best data but at the same
time
it's most probably that we will erase or
reject
most of our data so in this case we try
to
to find a compromise and we have applied
a selection criteria we have
selected those data that come from a
number of specimens
equal or higher than five and
um i have to say that going back to the
original
publications very often it's not so
clear
the number of specimens and the number
of independently oriented samples
so in this case we have chosen five
a quite large number of spacemen hoping
that this way
most of our results will not come from
just one
single sample okay some selection
criteria based on the alpha 95
angle of confidence and the standard
deviation
the age error was equal or higher than
200 years
and we also paid particular attention on
the acute density protocol
applied i have to say that we have
rejected all volcanic rocks that come
from
eruptions that their age has been
questioned or it's not so reliable
and all those data that were missing
metadata information in order to be able
to evaluate the
reliability asking
you can imagine after this election
criteria a tragedy happened
all great majority of our data were
rejected
so for this reason we have decided
to try to enhance italian data set
with data from nearby countries and
mostly cover the time periods that were
fully investigated in italy with
data coming from sites that are included
in 1 000 kilometers radius
around the terrible mutable is situated
here illustrated with the red
star it's situated more or less in the
center of italy
and using this data from the nearby
countries applying the same selection
criteria with those from the italian
data set who have a total of 594
directional
a data and 94 intensity high quality
reference data
if you have a look on this data you can
see here
these are the with the light blue are
the data coming from
italian archaeomagnetic sites both
archaeological sites and volcanic rocks
while
with the open dark blue dots are the
data from the nearby
countries and you can see that we have a
quite nice agreement
which means that most more or less our
selection container seems to have bored
and we can nicely see some clear
features
of the geomagnetic field vector
as far as the directional data are
concerned
if we have a more careful look on the
density data we can still see that there
are some time periods
where very few data are available mostly
periods before 400 bc but also have an
important gap
around 880.
using this data as reference data
and thanks to the precious help of
felipe lanos
i will have constructed a continuous
smooth circular variation cover curve
covering the last three
three thousand years by using the basin
statistics
as you can see and of course it is
expected
for the time periods where we have a lot
of data the reference
reference curves are well constrained
and accompanied by
um by small uh error envelopes
one it will have a low at the time
periods that you have
a very few data the curves are not well
constrained
and are accompanied by quite large
error envelopes if we compare now these
curves with some of the regional and
global to magnetic field models
we can see we can see a general good
agreement for most of uh of the period
however there are also some important
differences as for example
this um this decrease
in declination that is quite well
constrained by the italian curve
but we cannot clearly see in the models
or some
discrepancies also in the actual density
curves
that of course mainly due to the small
number of the italian reference data
available so for some periods
so i would just
i would like also to have a small
reference or to magnetic dating
as one of the most well-known
applications of arctic magnetism
is arco magnetic dating and i would like
to show you this uh recent the results
of this recent study of this
king that has been excavated at canoza
de gulia in the southern part
of italy actually this is a sandwich
that was carried out almost a year ago
on october
and 2019 and it's actually my last
sampling campaign before being closed at
home for several
months due to this unfortunate covet
maintaining situations so i'm happy to
show you
these results it's a sampling cam
performed in a
collaboration with dr italum tony from
surprise details of pojo and the
archaeologist from
cooperativa archaeology that i would
like to to thank a lot for giving me
this
opportunity to collect material from
this um
from this structure this is a site that
has been excavated and has been
discovered as often
happens during the last day decades due
to
the it's a rescue excavation and found
due to them
walks for a construction of a road
between
android and canosa and as often happens
very often before the the start of
these works there was a preliminary
archaeological
investigation and they were found three
kings i will show just the results from
the first kill
that as you can see is quite well
preserved keen
here we have the performium here is the
main combustion chamber and
this nice arch that we still preserved
and this king was most probably used for
the production of brakes
for archaeomagnetic investigation we
have taken
15 bricks from the main combustion
chamber
all of them oriented in situ with
magnetic and solar compass and
infiniometer
here you can see some of the results
obtained or have a nice
and strong magnetization nice linear
zener diagrams
and we have obtained a mean direction
well constrained mean
direction that then we have used to date
the the last heating of course the last
use
of the skin by comparison with the new
italian circular variation curves
and here you can see the comparison of
the declination
inclination and then here the
combination to probability density
and for the dating we have used the
archaeogetic matlab
tool and we can see that we have three
possible
dated intervals that based on the
archaeological context
of this structure we can say that most
probably
it was last used sometime between 480
and 530 the good thing with this
with this structure is that the
archaeologists going on with their
excavation
they have found in the brief volume of
this
kiln this characteristic rectangular
brick
with this nice sign of p that is
a quite a characteristic it's an
identification sign of the production
workshop
and it can further uh confirms that this
king belongs
more or less to the 5th to 6th century
which means that we are more or less in
the correct way
concluding if i would like to say a few
words about the future
i think the best thing i can say is that
there is still
a lot of work that we have to do
definitely
future research in italy should be
focused
on obtaining new high quality data
if possible reference data from time
periods before
the first millennium bc where the data
will have up to now are very scarce it
would be particularly important to
to try to obtain more high quality
archery density data
and it will be interesting to have more
data about
the beginning of the first millennium bc
in order to try to investigate and to
see
if the iron age levantine anomaly is
also
seen in the italian peninsula and i
would say that would be also very
important to have
full vector uh geomagnetic field data
from
the same well-dated material
definitely a particular rotation should
be always
paid on the dating of the reference data
that
is very important and magnetic data sets
databases and live organisms that should
be continuously
updated and fitted
here are some references and i would
like to thank you very much for your
attention
here you can see a photo from torino of
course it has nothing to do with dark
magnetism but
during these difficult times that we
cannot travel i thought that
magnet seminars could also contribute on
make us
traveling a little bit around the world
thank you so much for your attention
thank you so much here we um
thank you a big round of applause for
every kia
thanks for your presentation um
so if anybody has a question can drop on
the
chat box or raise their hands
and i'm sure fdk would be happy to
answer your questions
so i will jump in with a quick question
because i i as a host i can't actually
raise my hand
but um i i kind of noticed that there is
um a bit of a split uh obviously in
in the distribution of the data north
south because
vesuvius and aetna are are
located in southern italy and
the volcanic data tend to
to come from the younger ages and given
that that essentially your
your data sampling is across a diameter
of about 2 000
kilometers i'm wondering is there is
there any difference
uh between the northern regions and the
southern regions
and can you pick out more fine scale
detail
in in the data sets or is there not
enough data to really look at
that north-south divide
now actually i have not noticed any any
systematic or regular
differences between the the north and
the site
and the the southern part and
i have to say that there is not even
very
big differences between uh automagnetic
data from
archaeological material and volcanic
rocks
what then i i would have tried also to
use a smaller
radius to to be more concentrated to the
italian territory but unfortunately
it didn't enrich a lot our data set you
can see who have
huge huge missing of data but
it is interesting however to know this
is the great as
greg said most of the volcanic rocks
come from recent um
more recent time periods and uh if you
have a look here
we can see that even the data coming
from the very recent
periods almost the last few hundred
years still will have a great discretion
of the data
as far as the density results are
concerned
a lot of these data that you can see
here however come from
qualitative eruptions and the many
researchers have used
these eruptions to to test their density
results or intensity techniques
however yes you have a lot of dispersion
and i also have to
to say that the tragedy that happened
during the rejection of the data
due to quality criteria really um
it was very important as far as the
density data are concerned
and mainly the density data from
volcanic rocks
so do we have uh any uh further
questions
there is one in the chat that i can read
yeah
oh you go so it's uh by elizabeth
uh sandra elizabeth i'm sorry the usual
difference in thermal stability
and therefore also in the stability
reliability
in the data obtained from kills for
breath
for bread baking brick production and
shells
yes the the stability of thermal
remnants magnetization of kings
really is really excellent in
almost all material that i have studied
but also the material from
literature and data from literature they
are very very stable
and i have to say that i have noticed
also the quality of their
intensity data coming from from
bricks and from
kings is really good it's really good
they're not they're very stable probably
heating and reheating and
high temperatures make them particularly
stable
okay thank you i can see richard holm
waving his hands
uh his physical hand not the electronic
hand yeah
um hive doc here um
i um have a slightly different view
generally on selection criteria than
many
um when you do your model what happens
if you test all the data you've rejected
against your model
well the truth is that by rejecting our
data
what happened is that we mostly rejected
data that were clear outliers
and data that even with them
with easy observation would be rejected
because they were really
outside if we take them out
the difference is not such so important
it's not so important what the we
noticed however is that the selection
criteria on the density data
it is much improved then
the agreement among the available data
thank you you're welcome
so we have a question by shelby
so in the chat and she asked when you
were doing their archival work
were you reanalyzing their vector
average or accepting them as it is
i didn't get when i i revised the
previous data if i
revised also the vectors no no no no i
have not
taken the the original
uh measurements i i had no access we had
no access of the original measurements
we just
evaluated the information given in the
original
and papers saying about the reliability
how many specimens
if there were doubts on the
archaeological age
if other works later on changed the
previous psychological age as
sometimes happens also because as far
it's the
reliability of dating it does not
concern only the volcanic rocks very
often
archaeological excavations that go on
more data come
up and so the initial evaluation of the
dating may be
changed or reevaluated as far as more
dating results come
up more excavation findings come up
that's why i say that the database are a
live organism should be continuously
feed it and update it
so um so i just have a follow-up
question
so the the do you reject the site
or the studies that have re-evaluated
the dates
or you just use the re-evaluated dates i
use the re-evaluated dates
yeah and follow up to about that i was
sorry for excuse me for a volcanic rocks
when the dates
were evaluated re-evaluated based on
automagnetic data
they were not included because otherwise
would be a circular reasoning
and obviously now there is a the new
radiocarbon curve
from rhymer 2020 so we kind of have to
re
recalibrate everything that we've done
so
i agree with you it's a living organism
in the database and like max
brown can colleagues can
prove that and also obviously andy begin
so uh sandra elizabethton raised her
hand
uh yeah yeah um no i have a question to
the
you showed your data for the intensity
and i there's for the 400
years you have a gap of 10 microtesla in
your data
so from where you compare like the
literature data
and then your data points and
for one i think for 500 years you have
with two data points and a difference of
around 10 micro tesla
how do you explain that or what do you
think is an
explanation for that you are referring
in this data here
yes yes that's very interesting because
um
particularly for this time period that
has been
i was very curious and it's very sad at
the same time because for this
880 it has been already observed
like in the barrier peninsula a quite
high density
value around 880 and i was particularly
interesting
in this period but unfortunately
we don't have enough data to to make
conclusions
this data one comes from a study in
in france if i'm not wrong and one in
switzerland
and they are they have a different
synthetic i think
less than than 50 years or something
like that
both of these data seems to be of high
quality data
this one gave very high values and this
one
quite low values but i had no re
reason to to reject them okay so yes
thanks about actually referring to the
500 years
of magnetic data now it was a nice
explanation thanks
but uh i was actually not curious about
the 500 years
this difference is quite particular
that's why
you're talking about 580 yeah
this data okay yeah okay this thing has
two data from italy it do from my i'm
not sure if it's france or not
but once again when we went to to to see
what's what's wrong there was no nothing
wrong
that was easy to to
to detect let's say i
i am afraid that very often and
let's say disturbances on the data apart
from
laboratory techniques or laboratory
problems that cannot be detected
it's very often um a problem of the
dating that we cannot
really see it passes it passes very
easily the selection criteria but
maybe it's not so precise
so it's more probably a dating problem
which okay i don't know but it could be
it could be
yes thanks very much you are welcome
thank you uh so we have a follow-up
you want to say something yes i was just
talking about the basic
data i wanted to say that also it's
quite sad that for the
so interesting period of the beginning
of the last millennium we just have one
single data so
anyway more will come more confident
um so we have shelby
asking a follow-up question and
she asks uh did you use the past
magnetic statistical method as a filter
what is the past statistical method
sorry
past magnetic statistical method as a
filter
i i don't know what is the past magnetic
statistical
i'm not quite sure uh
oh here here like the magstep or pcs
pcis yes see
for my for my own data i have used the
principal component
analysis while for the literature
data i just have taken the the mean mean
values calculated by the authors the the
main point of our
update compilation was to understand if
the reliability of these data
uh those data were reliable but
we have not recalculated the
intellectual
data this is certainly be
an an ad value but it's a very time
consuming
and it requires the original data to be
available
which are only available in magic and
not uh
and i don't know what's exact numbers
but i i bet not so many
so shelby says there is a lot of great
work thank you for compiling
this data nice overview from kathy
great work congratulations a success oh
here uh from
despina condo pulo sorry if i
pronounce it wrong a question on 600
800 lack of data
uh yes i'm just surprised to see that
the intensity data have this big
empty space here uh what about the
geneva entire
data of medieval
yes they're here these
are the the very recently published data
by zenith
collaborators in 2002 20. no no no sorry
sorry
no i don't mean the italian data i mean
the french pottery data
which if i remember well are situated
somewhere
around eight hundred and one on
and because most of the french data are
included
in your confidence circle so
if i recall well uh there should be data
around between 800 and 1000 from french
pottery
and i can go back to the original
publication anyway uh just an
observation
we have the same difficulty in obtaining
intensity
data from greece within
the period 600 800
because of several reasons there
is a lack of material and in this way
we cannot catch the supposed
high value around 700 to 800
but i will really i'm very surprised
that we look to the literature
sorry for this gap anyway thank you for
your nice presentation of nokia
we have the opportunity to talk about
that later or in another one
thank you so much thank you so much it's
interesting yes
it's interesting it's sad that there are
not a lot of data for that
period i have to say that the selection
criteria applied about the five
specimens cut off a lot of data as well
then the selection criteria
rejected a lot of data most of them
because of the smaller number of
specimens
and then and
then
[Music]
the standard deviation value but mostly
because of the small number of specimens
thank you we have a question of max
brown that i almost missed
sorry so he asked can you comment on
whether the
bayesian model fit over fits the data
could a simpler model have a good fit
we haven't tried it tried another model
who have tried
the space and reconstruction and i think
it fits quite a while the data but
of course it fits well the data when we
have a lot of data
when we don't have a lot of data it
doesn't
fit also here with the two results you
can see we have a very
um large error envelope and
also in other time periods it cannot
perfectly fit the data but when you have
a lot of data
i think it fits well
thank you so uh we have a a question
from javier and then
andrei costa of ray say his hand so
[Music]
trm data with the historical data set
within your spherical region like junker
at
2003 or eastmac database
if if i have used historical data that's
the question
because uh the question sorry for the
last three four centuries have you
compared the
trm data with historical data set within
your spherical region
no we no we have not used either in the
either in the calculation or in the
comparison the historical data actually
uh for these very recent periods uh
we have just used in all our caps are
based only on
archaeomagnetic data either from
archaeological material or for volcanic
roots
and historical data are not included
okay thank you andrei
thank you for this nice nice talk
i wonder uh did you try to
plot your intensity data as a function
of
the material you use for
for intensity i mean separately for
kilns uh barter resent etc
that's a good idea no we don't wanna
it would be really interesting to see
because
and your data set is a nice thing
to uh to do that because it's very rare
that
you have so at let's several types of
material in the same location
maybe you do it in the future yeah that
would be also interesting to see
how reliable are for example the
determination from potter or from kings
yeah that's that that was my point
actually yeah
that's a nice idea yeah great thank you
thank you good talk yeah
okay thank you uh is anybody else have
questions
if so i guess i have one quick sort of
follow on just from from andre's comment
i mean
um what consideration have you given to
the corrections or lack of corrections
for
you know cooling rates and isotropy and
these kind of things
especially cooling rate because it's a
really tricky one to
you know pin down how much of a
correction should be
uh should be applied and i guess that's
kind of probably what
one andre is kind of getting out by
looking at the different materials as
well
yeah that would be important to have
both an isotropic correction and cool
grade correction
i have to say that the most of the
recent data both corrections
are are included so that's a quite good
thing
also in some older data these
corrections have been
somehow it or take any consideration
then the biggest problem is with the
oldest data that in most cases
miss both anisotropy and cool grade
and mainly when we refer to data from
pottery or even well-shaped bricks or
tiles
then then isotropic correction could be
also very important
very important so definitely there is a
lot of
work to do as far as density studies in
italy is
are concerned we have very few data
and um sometimes not
the best one so they will have to get
concentrated
and do much more job on that
it's time consuming
the low success rate rate that can
be some disadvantages but we'll have to
do it
thank you we feel you the one we're
working with the
intensity intensity
yeah we know what you've been through
okay so anybody else has questions
for now we don't um
i i may have questions but we can
i want to leave a room for others
okay then um so the
uh it's interesting how we all struggle
with selection criteria
and they still remain really
subjective um of course as you said
the most strict criteria we use the last
day that we have
that's kind of a given it's expected
um but the in while selecting
um the this previous studies
i was wondering if you can use kind of
several sets of criteria and they weight
them in a way that you consider all the
data you have rather than just get rid
of them
in a way cut them off kind of give them
a weight
rather than just have you have you
thought of it have you done something
that's something that very often uh
we observe in the publications and many
people apply this
way thing on the data and that's a good
idea we have
not done it there also because um we
what it just to be sure that we have
the best data as far as as it is
possible
of course keeping more data even if they
are waiting
less could be good to have a much richer
uh more data available but um
we decided here that we should work on
the best
data possible according to this
selection retail of course if we were
more strict
it will be even the best data but
the number would be very few very very
small what is interesting however with
selection criteria is the
the the errors on in dating that usually
we use a cut off
a cut-off criterium based on the
interval of dating
like one two hundred to er one hundred
two hundred years
but then it's difficult to to understand
how reliable is this dating
so many data that are not so
well dated past this standard selection
criteria
and we use them for modeling of global
data sets that's
i think it's important problem as far as
magnetic data are concerned and it's a
problem that cannot be
easily solved because we don't have
direct control on the dating or in the
on the updating of dating as time passes
okay thank you and i was wondering also
about
how you dealt with the problem of the
different methods that have been used
uh beyond the teletalia
methods i don't know how you treat them
and weight them or did you consider them
all as
no actually uh we were from this point
of view were quite
lucky let's say that most of the of the
data from uh
italy nearby the countries come from the
old reacts method or multi-specimen
what we we did and we try to pay
attention
of if we are dealing with the method to
be sure that
an isotropic correction or some other
corrections have been taken into
consideration
and more or less we try to individually
evaluate the reliability of data we
haven't
used such a cut off
criteria
okay thank you so anybody else has
questions
otherwise we can switch to
uh the informal part of the talks
oh yoga's as questions yes yeah
sorry i have a question uh with respect
to the quality of the
data from this neolithic kiln which
was used for baking bread and with the
quality of the
other kiln which is used to to make
bricks so with respect to the
temperatures because
to bake bread you you don't need such a
high temperature
is there any difference in the in the
quality
well there has been a study about the
heating temperatures of this
of these structures in fact uh we are
not talking about very high temperatures
it was
if i remember well around 5 400
450 degrees but
we still it was heated enough to give us
a i think
nice directional results but
definitely the data from the the kin and
the temperatures
arrived in the gill where um
much higher uh we're talking about
temperatures higher than 600
degrees and the magnetization was much
stronger
much stronger in this case
but once again we have nice nice
nice directional results nice
mean value well constrained
okay thank you so maybe greg
you can rub up now
yeah there we go um so now thank you
everyone for for coming in thank you
uh for a fantastic talk uh today i
want to take this chance to thank um all
of our speakers
um for for 2020 uh i've actually i've
lost count how many we've had i think
this is the ninth or tenth um but if
if you want to uh catch up on any of the
uh speakers that we've had this year um
most of the videos now are available on
on youtube
and we have more information on our uh
magnets website which is hosted with
earthref um so please um have a look and
catch up with some of the
presentations that you might have missed
there um this today's presentation will
be uploaded
uh to the website shortly and it will
have um
a doi so if you find anything
interesting or useful
in this presentation or any of the other
presentations uh it is a citable object
uh and and you can give
[Music]
the kia and all of our presenters credit
for their uh excellent and hard work
um just a bit of a heads up for
the schedule uh uh into next year so in
december we're going to have
a break um because agu will be taking up
most of december with
their fall meeting um we will come back
in in 2021 now here in the uk
at the very beginning um of uh january
we will typically host
uh our uk magnetic interactions our
local domestic meeting
um this year because of of lockdown we
can't
hold that meeting in person so we will
be holding a virtual
uh version of this and we're going to be
hosting parts of it through
uh the magnets uh seminar platform um so
please keep your eyes open
for uh any announcements for that um
we will be opening up um attendance
uh to the international community and
for people who are interested
in finding out what kind of science the
magnetic community is
is doing in the uk um but there should
be more information coming out about
that
in the next uh couple of weeks so please
keep your eyes open
uh sorry anita yes there is also the
magic meeting that you may have seen in
the gpm it's the 19 to the 21 it's on
zoom as well available for everybody
it's free and it's going to be a good uh
three days of talks and and things you
can email me or
need or anybody for more information
thanks greg sorry no thank you i forgot
to put that one on i was a little bit
late at making these slides this
afternoon
um but um we'll be kicking off the the
main
series of of the magnet seminars at some
point either in february or into march
uh next year and so we're looking for
um speakers for the 2021
uh magnet seminar so if anybody is
interested in giving a presentation
please uh reach out to either myself or
anita uh we can start uh arranging the
uh schedule for 2021. um and as always
um we are always welcome to uh feedback
any ideas or criticisms um
and suggestions that folks have for
magnets um
and once again just thank you everyone
for for joining