welcome to the magnet seminars
uh these magnets are hosted by myself
anita dicker and greg patterson
with the help of um uh michael grafoni
and nick
nick van der bon and richard bono and
that we think and the logo is by simon
lloyd
the seminal format is as usual uh it's
25 minutes presentation
uh where everybody's invited to keep
microphone
off and then after that would be
10 15 minutes question discussion uh
text questions always welcome and we
will leave time
uh to answer to the speaker and you're
invited to have um
to write in the chat nomic if you want
to
to read your question up it's an
informal environment so if you need to
go
don't worry about it the semis are
recorded
and there is gonna be time to catch up
as usual after the seminar and that's
not going to be recorded
so um joining me in welcoming today's
speaker is andrey coster from saint
peter's book
some petersburg state university and
and andre is going to talk about
magnetic minerals in archaeological
ceramics
old wine skins and new wine
okay you're welcome to share your screen
i will myself
all right right moment
does it work now can you see my screen
yes thank you great thank you i needed
wakes
thank you very much for having me here
for making
the seminar and i would like to
acknowledge my
uh collaborators on this project from
sofia
maria castadine and maria
and my also my colleagues from saint
peter's
institute in saint petersburg and
through moscow
and as you as we all know the
empty electromagnetism is a
subject of geomagnetism with long and
distinguished history so
okay next slide yeah
[Music]
and the field
and the field is uh alive and vibrant
uh these days and very recently
recently this month a feature article
has been published in
physics world which is a newsletter for
institute of physics uk which got very
appropriately digging up
magnetic clues and those clues um of
course the
behavior of the magnetic field of the
[Music]
centennial and millennial scale which is
of so much interest to
geodynamo model models but
one phrase in this otherwise very
very good readable account has
stopped my attention i read it
i know the field of archaeomagnetism
relies on the fact
that clay so uh
other materials containing magnetic
mirrors
usually magnetites and so forth and i
highlighted two words here which i don't
agree with
because
[Music]
definitely the materials that
conceited our artifacts do contain the
magnetic mirrors but uh
but but it's not always the case for for
the starting material
if we understand it this way and that's
the second and most serious
misconception is that
the this magnetic mirror is claimed to
be magnetite which is
which which is simply
not true in most in most cases
not in all cases i would i will see
come to it later but in most cases it's
true and so
this brings us back to the
[Music]
to the medium that keeps our records
and without which we could not have this
record at all
this brings up to the magnetic
meterology of the
archaeological artifacts and it's a bit
it came to me as a bit of surprise that
when i started working on this topic
that
the serious attention to the magnetic
meteorology has
has not begun until near approximately
mid 90s when these three papers
with this
italian titles have been published and
at that time and even the first
experiments has shown that
something very very different from what
we
normally expect in environment examples
is often observed in
artifacts in this figure you can see the
one of the samples from huge
collection kept in sofia
and the three axis lower
test shows a very uh
tremendous drop of heart
[Music]
to tesla component of monetization below
below something like 240 degrees
centigrade
and if then if you look at the
irm acquisition curve we see that um
we see that
at least half of the monetization is
acquired
above 300 milli test
at that time the authors
[Music]
preferred the preferred to call this
phase geotight
which is of course cannot be true
because since
then this brick would consist 50 percent
of good height
which is which
which is not possible of course and
so we have to seek for um
alternative explanations so that
that's it for it and it took another
roughly 10 years that this phase
demagnetizing below 200 degree
centigrade it has
has been recognized as a separate entity
and called high conservative
thermally stable low and working
temperature magnetic phase by
making persian dollars and
more recent studies has shown that this
this phase is uh very often seen in
in bricks tiles portraits
and so forth from
many locations around even more recently
spanish groups joined with america
again they has suggested they
have suggested that this
h acslt phase could be
it could be related to a particular
polymorphic form of iron three oxide
which is called
epsilon iron three oxide
okay just uh to summarize this
introduction
um what do we know from
about the magnetic neurology of
archaeological artifacts
they all they always contain a soft
magnetically soft face and uh
very often one or two magnetically hard
phrases for magnetic
[Music]
magnetic analysis normally a yoga yield
yields security temperatures around
above
500 degrees centigrade which is
compatible with many type of
she might but on the other hand
the very transition which is would be
indicative of stopping
has been seldom reported
never reported from ceramics and finally
they allow three exercise and tests to
reduce
the quite often reveals the magnetic in
the
heart face without walking temperatures
around two below 200 degrees centigrade
sometimes like
so instead of
[Music]
sometimes single minerals examples we
have to deal with at least three
magnetic phases which uh
magnetic maximize hematite and
also a this hc slt phase
all mixed in various proportions
depending on
and so um on the
uh yet another consideration is that
uh starting material for making ceramics
doesn't contain
those minerals nobody well nobody knows
[Music]
and so those magnetic phases has has to
be produced
during the firing process
uh whether it was intentional or not
and so we can hope that uh
by by investigating the language
we can learn something about the making
of the manufacturing
process as well so
this was a background of our project
that's used to
the samples back wait wait for a break
from archaeological
sites in bulgaria very rich
they have very rich selection
in there and also some breaks from
more recent times in russia
[Music]
mostly the second meeting in bc
andre i apologize for interrupting but
um could you talk just
um facing forward to the microphone it's
just it's yeah
yeah the hearing is a bit problematic
yeah okay i'll try
yeah and the methods we we used apart
from the standard
error magnesium method both the irm
acquisition and dc demagnetization
curves measured at high temperatures up
to
well up to above 600 but actually it
depends on the sample of course
also we measured some magnetic curves
in the cryogenic temperature range from
two kelvin to
room temperature and also acquired the
hysteresis loops and dcd curves
will filter the several tesla fields
which is
which is essential uh when i'm working
with syrix now
briefly to the results and here
you can see the room temperature uh
seven tesla heights with this loops so
uh
roll side black correct uh
corrected for hyphen slope i
immediately see that uh this hot face is
really hard
we we don't saturate the monetization
even in seven tesla fields and the loops
are
open until until three or four tesla
and of course uh just comparing
the comparing the figurative
points that they plot from
seven tesla loops and from one point
eight test
loops we can see that the name for uh
for the same
for the same specimen they could uh
plot in quite different parts of the
diet
and about the only
thing about the only thing in common is
that
we have relatively high mls over
medication and relatively high
acidity we should expect
from a mixture of soft and hard faces
so now
more
more advances
monetization versus temperature here
here i plot srm and higher which is the
simpler
[Music]
part
are their ratio and we can see that the
in this uh
those samples those samples from
bulgaria were selected specifically
to contain the hcs phase
but still we can see that they behave
they all
have this decrease of uh
hrms elimination towards
200 centigrade but afterwards the
behavior could be
quite different and in at least three of
these samples
we also have a significant
hematite phase about the same in
in two out of four samples from
uh russia sampled in uh
near yara's level but
there are also other samples that's that
are magnetic
also magnetically hard but still they
don't have
much of the hcl something okay
and have something like substituted
quite strongly substituted hematite
up to about maybe 300 or
400 degrees centigrade and then it
goes steadily down so it should
must be some form of some form of hammer
effect
now just with the
if we look at the temperature dependence
of the
caustivity uh we know in the hcs
anti-phases where a phase which is the
way it is
the most interesting we can say we can
typically observe
we typically observe the behavior that's
the
cause of force drops quite sharply
between
uh 40 degree centigrade and 160 and then
a little little sound and the
anatomy of these behaviors that is
is very straightforward in at room
temperature and
slightly above where the
zero magnetization axis is caused in the
heart phase
but starting at approximately
probably at 180 which is shown there is
a bold yellow yellow curve
the the crossing occurs already in the
soft phase
and uh so the costs
above 1 180 are more almost
indistinguishable
so my uh my favorite
my otherwise favorite uh technique they
will
tell them unfortunately for ceramics it
does not produce
anything uh
evidence for what these phases are
apart from maybe the uh
from hematite
maybe hematite in 2020
and to sum up
we do have acslt phase and
another the second part of the talk
would be
[Music]
and so just
epsilon iron oxide as i've known
the material science
is a peculiar uh polymorphic
form of iron three oxide
which crystallizes in the earth often on
the
[Music]
at room temperature exceeding one
exceeding two teslas in most perfect
cells
and in this very carefully orchestrated
synthesis
[Music]
one can obtain uh four
uh four polymorphic forms of iron iii or
oxide depending on the uh
calcination temperature which is which
shows
here which is shown here with
numbers and another
important uh takeaway from this
from this study is that
[Music]
epsilon iron oxide has a very narrow
stability uh stability field in terms of
grain size
after the particles larger than
30 nanometers again
once again in this highly perfect
highly very perfect perfect
synthetic root particles
larger than 30 nanometers had become
unstable and transformed first
bitter iron outside and finally to
hammer
what is and
also the at that time to the temperature
of the
epson phase was believed to have to be
around 500
kelvin but it all um
it was cast
with this paper by garcia muniz and the
others who
who showed that in fact this feature is
not uh
is not a real curry temperature but
rather
the temperature which shows where the
transition
comes from between two phases
which which are both ordered very
magnetically but
in a different way and the absolute what
we
what is known as epsilon 3
absolute hard phrase it has much higher
magnetization
and much higher core series than the
high temperatures but still the high
temperature phase has according to
up to 40 million
and not not non-negligible
uh magnetization which might maybe of
importance in
in the context of archaeomagnetism of
course
so uh a bit more a bit more
from the literature at cryogenic
it's in a very straight strange way
it has a quite
decent coarsivity at 4 kelvin
about 700 milli tesla then
the hysteresis nearly collapses at
between
85 and 100 kelvin and then develops in
the
group which is
[Music]
which is a trademark of this
iron oxide at room temperature the
facilities
as i talked about to test the
susceptibility versus temperature of the
[Music]
temperature depends it would be
could probably serve as a uh
as a discriminant for
started with a
highest resistance measurement and it
has
much smaller cursivity but still the
corset is
above 100 milli tesla apart apart from
this
range around 100k and
so even so that means that
even the smallest epsilon particles
could be
it could carry the magnetic signal at
room temperature
so all this
all these previous measurements have
been done at highly perfect
highly perfect material using the
approaches that are
common in magnetic material sense and so
we decided to
perhaps that perhaps we could produce
less perfect and
the less perfect material that would
resemble
the archaeomagnetic sample a bit more
and so we did we did that using the
quick and
dirty method so in which where the
silica gels were
impregnated two different silica gels
were impregnated with a precursor
on the precursor and then they cosined
at
900 degrees centigrade for four hours
there you can see that depending on the
gel
you used the samples uh
different color but that one contains
obviously more hematite
as you can see in the thermo magnetic
curve
as well and that one contains uh
obviously less temperature and
we also we also see
that the transition temperature of
epsilon phase is a bit different
in these two cases but
the on the other hand they have to be
this properties
at room temperature has shown something
something really very very strange
particularly for this
bronzer for example it's well it's
more or less similar to what we would
expect
in serene in some ceramics at least
consider it is high but
but not as high as you as you would
expect for perfect synthetic capsule
epsilon phase conservative remnants is
also
quite high and higher than we normally
see
but otherwise this sample resembles a
little bit
a little bit the behavior we saw in
there
in the surrounding circles but the brown
sample
is a is an enigma for for us at the
moment
and uh i i plotted it here just
uh just to show what could happen
uh and obviously
it has
we can see here the result of uh
coexistence of uh
two phases with extremely contrasting
coercivity the recursive force
on the major loop is about
four marker tesla but the loop is
uh remains open up to four uh
sorry milli tesla of course the military
but the loop itself
remains open uh
up to four tests and
on the other hand okay from here we
could
we could hope that red sample could be
some kind of analog to archaeological
samples
brown sample problem is probably
uh not so good and i like because
no and nobody would see we
[Music]
temperature the measurement
graduating temperature
[Music]
shows that uh red sample shows both
more in tradition what would expect
and also this this maximum at
around 100 cannon could be related to
absolute phase
on the other hand low temperature curves
are
nearly featureless so if you
[Applause]
inspect them closely you'll see some
plateau around 100 and some kind of
transition signal some kind of signature
for
transition but nothing else brown sample
is
absolutely crazy and i don't i still
don't know if it's
the instrumental artifact or not but
just to
i'm showing just to for uh
to account for this to account for this
for this particular experiment okay
now uh we can also compare the
results of our archaeology magnetic
samples
directly with no with known
data for for statistics using the
hysteresis measurements at graduate
temperature we did that for uh
for a few samples and for all of them
we see just a monotonous decrease of
coarsivity between five kelvin and true
temperature nothing
no collapse of high speed and also the
the remnants uh deduced from
customers slope follows very closely the
dk curves of the of the raman is given
at
1.8 tesla so
there there seem to be quite a
discordance between
the observations done on synthetic
epsilon
epsilon iron oxide and on
ceramic ceramic samples respectively
one possible way to
[Music]
resolve it to to
bring this this data to close
to closer agreement is to suppose that
uh
epsilon facing the
archaeological samples is i finally
substituted
this battle but this of course needs
further
investigation now much look for epsilon
phase and
we are getting back to magnetite and um
just maybe one month ago i would i would
say magnetite is never observed in
archaeological circles but
never say never recently they started a
few a few samples from
ireland page sites in bulgaria and they
are
they showed quite nice the retransition
the doubled one even in this case and
also
interesting thing about this to say
these two samples
is that gca curve runs
higher than fc which is a which is
obviously
an indicator of a rather large grain
size of magnetite in this particular
cell
this particular sample and that that
magnetite
[Music]
to me it's not very likely that it could
fall in city and
it could be inherited from
from the starting the
starting material for this source right
so i i would conclude also on the
few takeaways as a
just following the following this stream
and um the main the major problem about
the the magnetic meteorology of
archaeological artifacts is either
origin is the identity of the
hcslt phase and the comparison between
the
properties of archaeological samples and
the properties of synthetic epsilon
oxide shows that
these properties are quite dissimilar
and particularly particularly cryogenic
temperatures
and um
probably one possible
possible explanation would be to
allow for some metal substitution
in natural samples but but again
that has to be studied experimentally
this absolutely has to be studied
experiment
uh second uh
related to this hcs
is that in the light of uh
discovery of uh garcia muniz and others
can it carry
remains above the temperature of its
airplane disappears from the record
and does it really disappear
that shall also need to be
[Music]
that does also need to be seen in the
future
and uh i still insist that
stoichiometric magnetite seldom because
in
syringes and baked clay
and on the other hand if it's still
if it's still found in some samples it
can be
can be used this is an inference for
some particular conditions of
[Music]
these samples and
have seen in the past so thank you very
much for your attention
yep i think i'll stop here
thank you very much thank you very much
thank you
uh let's give a big round of applause
to andre thank you very much um
we are now open for questions
um if you want you can drop a question
in the chat or you can ask yourself
[Music]
some questions
so i guess the i will i will start with
the
with the curiosity oh so
that the late the last slide was really
interesting because it summed up
really what what you did so far do you
plan to
uh to to
uh deepen the study of this epsilon
magnetite
you cannot mute yourself yes yeah yeah i
do
[Music]
well this uh this synthetic samples are
shown
obtained just within last few weeks
and so of course we well
one idea is to start to add some
metals apart from iron to this uh
synthesis
and i didn't tell i didn't tell that
in the presentation but this um
in the material science they add some
alkali earth to earth
most often barium just to
produce the
pausing this pause in the situation
which are exactly of the
size of the stability of epsilon phase
and
by this and it's by this method they
obtain the particles that are very
perfect in shape and you have the
course evidence in excess of two tests
now good test
but in natural samples i think that
we can we cannot exclude that uh we have
we could have some
cancer or magnesium
you know in our rocks and uh i'm
wondering if
this this light outer layers
methods metals could uh work in the
similar way
another thing is that just
we have we have several uh candidates
mental candidates for uh
which could substitute irons and
it's as yet it's
not known what would happen with these
particular metals
there are once again in materials
they they use the substitutions for
completely different purposes
and not with matters we would like to
them to study particularly not with
titanium
and but but in the recent study
the in the recent study
team for a team spanish team that
discovered the high temperature phase of
epsilon oxide
did they did the same using the chromium
substitute
the epsilon phase and the transition
temperature
unexpectedly goes down which is
which is fine
which we would have hoped for and also
but the
but the high temperature phase also
exists in this substitute that
absolute oxide as well so it's um
so it's a quite
rich field for further study yes
yeah with important implications for
sure
greg here the question i do have a
question but
uh despina has has one as well so we'll
let we'll let her ask first
sorry i didn't see the hand raised i
apologize the spinner
uh and don't apologize because i'm very
bad in
uh in all this stuff so um
my question to andre is first only this
research is very
interesting and i read your paper
yesterday so i have a
let's say an overall view but what i
would like to ask you
is uh very elementary about the choice
of your
uh collections i mean you choose one
collection from bulgaria
and one from russia the first one is
mostly
uh neolithic with a couple of roman
bricks
the second one is medieval bricks from
russia
and then it seems that there are
differences between these groups
can can you tell us a few words uh i
mean this is a
difference it cannot be geographical so
the
is the environment from where these
collections come which is different
or what i would very much like to
to have an answer to that maybe through
an email i mean you don't need to
reply now yeah well that's
a very good question yeah and
but uh
well we uh yeah we worked primarily
with bulgarian samples just because they
they were this is probably the
best collection around the world
i cannot hear you andre i cannot wait
i'm so i'm
i'm so i'm sorry i'm trying to suggest
much better it's better yeah great okay
the bulgarian collection is
uh obviously one uh probably the
the the best available collection yes
10 years old 20 years or 50 years yes
yeah and just uh
russian samples were included because
they we did see
some interesting interesting difference
between the burger and russian samples
particularly
those two that have uh those two that
have the this hc salty place have it
the properties is a little bit different
that temperature at which
that this phase disappears from the okay
the disappearance is
[Music]
maybe as low as 120 or 140 degrees
centigrade which is lower than in
bulgarian samples
there was also some few samples from
novgorod which
did which have seen when we saw them
[Music]
both epsilon was hclp base
and domina but they were dominately
dominated by hematite
so so we tried to
[Music]
find more as much as different samples
as we could simply
because well i think one two 120 is
probably the lowest
temperature the lowest temperature at
which this
uh slt
acs ultra phase disappears
ever reported so basically the reason
was that
yeah thank you why why there are so much
and to me the difference those
differences are quite big
and but we still don't have clear
answer or why maybe i will contact you
through an email because i have maybe
a couple of other questions but not now
thank you andrei
thanks a lot thanks magnet for starting
collaborations
we see that coming yeah that would be
great yeah
so um thank you thank you so bruce has a
question as well
raised hand andre uh interesting
interesting talk you know that epsilon
phase
must be related to the actual clay
composition
in the original pot that got fired
and that epsilon phase seems to form
from iron rich smectite clays
for the dehydration of those clays at
high temperature
where probably not titania but aluminum
calcium
uh might be more important
iron substitution of that yeah
yeah we have to look into it
yeah because unfortunately
the problem is that the claims also are
not always known
for archaeological uh
artifact particularly for more ancient
ones so
right it might be a problem
that's uh that could be uh that was
that is what you could look into using
this russian collection because
particularly this year's level
collection it comes from
[Music]
churches which were erected between
in 18th century mostly and so in the in
this
case we can try to track the
sources from docking so it might be
it's good it's a good idea good thing to
do
and we'll try to we'll try that yeah
i know your paper there that you you hit
the non-tonight
and uh ended up with something similar
yeah yeah that yeah that was 35 years
back we saw progress i know that but
well and uh yet another
there was yet another study in materials
that also he
known tonight and ended up and
[Music]
obtained also absolute like phrase
but unfortunately no magnetics was done
on that
but uh that that has to be investigated
yes
yeah thanks you
thank you thank you anybody else with a
question i can't see all
all of you but uh you cannot mute
yourself you you do have a question
greg do you have a question
um yeah so i guess my kind of question
is is how
might you expect this so you describe
the epsilon phase as having
an apparent curing temperature which is
maybe related to to
a change in the phase um how
might you expect that to manifest in
a remnants experiment like a paleo
intensity experiment for example
well i would rather hope
it would not have a great effect because
the high temperature phase of high
temperature epsilon
is much weaker than the low temperature
and
hopefully it wouldn't be
in the reals in the real samples i
i would believe it would not be
distinguishable from
make hematite or hematite
because the conservative range would be
approximately the same
but it would be it would be curious to
investigate that in
in synthetics well there was a
recently the uh
the same spanish group that that i
mentioned
published the paper
[Music]
where they tried their tried to do that
silly experiment on the highly highly
perfect synthetic sample
this is uh this is the lopez sanchez and
dallas
2020 but unfortunately the their partner
was
[Music]
dispersed in epoxy which could not be
heated above
235 and 235 degrees centigrade so
we we still don't know what would happen
we still don't know what would happen in
highlighter for example we still don't
know what would happen in
sample like all right but yeah we can
it's something that we have in mind to
try
thank you very much i guess this was the
last question because we don't have
much uh uh space for another one but you
you you can share email after that
yes yes so um so the
and we have some uh schedule already
line up
uh the next um the next seminar is going
to be with jay
shah taking us into space somewhere
again
and then the 14th of april we're gonna
have andrea biedermann
and then we're gonna take a break for
the egu and we hope to do
and eastern hemisphere time slot uh
in in the same month together with the
eu
so we we are working on that and if you
have any suggestion
uh comments if you want to give a talk
with us you can
feel free to contact us thank you very
much all for coming