welcome hi everybody um welcome to
um the next um in our 2021 series of of
the magnet seminars
uh we've been going strong for quite a
while and and we had some really great
uh support from our community so thank
you everybody uh for coming along and
thank you to
um all of our pre presenters uh past
present and future
um just a quick reminder for those who
haven't joined us before
um the magnet seminars are 25-minute
30-minute
presentations so we kindly ask that you
keep your microphones uh muted
um and during the the presentation and
if you have uh problems with your
internet connection um turning off your
video can can help improve that
um after the seminar we'll have um time
for our 10 to 15 minute
question session and discussion session
and questions are are welcomed via the
um text chat as well as via the
microphone um
if you don't want to speak um with the
microphone please just type into the
chat no mic
and i myself or one of our co-hosts will
um i read out the question um for you
and as always we've got our um our lives
going on around us
in in still in the midst of a global
pandemic
so if you do have to get up and go uh
halfway through please
just um get up and go it's absolutely
fine
and at the end of the the seminar we
have some time uh for a bit of a catch
up a bit of a social
um um time for us to chat with each
other and just
see how everybody is is getting on and
this part of the
the seminar series isn't actually
recorded so you won't have to
you can unmute and you can show your
video
um so today we have uh beck strauss
who is from uh not only from nist but
also from nasa
um and they will be talking about um
constraining uh the moon's magnetic
field from
the analysis of apollo samples so beck
thank you very much for
uh speaking today
thanks very much for having me let me
see if i can share my screen
okay we see in my slides all right
perfect
great um thank you again for having me
today it's a little bit intimidating to
follow lisa tookes but i will do my best
again for those who haven't met me
before i'm beck strauss my pronouns are
they them theirs
and i am a term research scientist at
nist currently on detail to nasa goddard
space flight center
so today i'm going to talk with you a
little bit about how we can use apollo
samples
to study the decline of the moon's
magnetic field
so measurements from orbiters landers
and portable magnetometers at the moon
have told us
that the moon does not have a strong
magnetic field in the present day
and in fact these uh these measurements
generally agree
that the surface field intensity there
is on the order of somewhere less than
one
nanotesla which is pretty weak and for
paleomagnetic purposes
we can think of the modern moon as
essentially a zero field environment
now the big exception to this is some
regions of magnetized crust or crustal
anomalies
some of which are associated with
features like craters and lunar swirls
and we can take these as evidence that
the moon must have had a much stronger
magnetic field
in the past to understand the history of
that field
we've been working with material from
the apollo sample suite which is made up
of more than 2 000
rock regolith and core samples collected
by the apollo astronauts and returned to
earth
these collections are now available
primarily through johnson space center
and the captain program
which has recently changed to xmag the
extraterrestrial materials analysis
group
when i think about studies of lunar
paleomagnetism it's uh most helpful to
conceptualize them on a timeline so
here i've got billions of years before
the present on our x-axis with the
present-day all the way to the right
and paleo intensity or the strength of
the ancient field on the y-axis in
microteslas please note that that is a
log scale
there are two kinds of data on this plot
first the
filled shapes indicate actual records of
ancient magnetic fields
and the open shapes indicate maximum
intensities those fields could have had
based on the recording limits of the
associated samples which i'll come back
to in a little bit
so i want to point out some big trends
in this collection of data to help guide
your eye through how we usually
interpret it
there is a generally recognized high
field period when
the moon's magnetic field reached
surface intensities um
of an average of 77 microteslas
somewhere between 3.56 and 3.5
3.85 billion years ago excuse me
subsequent to the high field period a
series of studies established that there
was no longer any evidence for fields
stronger than about four microteslas
by around 3.19 billion years ago
now from that information alone we can
start constructing this kind of generic
schematic curve this is not quantitative
this is purely intended to guide your
eye through the data
so a few years ago another study came
out that found an actual record
of a roughly five microtesla field in a
much younger sample
dated to somewhere between one and two
billion years old and a study that was
published
last year in 2020 showed that there was
no evidence for fields any stronger than
about 0.1 microteslas by a half a
billion years ago
so that was a lot all at once the main
thing that we're interested here
interested in here is that the
paleomagnetic data from apollo samples
seems to indicate
the moon's field didn't just up and turn
off one day
rather it went through a couple of
periods of decline
we're really interested in these dynamic
changes in
the intensity of the lunar field because
intensities of magnetic fields tell us
something about planetary interiors
a whole bunch of mechanisms at least a
dozen have been proposed to explain
why the moon had a strong magnetic field
at some point and what might have
happened to it and i'm just going to
mention a few of the major ones here
some studies have looked into chemical
convection dynamos or impact generated
dynamo systems
which would have been able to account
for fields on the order of maybe seven
to ten microteslas but wouldn't have
lasted much past
3.8 billion years ago other studies have
looked into precession dynamos where the
interior and exterior portions of the
moon could have been decoupled and moved
relative to each
other and that motion and the associated
stirring might have been enough to
generate the currents we need for
magnetic fields
that could have given us field strengths
on the order of 100 micro teslas and
would have lasted till
maybe 2 billion years ago depending
whose model you like for how far
the moon was from the earth at any given
point in time
and still other studies have looked at
thermochemical convection similar to
what we have on the earth today
this would have been able to sustain
fields on the order of five or six micro
teslas till maybe a billion years ago
tops
so you may be looking at this end
rightly saying to yourself there is not
very much data on this plot
what that means is we really need to
keep an eye on small number statistics
problems and make sure we're not
creating these big assertions out of a
statistical anomaly
so i want to answer a couple of
questions in this study the first is
did the lunar dynamo really decline
after 3.56 billion years ago
or are we suffering from a small amount
of data could there be methodological
problems or issues with our materials
and second if the dynamo did decline
what happened to it
what kind of change in mechanism could
explain this
this change in state that we observe to
answer these
questions we need to work with samples
that are capable of recording weak
magnetic fields
after 3.2 billion years ago so that
brings us to
a case study using some apollo 12
basalts this is
primarily work that i did with sonya
tiku while we were both at rutgers
university
and we just had it published in the
journal of geophysical research planets
so we'll start with a field map for the
field geologists in the room uh this is
the location where our samples were
collected at the apollo 12 landing site
please pardon the truck noise in the
background
um all three samples were collected from
the sort of upper left edge of this
image and i have photos from a couple of
the locations where our samples were
picked up
unfortunately i don't have a photo for
where the third sample was collected and
this i think is a point in favor of
sending more geologists to the moon
because we know to take a picture before
we mess with the field site
so these are the actual samples that we
worked with we got much smaller pieces
of course these are each about the size
of the palm of your hand these are
apollo 12 samples 12008-12009
and 12015 and just for fun uh after all
of the analyses i did take a couple of
photos of me holding the samples
you may notice that each of our little
sub-sample slices has an orienting arrow
on the disk to which it's attached and
this is because we wanted to preserve
the relative orientation of subsamples
from each of our main samples
even though the bulk samples themselves
were not oriented on collection
okay so all three of these rocks are
olivine vitrifier mari basalts
and our microscopy didn't turn up any
evidence of major shock effects so
we are going to assert that these were
most likely magnetized through a trm a
thermo-remnant magnetization
we determined new argon argon ages for
two of these samples and
the first ever argon argon ages for the
third and
dated all three of them to about 3.1
billion years ago which is exactly what
we had been hoping for
now because these samples were rapidly
cooled and have a fine overall grain
size
our hope was that they might contain
some fine-grained magnetic material that
would make them good paleomagnetic
recorders
and at this scale we were able to
observe some bright metallic grains that
we thought might be the iron nickel
grains suggested by previous studies to
exist in these samples
okay i'm going to go right into our
paleomagnetic results first
the first question we asked was did
these samples record a field when they
formed
now usually when i give this talk i'm
talking to people who have never
taught uh never thought about magnets
before so i go through a little
explanation of how we build xiphel
diagrams and what they're kind of
supposed to look like and how the data
should trend toward the origin
but i think in this group i can probably
just show you my data
uh if you are familiar with ciderfeld
plots at all you may be noticing that
these are statistically
indistinguishable from spaghetti
at least once we remove this low
coercivity component that's consistent
with an overprint from just hanging out
in the earth's magnetic field for about
50 years
so unfortunately we're looking at the
data that's indistinguishable from noise
and what that means
is we were not able to retrieve a stable
high coercivity magnetization
through a standard afd mag of the nrm
so then we asked how weak a field could
these samples have recorded
if there was a field present at the time
now this is an important question to ask
in lunar studies because the
paleomagnetic techniques that were used
during the apollo era
were not always able to differentiate
between samples that did not record an
ancient magnetic field
and samples that just had poor remnants
or shoddy recording properties
or between samples that did record
strong planetary fields
and those that had just picked up
spurious remnants on earth
so to determine the fidelity limits for
these three samples we performed a
series of laboratory experiments in
which we were essentially applying a
magnetic field of a known intensity to
each sample
to simulate a trm at room temperature
because nasa doesn't love it when you
cook their rocks
um and then attempted to get back a
record of that applied field
using the same af dmag methods that we
had to try to get at nrm in the first
place
the hope being that we should see a
one-to-one relationship between the
applied field and the retrieved field
here are the results of those analyses
if you look at the plot all the way to
the left
we have our applied laboratory field on
the x-axis
in microteslas and the retrieved paleo
intensity on the y-axis again in
microteslas
and ideally all of our data should
cluster around this one-to-one
line that i've got in gray dash here
it's kind of hard to see exactly what's
happening from that figure alone so if
you look instead
at the middle figure we're applauding
we're re-plotting exactly the same data
in
a different way now we have the applied
field on the x-axis
and the difference between the applied
field and the retrieve field on the y
and using this 100 difference cut-offs
from some previous studies
we found that two of our samples could
give us back good records of fields as
weak as seven microteslas
and one of our samples was able to give
us back good records of fields as weak
as
four micro teslas which is pretty good
so
we would say that our af methods would
have been capable of retrieving records
of a weak trm
if the magnetizing fields were any
stronger than about four to seven
microtesles
you may recall from two slides ago that
we did no such thing
so let's go back to our timeline for a
second we have some new argon
argon dates we have some new fidelity
limits and we can add our three points
onto this timeline effectively
quadrupling the amount of data available
between 3.1 and 3.2 billion years ago
which is sort of fun to say one of the
things that i
really enjoyed about this study is that
we got results that are in really nice
agreement with previous work and this is
essentially a replication study
a hill that i will eventually die on is
that we should be able to do more
studies like that
because what this lets us do is we can
think back to this small number
statistics issue i brought up at the
front of the talk
and ask is the decline that we're seeing
actually statistically significant
we wanted to determine whether the paleo
intensities in the high field period
and the intensity limits determined in
this period of
initial field decline are really derived
from
separate populations or separate events
or whether they could be coming from the
same initial distribution of paleo
intensity values
so prior to the study just looking at
literature a ks test gave us a p-value
of 0.0152
saying these are almost certainly not
from excuse me these are almost
certainly not
random or from the same initial
distribution but when we add our three
data points we're unable to improve that
result by an order of magnitude and say
with
much more confidence that there was
about an order of magnitude field
decline
subsequent to the high field period on
the moon
so now we can extend our generic
schematic line
uh and say with a little bit more
confidence too that following the high
field period
there was a state change that put us
into a sustained weak field period
for some additional period of time so
again the reason that we're interested
in these kinds of questions about
changing intensity
is that they tell us something about the
mechanisms by which the field was
generated
and the hope is that by improving our
constraint of the timeline
we can eliminate some of these candidate
mechanisms from
our plot i'm not going to talk about
that right now though what i do want to
talk about instead
is the question of what is recording
these fields so i really want to talk
about mineralogy today because
these three samples have particularly
excellent fidelity properties for lunar
rocks
and i got pretty excited about trying to
figure out why so
previous studies have showed that the
ferromagnetic
mineralogy of lunar rocks is primarily
metallic iron and camasite
which is a low nickel iron nickel alloy
and i wanted to explore a little and see
what we could do with that information
so at rutgers we had access to an
electron microprobe uh
what you're looking at here in the
second through fourth columns are
qualitative elemental x-ray maps which
we collected in addition to obtaining
quantitative points from
individual grains you can basically
think of each pixel in each image as
representing a single data point
so if you look at the third column which
has this kind of navy blue background
we're showing iron in blue and nickel in
green and from that we can say we were
definitely seeing some actual iron
nickel grains which was pretty cool
i do want to highlight a few things that
we noticed during these observations
though
first we found grains with different
iron nickel ratios within
each sample and we were able to identify
both camasite
and martensite in this total collection
of grains in fact we were mostly finding
martensite which is a
slightly higher nickel content than
campasite we also saw
that many of these iron nickel grains
are not homogeneous
so in this figure you can see some
compositional gradients across a few
but not all of the grains that i'm
showing
there are color differences across the
grains and we
also observed some very likely iron
nickel grains of a sub micron size that
were unfortunately too small to acquire
quantitative points from
individually so in summary we were able
to observe what we're pretty sure our
multiple grain sizes of both camisite
and martensite
again pretty cool we've also been
thinking about some
studies that were published recently
suggesting that association with
troilite which is an iron sulfide
mineral
might be an indicator of good
paleomagnetic fidelity in lunar basalts
but we went looking and that's what's
going on with this fourth column where
now we've got sulfur in magenta
and iron in blue and we didn't find any
grains with compositions consistent with
trolite
so in general we would say that troilite
may be forming through
processes that also produce submicron
iron grains in some lunar rocks
but it's clearly not a requirement in
order for lunar rocks to have good
paleo-intensity fidelity
so then we also did some hysteresis
experiments the figures here are each
showing a representative subsample of
one of our three main samples
and we've got our applied field strength
in teslas on the x-axis
and the measured moment in ammeter
squared on the y-axis the
orange curves are raw data and the blue
curves are corrected for parametric
slope you might
recognize the irmdb software output here
i've also pulled out some of the
parameters that we used to define the
shape and size of each of our loops and
i will come back to that
very shortly so our measurements were
dominated by diamagnetic and
paramagnetic contributions probably
because we were using very small samples
for these particular experiments
but we did also observe some open loops
that we thought could be suggestive of
multi-domain states
and i want to note that they could also
be explained by some combination of
having extremely weak samples
and some known thermal disequilibrium
issues with the particular agfm that we
were using
okay so let's step back for a second and
talk about
domain behavior in lunar rocks between
beyond these three samples
what i'm showing here is a day plot and
these are typically used to understand
the hysteresis parameters of different
samples relative to each other
now i know that the terrestrial folks in
the room may be a little bit alarmed to
see this here especially if you are
familiar with andy roberts's seminal
2018 paper a critical appraisal of the
day diagram
but i ask you to please bear with me
because there is a point that i'm going
to try to make with this
um so on our x-axis we have remnant
coercivity
divided by coercive force and on our
y-axis we've got saturation remnant
magnetization divided by saturation
magnetization
and the general hope with the day plot
like this is that samples with better
recording properties
should plot toward the upper left and
may correspond with better magnetic
fidelity
so what we built in our study is to our
knowledge the largest published
compilation of hysteresis parameters
from apollo samples to date
each data point that you're seeing here
represents one sample or sub sample from
literature
sorted by bulk rock type kind of as a
first pass and the data from our study
is in the orange squares
i've also included these gray dashed
lines to indicate domain state regions
from the original day plot
so note the positions of samples from a
few recent studies on this figure just
by way of example
and you can kind of get a sense from
this handful of points that the general
trend we're hoping for
does seem to hold we see better lower
fidelity limits as we look toward the
upper left
of the plot however there is a problem
okay there's like there's a bunch of
problems with this figure but i'm just
gonna focus on one today
um those dashed lines do not actually
exist
the guiding domain parameter ranges were
originally developed for magnetite and
are not applicable to other kinds of
magnetic minerals
and this is crucial because not a single
one of the samples shown on this plot
nor
any of the samples used to build that
paleo intensity timeline
contain magnetite all that being said
we built this plot in the first place
because i wanted to understand our
samples in context
about half of the data that you see here
was collected prior to the invention of
forks when
this technique really was the cutting
edge and i'm convinced that we can at
least start some useful discussions
about how to go forward by
making these kinds of comparisons so
long story short i'm very proud of the
data compilation that we assembled here
and it is freely available at the nist
data repository with the link at the
bottom of the slide
um but i do strongly caution against
using day plots to determine specific
domain states or grain sizes
for the magnetic minerals in lunar
samples
okay if you zoned out or went to check
your phone i'm now going to summarize my
whole talk in about a minute and a half
what happened to the lunar field after
3.56 billion
years ago our methods would have been
able to retrieve a record
if the magnetizing field was any
stronger than about four to seven
microteslas however we did not retrieve
a stable record
of a magnetization consistent with that
kind of planetary field therefore
we find no evidence for lunar surface
fields any stronger than seven
microteslas
at about 3.1 billion years ago and as a
reminder this is roughly an order of
magnitude decline in field intensity
over about 370 million years in order to
explain this
we need either multiple mechanisms of
field generation or
a bistable dynamo for which the idea
would be some dynamo system that could
sustain itself in a strong state get
destabilized and then be reasserted in a
weak state
we think it's a little bit more likely
that we're looking at multiple
mechanisms here and we're particularly
interested
in a precession generated dynamo which
could have given way to
an underlying thermochemical convection
system after the moon
reached such a distance from the earth
that its gravitational state
uh destabilized the procession required
to produce those strong's field those
strong fields
and with that i will leave up a few of
our major takeaways
i want to say thank you again for having
me today it's a real honor to be part of
the magnet series i want to thank the
captain
program for sample allocation um and
thank you to
the two folks i think maybe in the
audience today who reviewed our paper
and gave some really genuinely
constructive feedback that actually
uh really helped with the draft that we
were putting together
i also want to make a very quick plug uh
if you are going to lpsc the lunar and
planetary science conference in a couple
of weeks
i'm giving two presentations one is on
uh magnetic domain domain behavior and
interpretation in apollo samples where
i'm going to go a little bit more in
depth on lunar magnetic mineralogy
and i'm also presenting a poster on some
work that i've been leading on gender
inclusive study methods in planetary
science and related fields and how we
can be more welcome to
welcoming to trans and non-binary people
in our study areas
and with that i'd be happy to take
questions
thank you very much beck i was great
presentation
uh really really really good um we are
ready now to take
questions if anybody yeah big round of
applause thank you
if you if you don't want to speak you
can drop your question in the chat
as well carney
says awesome talk thank you back thank
you
sorry i'll get the ball rolling um on
some questions
so you you're talking about um
a sort of order of magnitude drop um
over
over sorry what what length of time uh
was it
370 million years or so yeah i mean
have you thought about how that compares
to some of the the changes that we see
in terrestrial uh patio intensity data
yeah so this is uh this is something
that actually our reviewers gave us very
good feedback on uh we've gotten into
the habit of describing these
periods of decline as rapid because the
temporal resolution of data that we have
for the moon's magnetic field is so
sparse so when something happens one
billion years ago
and something else happens three billion
years ago everything in the middle feels
really fast when you have nothing to
compare to
but compared to terrestrial systems this
370 million year decline is probably
quite
slow and in order to get a little bit
more nuance about that honestly this is
one of the biggest pitches for
both improving our access to doing
magnetic studies of the apollo sample
suite because we have all this
this material available we might be able
to get better resolution
but also a pitch for thinking about how
we do
sample return in the future and with
lunar missions like artemis and even
mars missions we can think about how to
um improve coverage that might let us
get at things like
for instance reversals i have no idea if
there were reversals on the moon because
we just don't have the
the data to show that yet
thank you james is his hand
up i think that was a really nice talk
thank you for giving that thank you
um you mentioned that most of the grains
in your samples uh
martensite um and i just want to kind of
ask uh
what you thought the actual going
through the martensitic transition would
have done to a pain intensity would have
been like a
a re-recording will it be a crm would be
a trm would it be a crm that's carrying
a trm like what actually
sort of um mechanically is happening
there and what do you think the impacts
of that would be on a paleontology you
recover from a sample like this so
our our current understanding of this
and i do
want to like go on a tangent about how
we need to understand martensite more
thoroughly in this context
separately um but our current
understanding of this is that
the the um transition into martensite
was likely happening
very rapidly looking at the grain sizes
that we see
and the textures that are visible in our
microscopy we think that these
rocks overall cooled like less than a
day something on that order and from
that we are continuing to refer to this
as a trm
um there we've done a little bit of
digging into literature and it seems
that the overall magnetic behavior of
camasite and martensite are likely very
similar so i think the assumptions that
we've made in order to do these arm to
trm calculations
probably continue to hold for martensite
just because of that speed
um but i would very much like to do a
deep dive into exactly what the nuances
of these
like honestly these are ranges of
compositions right we say martensite for
things going from five percent up to 25
nickel and then i talked to my material
science colleagues and they're like
that's like eight different things you
know
um so i if you have more thoughts on
this i would very much like to to chat
about that further
thank you thank you now kathy constable
you have your hand
up yeah i was just wondering
um what the prospects really are for
filling in
based on the apollo samples so
i i i assume that many of them have been
dated and i'm
guessing you've looked at that array of
dates and
thought a little bit about the
composition how many samples do you
think you could get from there or do you
really think you're going to have to go
back
so it's it's really a goldilocks game
right like you need a sample that both
has been dated and is from the correct
time period and has formed in such a way
that it likely could be holding a good
record based on
mineralogy and speed and other processes
that's been through and handling and
whatnot
um and at the end of that i actually
have a proposal in related to this where
i think we might be able to get on the
order of
like a hundred samples would be cool
maybe a couple hundred would have the
information that we need
currently without doing any further
dating analyses or any further moon
missions
um but if we want to do better than a
hundred or a couple of hundred data
points which is what we
would expect for like a comparable
terrestrial study
then that's where we really have to have
conversations about changing the way we
think about sample
return and there is of course also the
additional layer here where
the processes by which new rocks are
being formed on the moon
are very much relegated to particular
time periods it's not
like we have continuous lava flows
occurring all along that entire timeline
um so the the cross section of
information that we have is i don't
think all 2000 samples would give me
good information
but we could definitely improve what i'm
currently showing by
doubling or tripling the information and
that would
still of course be a somewhat uh i don't
really have an idea of
what how that spotty record would look
yeah it would still be it would still be
terrestrial standards um
but this is like one of the one of what
i think of
are both the funnest parts and the
hardest parts of doing planetary
magnetism
so if we use terrestrial studies as the
standard what i'm showing today is like
almost nothing i've said a huge amount
from three data points but if we look at
mars for instance we're doing way better
than we
have done for the intensity timeline for
mars so it's really a
it's kind of a relativistic game but i
think a lot better
i mean i think if you look at three
billion years ago on the earth we're not
doing that well either
that's fair that's a fair point
thank you anybody else has questions
elliot remember that you have an answer
for the pressing question of the day
regarding beck's background image if you
want it
oh yes um just context for anyone who
tuned in a second late i am standing in
front of an image from lady gaga's
chromatica album
and no one has yet been able to identify
the original land feature that this was
photoshopped on top of
so uh elliot what do you think it is
in california
i didn't work it out i did a bit of
google foo
still counts that's literature research
i'll count that yes
but look i have confirmation so yes it's
trolling pinnacles in california
awesome thank you i demand a cookie in
prize
you'll get it thank you
awesome talker so thank you very much
that was deeply enjoyable
thank you
any more questions
andre you have your hand up yeah
well i got intrigued with your uh
uh high series properties compilation
thank you for that
and uh but still uh
i would advocate a little bit the old
version of uh of ideas of
we all had about their plot with all the
reservations that eddie did
two years ago three years ago st
still if you have
if you have generally very low mrsms
ratios and very high
hcrhc ratios
does it is it not showing you that
you have you have a lot of very fine
super paramagnetic grains in your
samples
and have you looked at this using maybe
low temperature measurements
so i haven't looked into that
specifically with these samples the the
big day plot that i'm showing
is really compiled from literature and
we haven't been able to do further
experiments due to
because the question about sp is super
paramagnetic grains is that
unfortunately if you have a lots of them
in your sample
they are bound to be a very bad
recording of any magnetic information
you would agree so maybe it
might be might be a
thing to look
look into because i can't remember many
low temperature measurements on the
lunar samples in particular
yeah it's i i'm racking my brain as
you're saying that and i think that's
one of the cases of like
something that i want to put together
following this work
is recommendations for how we can do
better in the future and so one of the
things that i've been really focusing on
is forks because that's now a tool
that's kind of becoming bread and butter
and terrestrial paleo
you have you haven't shown one
because i don't have any for my own
samples and i
was only able to find like one or two
studies that have collected okay
okay so so it's it's a matter of future
yeah
okay thank you very much very very good
talk here
yeah thank you and i do want to say that
the kind of low temperature experiments
you recommend
you're suggesting are exactly the kind
of thing i think we can start to write
well it's it's pretty simple it's
fast fast enough and as far as
as far as i read about the new
developments
in minnesota at the irm they've got this
nice machine in pms3 which is much
faster than the previous one and
much nicer and you can collect let's say
20 times more data through the same time
so just keep going
yeah thank you very much for sure thank
you thank you
thank you laurie you have your hand hope
you want to
ask a question you might want to unmute
yourself
thank you great talk back really
interesting i have a question that's a
little off from what you were talking
about but you did mention the crustal
anomalies
and can you say anything about what you
think the source of those are
internal or external or whatever
um i i can vaguely say that i'm on the
side of buried source bodies of some
kind
but i haven't the more i learn about
lunar swirls the more i learned that i
don't know anything about lunar
squirrels so i will unfortunately have
to punt that question to a colleague who
has been focusing more on those features
okay thanks thanks
thank you so any other questions
no i guess
yes if we have uh no more questions
we'll we'll wrap up
on this week's magnets so i just want to
thank beck again for another
uh fantastic and really uh interesting
talk
um it's a great diversity that we're
building up now
in in the kind of things that we cover
in these series so it's it's really
uh really great to have that thank you
very much thank you for having me
um so just a a quick reminder of our
upcoming
uh schedule um in a couple of weeks we
will have
uh andre and we'll be giving us a talk
um
and a couple of weeks after that we have
an open slot so if anybody is
interested in presenting their work here
at magnets please just
get in touch and then we'll have andrea
byderman
um into april and as before we'll have a
break for egu
and then after egu we'll move to um a
time slot it's a little bit more
favorable
for uh our colleagues in the eastern
hemisphere uh
in australia new zealand uh china and
japan and we'll have more information
about that coming
uh coming soon um but as always we're
looking for
um many more speakers and if anybody has
any thoughts or suggestions
um please get in touch and any form of
feedback or or comments
are always very very welcome and just
thank you everybody again for
coming along for another magnets cheers