um
hi everybody um thank you all very much
for
um joining us for the um first
uh magnet seminar of 2021
and the series that we ran last year was
was very successful
and it was really great to see uh so
many people
uh still coming in already we're over 17
still counting
so it's really fantastic that we've got
so many people here
supporting our community um through some
sort of
challenging times that we're all facing
um
so just a quick um note for for people
who
haven't actually attended these seminars
we've got a few new faces
um joining us now um these seminars are
typically on the order for
25 to um 30 minutes long we have a
little bit of flexibility because i know
lisa is gone for a slightly longer talk
but
we'll squeeze we'll squeeze it in um but
can i just ask that everybody
um please keep your microphones muted um
while the presenter is is speaking um
and if you're struggling with internet
connection
um if you turn your mic your video off
and that can often
um improve some of the speed um at the
end of the seminar we'll have a 10 or
15 minute chance for for questions and
discussion
um you can either raise your hand and
ask an
oral question or you can type in into
the chat window
and one of us most likely myself will
read out the question
um for you and just a reminder that you
know
we all have life going on around us in
the background so
if you have to to to go halfway through
these seminars
and just go we all know what it's like
uh working from home
or up early in the morning and all sorts
of things going on that doesn't apply to
you lisa you're here for the duration
i'm afraid um
and at the end of the seminar we'll have
a chance uh for a bit of a catch-up
because we're all um spread around the
world not really
interacting with each other in the same
ways that we used to so there'll be time
for
a catch a catch up on a chat uh later on
at the end
and that part of the seminar is not
going to be recorded so it's it's it's
um uh a bit more relaxed
um and so our speaker for today um is
lisa talks i'm really grateful for her
for
speaking today for our first seminar of
and today she'll be talking about
understanding non-ideal
paleointensity recorders in igneous
rocks
so i will hand over to you lisa okay can
i share my screen
yep okay
um
[Music]
if this works
can y'all see that yeah that's perfect
uh i think i shared the wrong screen
uh um do you have it in present review
yeah just a minute
um so let me share
this screen
how's that can you see that or do you
see two slides or one slide
uh we see one slide okay great
okay so the talk today um uh
is with my uh collaborators Christeanne
Santos
uh Brendan Cych uh Andrew Roberts
Les
Nagy and Wynn Williams was the paper
and um and so
i just i'm going to launch in without
you know skipping all the jokes in the
beginning
and uh talk about i mean mostly
people in paleomagnetism understand that
the basic
laws of the paleointensity experiment
are
that remanence is blocked at the same
temperature at which it's unblocked
that partial remanences that are blocked
between two temperatures are independent
of all the others
and that the sum of the TRM
acquired through a bunch of steps of
pTRM acquisition would be the same as
the total TRM and
when these laws are obeyed you have an
unblocking temperature spectrum and a
blocking temperature spectrum
there's a little tiny red line inside
the blue line and so the blocking and
unblocking are the same
then we do this experiment
which is a Koernigsberger Thellier-Thellier
type experiment
but we do it in a particular way where
we alternate in
field steps and out of field steps and
this slide just kind of summarizes the
experiment
and then if you plot the magnetization
remaining against the magnetization
acquired at each step you get a straight
line
the slope of which is proportional to
the field so that's great
now what happens if the two if we
no longer have reciprocity so
the blocking temperature is higher
blocking temperature
spectrum is higher than the unblocking
temperature spectrum
in this case you'll get a downward bowed
arai plot
on the right that's a the plot the
remanence remaining against the remanence
gained
and it sags below the line now
i'm glad to see that Dunlop and Ozdemir are
here because this was a great paper
um you have um the
you give it a they gave remanence to
um uh by cooling in a field between 370
and 350
and then demagnetized that remanence
and found that much a lot of the
remanence started to decay
well below the blocking temperature
giving rise to something we call low
temperature
tails pTRM tails and
and some of it remained um after
the blocking temperature which are high
temperature tails
and they did ery they did um
uh paleointensity experiments on them and
plotted
something that looked a lot like an Arai
plot
um where you can see that
all the the coarser grains
the purple plus signs at 135 microns
gives significantly saggy
um Arai plots whereas as
the grain size gets smaller and smaller
you get straighter Arai plots
and i didn't notice for a long time but
that the
the x-axis was normalized by the total
trm
on the x-axis and the y-axis
was normalized by the original remnants
and so
i thought from this diagram that you
could just take the total trm and get
the right answer
but that may not be true as was um
uh shown by a few years later by
cross-eyed all 2003
where if you have very fine-grained
material 60 nanometers
you get the right answer in the lab
field the
the le these experiments were done in 60
microtesla lab fields
and you can see the figure on the left i
don't know if you can see my mouse but
i can't even see my mouse never mind um
uh the that you get 59.3 you know you
get the right answer
whereas for larger grain sizes you can
see the one on the right hand side is 12
micron
material and it's underestimated by
uh by by hugely it's 42
microtesla instead of 60. and um
and that just seemed to be that the more
curved the Arai plots the worse
the uh total TRM answer or the best fit
line answer was
so is does this happen in nature or is
this only something about these
just big synthetic magnetites
um so i um
i have been collecting data for a long
time
and here are uh four examples of four
lava flows
that have specimens in the lava flow
that gave
very nice straight Arai plots that's
the top row
and the bottom row are sister specimens
from the same lava flow
and you can see that whereas
the one historical lava flow that we
have this hawaii 108
um we know the answer the answer was
a 39
microtesla is the correct answer
this hit the arai plot from the straight
one got the right answer
um but the sister specimen from the same
flow uh the best fit line and the total
trm
are low by 30 microtesla so very very
wrong
extremely low bias and we found that if
you take
uh straight arai plots from lava flows in
general if you compare them to the
results from
curved Arai plots from the same lava
flow you tend to get
an underestimate so there is a bias
associated with
with uh curved Arai plots and it tends
to be
that if they're downward sagged
that there's a negative there's a low
bias
and interestingly if there's an upward
bow
it tends to be overestimated
why i don't know and maybe we can figure
this out um
but um the
this so
the um the blue uh
circle is around one particular lava
flow that
we published in 2009
and um we sampled this from Isla Socorro
in the Pacific Ocean
and um and found this and i thought
because at the time
this was about in 2006.
we were talking in the community i
remember having conversations with many
of you
um at many meetings about how we should
be comparing unblocking with unblocking
and not
blocking with unblocking and so on and
so forth so i thought well
why don't i just give this guy a fresh
TRM
and then do it properly but the problem
was
that you can see that this is another
pair another sample from the same lava
flow
that um the Arai plot in the original
from the original experiment which is um
in the top
diagram was quite curved but
the uh Arai plot when we gave it a fresh
TRM
in the lab is the lower right hand side
and you can see it's perfectly straight
so the curvature was not reproducible
and so therefore any attempt to compare
um the blocking temperature
in the lab with the or the unblocking
temperature in the lab with the
unblocking temperature in the original
would not give
a good result um and i don't i did not
understand
why uh this happened i couldn't
these are a couple hundred thousand year
old lava flows so
vrm is not really an option here
and um and so i was puzzled
uh and i i now call this behavior
fragile curvature so it's not the same
thing
that what Dunlop and Ozdemir were
looking at or crossovers
were looking at which is a reproducible
curvature
and that you can maybe compensate for
because it's reproducible in the lab but
this
fragile curvature which seems to be
everywhere in natural samples
um particularly lava flows uh
is is a is a bear so
um how um
um that's that's a a bummer uh
so it started me thinking about this
problem a while ago
what causes curvature and Arai plots and
what cause why what causes this fragile
curvature
does this fragile curvature we start out
with a nice straight arai plot does the
fragile curvature
increase with time and are data from
these kinds of
samples biased and is there
some hope and it's the remedy part that
i'm probably not going to get to today
because you can see i have way too many
slides
so i i can think right now of of
two sources of curvature
one is the stuff that donal upper nurse
number published about
and crassa and uh those are domain walls
that produce this curvature the
separation of blocking and unblocking
and i think that um that
that phenomenon is
pretty well understood maybe not but
um i'm not going to worry about it
because most of my samples don't have
multi-domain grains
or big multi-domains but there's this
fragile curvature
which is not reproducible it's caused as
a mystery
and i think it's a failure of the
additivity test
and through micromagnetic modeling i'm
hoping that
Les nagy and Wyn Williams can help me
figure out
what is going on um
and um i mean you can you can ima i've
got
some guesses we've got guesses um and
um it is a serious problem
because i think anything that is
curved right now i would be highly
suspicious of
the result so
in order to investigate this further
char rancher then my postdoc
and i took a bunch of samples that were
curved curved Arai plots originally gave
them fresh trms they were perfectly
straight
we aged them for two years and the
curvature increased
and the results were biased relative to
the lab field so
then Christeanne Santos was a master's
student
in my lab and we added
we decided to do it again this time
taking
what we considered to be ideal specimens
so ones that had straight Arai plots to
begin with
and um give them a fresh TRM
and then do this experiment again
and so we did that and published it in
we came up with several categories of
behavior
and here we used Greig's marvelous
curvature criterion which we just use it
as a way to separate
things that uh into
well-behaved straight Arai plots and
poorly
behaved curved area plots so it's just a
empirically based um way of separating
things that are
quote unquote good from things that are
quote unquote curved
so we had this behavior where we had
four categories of behavior one
that the original trms in the upper
left-hand corner were straight
perfectly straight and then when we gave
them a fresh TRM they were perfectly
straight and we call those
straight goes to straight and that's ss
um then we found a bunch that were
straight in the original
where actually it's only one lava flow
but it's a
it's a it's kind of over represented
because i thought they were straight
um the straight
uh original Arai plot in the lower
left-hand corner
went to a curved array plot but you can
see it's a particular kind of curvature
it's got this high temperature hook to
it
and so that we call the straight goes to
curve i'm not going to focus a lot on
those
and then there was this case which was
in the sparbouri
study where we had a lava flow
that gave a curved arai plot and that's
on the right hand side top row
and then when we gave them a fresh trm
in the lab they became straight
according to greig's criterion you can
see that it really did straighten out
and that's what i'm calling fragile
curvature
and then there was this set that
started out curved um and
um went a lot straighter in the lower
right hand corner
they're much straighter but they're
still curved according to greig's
criterion so
these are the four categories of
behavior
so then um christeanne and i
and i pulled in some others to help me
on this
who are on the paper
took sister specimens from each of those
samples
10 sister specimens um unfortunately you
can't do this
study using the same samples over and
over again because we age them for
a couple years and so we'd be here until
um
the next century probably trying to do
this experiment
so we did it this way and there are
design flaws but
that's just the reality of of
of how we had to do the experiment so we
took 10
sister specimens from each of those
samples that i just
uh told you about
and we uh gave them um
identical uh we we gave them a trm and a
70 microtesla field
then we put them in various orientations
to two different lab fields
so a 70 microtesla lab field parallel to
the remnants
is position one top row so nothing
should happen right
it's it's in its equilibrium happy place
so nothing should change for position
one in 70 microtesla
and we did it at uh in five different
positions
then we also did a set where we aged it
in a lower field of
35 microtesla
same positions and so
we um for the study the tokusat 2021
study we aged them for two years
and um and did some rock mag
on them to try to characterize them i
did have a whole set of slides to
explain these figures but i'm just gonna
move on on the left hand side most of
you are familiar with the conventional
forc diagrams
so the top one is a conventional forc
diagram
the top left of one of the ss
uh specimens straight their single
domain and they look single domain right
i mean sure they're single domain and
then the sc
um the ones that went that had this
hook on them have this pirate hat
um distribution in their conventional
forc
and you can see that the one in the
lower left the
curved has probably a lot of
multi-domain in there
then we did the remnants forc and
the transient forc and the
induced forc and the one on the right is
this induced forc that
shenzhou came up with um
i think it was him it might have been
andy i don't know one of those two
um and the induced forc
has has some features and i don't
understand them
yet but the upper right hand
is characteristic of single domain
material
you can see this in magnetic recording
type
you know type section of of single
domain stuff
and um and the lower right hand corner
is
characteristic of multi-domain uh
or multi-axial large um
i mean i think we call them casually
multi-domain but they might be
some of these weird bizarre um
multi-axial vortex states i don't know
um
and you can see that it has this pattern
of negative positive negative positive
negative
positive up at the top right hand side
um and that's characteristic of the
coarsest grains
now these two middle eye forks
have a feature which i haven't seen
described in the literature
yet it's i've called it n plus
so it's a double slope of negative you
don't see it in the coarsest grains you
don't see it in the finest grains
and it's characteristic of a lot of lava
flow
type things um where you get this double
negative
um in the in uh in the zone
uh one and three of the i forc
and so i interpret this to mean that
ss are single domain mostly
and cc is a broad
span of grain sizes between
all the way from super paramagnetic up
to perhaps multi-domain
some multi-domain
and then um the two middle ones
i think are intermediate grain sizes
that span the range from
from um uh from
small um up to uh
up to single vortex and and um
and i i don't know any more than that
you guys can make something up
so uh the next question is why
are curves what causes fragile curvature
its reproducible curvature is in the
multi-domains
state fragile curvature is
characteristic of these
medium grain sizes the the ones with the
n
plus what i'm calling a butterfly
uh lobe in the eye forc
and then we'll get to the rest of these
um questions later so
here's my guess that it the the fragile
curvature has something to do
with um i mean the Neel state is you
have two stable
states and it can go from one to the
other there's an energy barrier in
between
but there's only two choices left to
right
and um in Neel theory um
but uh of course uh Wynn and Les have
pointed out that there's many more
states um i mean Wynn was one of the
discoverers of the vortex state in the
beginning
and along with uh Dunlop and
um and my buddy Neil bertram
but
they discovered that there's these more
complicated states but that was in the
late
80s um and so now
um we know that there's some some
very bizarre states in between the
domain and
in between single domain and vortex
and uh that if you have a multiplicity
of choice i call it it's sort of the
tyranny of choice
then you can you can have your blocking
temperature change
without changing the net magnetization
which is another feature that during the
aging process
the NRM did not change at all and yet
you have this growth of
of curvature so this is a a
kind of a weird thing but i think it's
explained by
something on the right hand side and of
course we need to do a lot more work on
that
um what could be causing it but for now
the key question for me as a practicing
paleomagnetist
is uh does fragile curvature increase
with time and
two are data from curved error plots
generally biased
and is there some way we can get around
this because this is
most of the data in the pint database
i just have to say so it's it is
serious if we want to know anything
about the ancient magnetic field we have
to solve this problem
so does curvature change with time um
on the left you have uh kernel density
estimates
of curvature in the fresh trms
from the santos study the the 2019 study
and you can see that even the worst are
uh
less than 0.4 that's still pretty bad
but then when you sit these same or
these sister specimens
in a field for two years
the curvature uh increased
not so much for the finest grain the red
curve there which are the
ss samples but
it changed a lot for the
cc and um
um and the um
cs and the sc to some extent
yes so um those the x axes are the same
on both of those plots
and so i can say i think with some
confidence that even over two years
the curvature of the Arai plots um
increased significantly and that dotted
line is Greig's
cut off for straight on the left of it
and curved on the right
i hope you can't hear the screaming in
the background it's my grandson enjoying
his breakfast
um so
so this fragile curvature exists
even within our lifetimes and um and
it's not explained by
by any kind of viscous theory that
involves an al theory so
um the
then the then the critical question is
is what i
said uh true i said in the beginning
i started the talk by saying i think
that things that are downward sagged
are biased low and this is bad
so let's see how these just two-year
aged
uh samples perform
so um i lumped all the
uh fresh and aged results
the fresh results from the santos 2019
paper are the blue line
the kernel density estimate for the
the blue line is clearly the lab field
was 70
as i said and you can see that there is
a bias
to lower fields you might say well it's
only five microtesla lisa
don't worry about it but i said this is
only two years come on
and if you if you take from those
data only the things that are curved
you get the solid blue line which is
clearly biased and the solid red line
which is also biased
and if you take the straight uh eri
plots from that same data set
and do the same thing you can see
they're not biased
so there does seem to be a slight bias
associated with
curved arrow plots
and um so now um
do i have time to keep going greg
yeah yeah you can go on for another few
more minutes
so so now we get to well what do we do
about it
um and here are some ideas whoops
um you could do ltd shaw method
which is supposed to knock out the
multi-domain contribution
and yuji yamamoto i gave him one of the
sets of samples which had been
aged at the time i think four years
and his method i can he's
writing up the paper i think but
basically what
the way he does it now is he'll reject
the same
samples that i do if i use greg
patterson's
curvature criterion to say okay i'm not
going to use any curved
results that's what the
cromwell criteria does um
he rejects the same specimen so his
method works but it doesn't get around
this problem
because he just chucks them out the way
i do
so the multi-specimen technique was
supposed to correct
for multi-domain behavior
um and so let's try that the
um and it occurred to me after talking
to
thomas bernt that maybe a fragile
curvature
is caused by these weird unstable the
things i've been calling the bad boys
maybe if we af demagnetized
the samples is part of our paleo
intensity experiment so before each
measurement we just af
at 10 micro melee tesla maybe that
solves a problem
or maybe we just assume that there's a
bias
and correct for it and that's the work
of brendan siegen i'm not going to talk
about that because it's
i'm going to he's working on a way to
get around this that i think might work
i'm pretty excited so
so um i um
did some of these things so i'm going to
quickly show you the results
brief history of the multi-specimen
approach it was first proposed by
hoffman ken hoffman in 1989
and then deckers and bernal uh refined
it
and their title is reliable absolute
pale intensity is independent of
magnetic domain state so that should be
a good place to start
then fabian and leonhardt uh refined it
even more
and it's supposed to be better for
domain state correction
and so um let's try those out
on one of the sets of age specimens so
here
i took uh one batch and applied
the um
did did the decker's bernal approach
to uh this the upper left
is decker's bernal on our ss sample so
the single domain
and you can see that the um the
result is does not include
the lab field which was 70 microteslas
so this is not
an accurate this is inaccurate and it
has low bias
and these are the single domain ones
then if you do the fabian and leonhardt
correction
it's uh worse so um
it has a an expected field of
57 microtesla instead of 70.
then the um the ones with the hook
this the hooked ones the straight went
curved um ones that's pretty accurate
on the decker's bernal but then when you
apply the fabian
leonhardt correction it's inaccurate
and a low bias then for the larger grain
sizes
the decker's bernal method
on the the cs samples
the ones with fragile curvature you get
the right answer but it's
extremely imprecise of course i suppose
you could do more specimens in there and
try to tamp it down
and when you do the fabian and leonhardt
correction
you get the right answer right it's it's
pretty good
so um the
the curvature ones uh
the the coarsest grain ones the cc's
um the decker's bernal approach
the error bars include the right answer
um it's very imprecise and um
but when you apply the decker's bernal
the fabian leonhardt correction you get
the wrong answer
and it's biased low so i'm not very
optimistic about this technique
solving our problem because the thing
that was supposed to fix
were the things on the lower um lower
row there so maybe there's another way
um uh we uh
and that is to do this af izzy uh
technique and so i did a bunch or
christiane did a bunch
on um specimens from
position two the 35 microtest and 70
microtesla
um fields these are all of the remaining
samples
and so you can see on the top row
that's the results of our af izzy
and you can see that on the right hand
side
as a curved went curved this af
izzy did not cure the curvature
and uh and i was hoping it would
but it doesn't the stuff still curved
it's still
and so is it still biased
so af izzy um here
are the curvature results uh on the
upper
left hand side the curve the
results of af izzy of course these were
there's a i mean there's a technical
difference between these these were aged
five years before we got around to
measuring them instead of two years so
there's a slight difference
however it seems pretty clear that af
izzy
resulted in worse curvature
in all cases and
the total trms are
um interestingly for the
finest grain material are um
biased high so
i don't know uh and with the plain izzy
uh
the curved results were biased low
so maybe five milli teslas is better i
don't know
but um i'm i'm now uh over
curved results and so um what i want to
do
is to encourage uh brendan
to work on on his idea
of how to fix this so stay tuned i'm
not gonna talk about that
right now okay
questions
excellent thank you very much lisa that
was uh that's a really interesting
somebody said they think that's an
interesting talk if you can hear my
background
um i'll just ask everybody to join me in
a virtual round of applause for lisa you
can do that through zoom or you can just
hold your hands up to the camera and
clap that's a really interesting
um presentation so i will um
open open the floor to any questions for
for lisa
and i do have a bundle so um i will
invite other people before i
uh jump in
i will say i'm loving your curvature
parameter
uh yeah i think i mean it's um
yes bds not so much but yeah i mean the
curvature is a very much it's a
you know an empirical thing it's a
geometry of of how the arrive plot um
behaves and it's kind of intuitive that
um
you have a higher chance of getting or
selecting a sort of
inaccurate result if you're a right plot
isn't
isn't straight um so
i'm going to jump in with a question
about your multi-specimen stuff
um so you're comparing the um
the decorative bonnell method and the
um uh fabian uh corrected method
is that when you're doing the decoration
banal that's just the
original method that's not taking the
fraction
correction into account is it no it was
just the original one as proposed
and then i used the fabian and but but
that one
it seems to work better than the the
mainstay corrected one of fabian
so the i guess i mean the domain state
corrected one
kind of always shifts the result
downwards it can never
increase the intensity but i wonder if
if some of the results if
you just did the fraction correction but
not the domain state correction if that
might actually give
you know you've got accurate and more
more precision maybe
and something i'm not optimistic maybe
um
but but my feeling is that you don't
know which category you're in
if you do this you only know that do a
full
uh paleo intensity experiment um
that and that only some
of the specimens performed
well with um with the
any of the multi-specimen approaches and
so my feeling is that
if if your samples are are curved or
biased or
have this fragile curvature that you're
basically
if you don't know that you are going to
make a mistake you're going to be
um you're just not you're going to have
to by especially
um i said adrian did you flash your hand
up for a quick question i don't see you
up anymore um but if anybody has a
question you can just
raise your hands through some otherwise
i will i'll just dominate and ask
tons more questions are clear clear has
a question
clear nichols when you go clear all
right look at the wrong screen
i'm yeah um hi lisa great talk i was
just wondering with the
uh you see the bios after two years as
five microtesla and
i guess if that's a linear bias that
gets worse most of the time
then it's a big problem but do you know
if it actually gets
much worse very quickly and then kind of
settles or if it continues like
is it twice as bad after five years
it's time to talk to you in five years
i i just uh in order to do these last
two experiments
the last three ideas i used up all the
specimens that were
aging and so now we don't have any more
so someone else can start i just retired
so
i've gotta be here to get to the answer
um uh i think it keeps getting worse
i don't know the answer if you look at
the original era plots
for some of these they're really very
curved and so i
imagine that the curvature just was
you know over a hundred thousand years i
don't know
okay have to start aging some samples
why don't you do it we'll talk to you in
five years ten years
so it sounds like somebody could start a
career out of this
um so uh andre you have your hand up
[Music]
oh okay now
okay now yeah okay
okay eliza
well there is a
brief question and also a sort of
suggestion
uh first
when you see in your curved
nagatara plots
how did your ptrm checks generally
behave
these samples were chosen because they
had all
undergone a atelier experiment
and had shown no alteration so the
alteration checks on these were fine
that's not the issue
here in this case all right
let's still uh okay i might i'm
i may be blowing in my own trumpet but
uh okay
uh some 20 20 plus years ago
mr michelle prabhu and i published the
paper
which showed what you call fragile
uh curvature and we did the same
we did basically the same experiment
with two
what was that published we published
the the paper in ggi in 98
and we did basically the same experiment
and
ended up with basically the same
the same conclusion that you have you
have very
very curved negative right plots on
original
samples and then you get uh almost
straight lines when you do the
chile experiment on the turtle theory
and we we did the we went a little bit
further on on the rock mug line and
investigated the hysteresis loops
at elevated temperatures
and actually we found out that
in all in all these samples with a
fragile curvature was good good term
okay they showed uh
they showed up very very characteristic
changes in coercivity
upon heating and it was sufficient to
heat up the
samples to something like
250 to 75 degrees centigrade to end up
with very
this clearly irreversible behavior of
history
of high studies and our
our interpretation with michelle was
that uh
when you hit this uh when you hit the
samples
with this and we change this
the internal stresses which which
controls
the core civility and that's
and unfortunately the answer to your
last question
seems that there is no remedy apart from
this
perhaps this
[Music]
if this interpretation is correct then
the our only hope would be this
numerical
correction but once again we
we need to figure out how to do that
properly
so maybe brennan can get a seminar in uh
maybe a month a couple weeks or a month
um
because he's about to submit a
manuscript which i
i think may be
a way forward yeah of course and
uh one thing to uh one thing to
recall about this whole study was that
the pro the worst uh curved
sample was there was one with the
largest
mrsms ratio
of something 0.3 so it was nearly
in the single domain verge
i don't know yeah and the coercivity was
something like 40 30 milli tesla and
still it behaved
terribly but mind you but in that case
uh we did see the we did see the
failed ptrm checks at the uh
where the where the curvature was
developed
because well
okay yeah richard has a question now
yeah i agree we'll move on to it
otherwise we'll lose all of our time
yeah okay um okay so
a non-paleomagnetist question so
implications
um so we spent many years doing analysis
of all sorts of or putting into models
all sorts of data
so for example it always puzzled me that
the field seems to be stronger now than
it was in the past
could this be part of the the story
behind that
um is this only volcanic
so are kim
but i i do think that to feel the
stronger
the present than in the past because if
you choose only
uh good results that have straight
era plots that's what it shows so i i'm
confident now but
this does raise a question so how
how about results in uh
databases that do not include the
original measurements
what confidence can we have in those
results
like for example the pint database that
has just studied
just site level uh
estimates and you have no idea about
where they curve did they not occur
where were they yeah
so um uh
i'm advocating for people putting their
data into the database
and the good news is that if brendan's
method does work
then we can rescue a lot of results
and correct for this bias but
um for now you know that story about the
high field recently
is is a lot of archaeological data and
archaeological artifacts um
despi was on uh she can attest to the
fact that
a lot of um archaeological
archaeomagnetic data are really
great they're straight eri plots they're
not don't
have this problem it's only when you get
back further further in time and i would
say that this is a general problem of
lava flows but not of the lava flow tops
which are glassy or finer grained and
then you get yourself into the single
domain range
and so you can get good results from
lava flows as shown by cromwell
and um and that's been our approach
for the last 30 30 years
20 long time 20 since 1990 i started
trying to find
single domain material um
i'm very pleased that you're not
throwing away the glassy breathing
otherwise you might disappear out your
own um
so that's very good to hear i'm not
throwing away the glassy stuff although
really bowls might
for me for some other reason
i don't know no but i mean i can
appreciate what you're saying about
trying to find the best data but when
you were going through your conditions
i have to admit i was less worried about
the one that was kind of imprecise but
at least
accurate i didn't care so much because
there it's the
it's the consistency it's the systematic
bias that's the problem
if you've got inaccurate but accurate
but or accurate but um wide sounds that
just take lots of the data
that's right so that's
give me another five years and maybe
we'll solve it
um i just want to thank uh lisa again um
for a fantastic talk some really
interesting stuff in there
and i'm looking forward to uh some of
the future stuff
um as i note because you kept mentioning
brendan's
method and brendan should give a
presentation he ate
bread and such actually gave a
presentation as part of
uh magnetic interactions um earlier uh
this year
um as part of magnets we recorded that
seminar
and one of my magnets duties is to
upload all of those videos online uh
which is coming
they are um coming on so everyone um can
catch up on
on uh magnetic interactions um 2020 and
brendan's talk and his uh pretty cool
looking method of of correcting
um some of these uh biases so i just
want to thank
uh lisa once again and you can throw up
another virtual
uh round of applause for for lisa for a
fantastic
talk um
and and before we um bring um today's
obsession to
to a close um i just want to remind
everybody um that
that moving into 2021 we've got several
more people
uh lined up to to give presentations
so we're going to be running the
seminars um every two weeks
uh and you can see that we've we've
already got
our lineup for the next few weeks a few
months sorry
um we're going to take a break for uh
egu and to give people um a little bit
of a chance to
uh not be bombarded by too many um
seminars um but after egu we're actually
going to change
um our time slot a little bit um so that
we're running in an eu
um eastern hemisphere slot so that we
have a chance for
some of our colleagues in australia and
china and japan
to join these seminars live but also to
to actually
um present some of the science that that
they're doing
um and i'll give more details about that
um later on as we get closer to that
time
but we've got a few a few people lined
up and to give a range of
of talks and and as we move forward into
um we're we're always looking for more
speakers so if anybody is interested in
giving a seminar um please just um get
in touch with us
and we can sort out a future slot
um and one last little mention is um
up until now um our magnet seminars have
been made available through
the magic youtube channel and i want to
thank the magic team
for helping us get started and host that
moving forward we will have our own
dedicated
magnets youtube channel where these
videos will be
uploaded um well i'll send around some
more details uh for the web links and so
on there
but this will have our 2021 series
and i'll have the magnetic interactions
uh seminars as well
but i'll pass those uh details around um
and as always um any feedback
ideas and criticisms um are always
welcome to to improve
um our community uh seminar series but
thank you all again um for for joining
magnets and i'll see you all in a couple
of weeks