final talk of the
the session and it's by
gunter klitechka and the title is
magnetic interactions in the human brain
so
you can take it away and share your
screen
oh can everyone hear me yep
yep good and can everyone see the shirt
content
yep i can see it now
okay oh it's good to see you oh
everyone it's good to hear you it's good
to be
a little less isolated um so
here i want to present some applications
of magnetism
and biological human or medicine
research
robert basala who is a second author is
a medical doctor
that is working with me and because of
that we had access to
unique material and it looked like that
well we know the geometric fields are
there
and they interfere with the human brain
and we were just
studying uh the samples that we had on
hand and
found that not only there is magnetic
material
in the human brain but there is also a
way how this magnetic material can
interact with the synapses or with the
neurons
and so
here's uh what we find out well before i
proceed
on the left corner and right corner you
see
approximate size of our sample so you
can see they are all
roughly two centimeter by two
centimeters
cubes so let's also show the resolution
of the method that we use
okay let's see
the brains we got them from this
institute of forensic medicine
and there was also according to the
regulation and guidelines in czech
republic
so here is just uh an idea
how the samples were obtained
and how they were cut we used the
ceramic knife for cutting and we try to
use
the best way in order to
avoid any contamination
even though it when
when we obtain the final results and
we're comparing with some other
published data it
looked like the noise level of our data
were
quite high
but we are still confident that our data
show
gives us reasonable conclusions
here is an example of the typical
demagnetization of the
sample so the rb basically means right
like a right hemisphere but that's not
important the important thing is that
you can see that the noise level is
quite high and
uh the dimensions some of the different
it's quite
difficult to demagnetize these samples
using alternating
field up to 40 milli tesla
on the other hand when you when you
saturate those samples and demagnetize
them
you can see that uh
the intersect of the two curves is quite
low which indicate that there is a
there is sort of negative interaction uh
in this system
and uh but you can also see that they
they're they are quite magnetizable that
the material
can and it's also quite
soft in terms of the following
demagnetization
uh here's the uh kind of a
complicated plot uh on the left
plot you can see the nrm of samples
and on the horizontal axis it's
saturation remnants
after you gave saturation in two tesla
fields
uh you can see that there's a like
different colors and red and yellow
are the are the brains that have
had a neurodegenerative disease while
the blue and greens
are without neurodegenerative disease
on this plot you can see that the red
and yellow
there they both uh indicated that
there's a larger or tendency to have a
larger
saturation remnants
while the nrm was about the same for all
the samples
the lines at the lower part of the
diagrams
are kind of a histogram of the data
so you can see how they were distributed
so uh maybe more to these samples the
b01 and b02
with the neurodegenerative disease and
b0 strain b04
e03 is an adult brain like a old
person and b04 is a child
brain meaning that we use it kind of
like a
control because we know that there was a
[Music]
it was a young and without any
iron accumulations as a result of age
because it's known that with age
the iron has a tendency to accumulate in
the human brain
on the right diagram i just
wanted to show the comparison of the
remnants
on the left diagram with the induced
magnetization
now here uh shown by magnetic
susceptibility
so the the labels are the
are dissimilar then red and yellow it's
a neurodegenerative disease and blue and
green
are the health brains and
so in here you can see that there's
there's a contrast that
in here in the remnants field the
disease brain has a large remnants
however
in for the susceptibility you can see
that the the red
one that had a large remnants has a very
low
magnetic susceptibility
compared to all the other samples
so uh so that was
uh so there was a question how to
resolve that uh
issue and we'll talk about a little bit
later
and the another interesting thing is
that since we
were able to get the oriented samples
in terms of the one brain we
were plotting the magnetic directions
and
find out that the magnetic directions
are from the
from the oh from the forehead to the
back
of your head and so we were
kind of curious why is that why a human
would have a magnetized brain from
forehead towards the back of your head
and
the the the other brain did not show
that the other brain had
more like a shotgun distribution of the
magnetic directions and so
the then we find out that this specific
person
spent the last three years in a bed
because it was an urgery person and
could not move so
she was just spending the whole
three years in a lying horizontal
position and in terms of the
magnetic field in a region
here in central europe in prague
the magnetic field is small it's a
vertical and so it
started to make sense why the
brain would get the magnetization
from the forehead to the back side of
your brain because as the
during the during the final progression
of the disease the last three years
and there was a growth of the or
magnetic mineralization
these grains would get the chemical
remnant magnetization
and it will be recorded from the
overhead to the back side of your head
this side the diagram on your right
shows the stability
since most of these uh magnetic
mineralization and brain are
super paramagnetic uh there is a
you know there is a the signal has it's
not
very stable as soon as you measure
the saturation remnants you can see
there's a decay in terms of the second
as as because of the low
stability of the magnetic range as a
function of time
we also obtained data of
of zinc and calcium that
kind of related to the disease
and also the iron concentration
of those samples and we'll
talk about it a little bit later
this diagram is a little bit more
complicated
but let me just try to quickly uh jump
into it i mean
there's a brain there's a neural cell
and so this diagram
right in the middle it's basically the
interior of the neuron
and of course there is an iron which is
kind of a
trying to be stable on a on the equal
level and so there are
there is a there is a one door or one
opening
there are openings where the iron gets
in there are also other openings where
the iron gets out and of course there
are mechanisms that are trying to keep
the iron concentration
about at the same level and of course if
there is a
reason for a higher concentration of
iron
then uh there is a mechanism that kind
of try to precipitate the iron in
some kind of a solid matter so it's not
in a liquid state
and so one observation that was
reported is that on these doorways when
iron goes in and out very often like a
zinc
uh plays a role that it can actually
block
the the entering of the door
and this would cost or or
exit of the door and this would cause
the mineralization and
so we showed this uh
hypothesis that once you get this
uh like a magnetic brains or
mineralization that
because these particles are super
paramagnetic
the their magnetic dipole is oscillating
like
randomly and as a result of this
oscillation because around
all this material all this liquid is a
conductor
you would be inducing the electric
currents that would have the similar
frequency
as the frequency of the of the rotation
of this
dipole because it's a superpower and
magnetic grain
and so the general model uh
suggests that uh you know when you are
born i mean you have some
like a mineralization in your brain
which uh
as a which i mean is keeping
its its size small or super magnetic
however when when this mineralization
when those grains get bigger
uh you are slowing down this oscillation
of the magnetic dipole inside this
magnetic particles and as a result of it
you have this
like a different electric
variation or the electric currents that
has an alternating
current that may interfere with the
neural
synapses and because we know that the
neural synapses are operating
approximately as like a tensile hertz
frequency as soon as you were to
increase the size of these
minerals that the size were the
frequency of the oscillation would be
about
20 50 10 hertz
you would have a way to interfere with
the
synapses electro electric uh
electric uh pulses
so this is the hypothesis that we are
following as a
result we also try to
try to like modify the
nil theory or adjust it to you know to
get some kind of
handle on understanding how this crm
because the this theory was
written for trm so we have a crm
substituted instead of trm in this
tangent hyperbolic function
and of course we are using blocking
volume instead of the
blocking temperature and then we follow
basically
we also use this time scale because we
also would like to have a handle on the
time
how quickly the magnetic vector of a
single domain particle oscillate
and once we put it together
we assume that the crm and saturation
remnants
in those individual particles are the
same so we have one
and then when we have a argument of this
tangent of
hyperbolic angle we know that for
for everything greater than 2 this is
this is
correct equation so we basically
say that once the argument is equal to
two we have a like a simple
uh or simplification that kind of could
give us a handle
about how much field you would
require for in order to
to stabilize the particle that has a
certain core acidity
so this kind of like a preliminary like
a
idea how it may work and
then we also try to get the handle on
frequency dependence measurements and we
show that there is a
lower susceptibility with the higher
frequency which is
which is confirming that we are dealing
mostly with
super uh paramagnetic grains
and this uh comes to the conclusions
uh that we made from this study that uh
we think that this non-nominalization
uh correlates with the neurodegenerative
diseases and you could you could monitor
it by
motor monitoring the magnetic remnants
because as soon as you have a magnetic
remanence presence
then you know that the magnetic
particles grew to the size
where they already have a they are so
large
so they could record the remnants
however before they reach that that
grain size
there is this electric noise which
relates to the electric uh frequencies
that are operating
in a human brain and so we think that
this transition
between super paramagnetic and like a
particle with the remnants is important
in terms of the electric noise in your
brain
we have some reason to think that zinc
may interrupting the iron pathways and
this may be the way how you could
start to induce the mineralization
in the human brain and
we have observation that both low and
high magnetic susceptibility
occurs in the brain with
neurodegenerative disease
and we interpret this that this has to
do with
once you change magnetic particles
from super paramagnetic single domain
the
magnetic sustainability is sharply
like a decreasing for these drains and
that may be the reason
for this observation and
and so we think that we also offer like
a
different mechanism for electric
interference of these
magnetic nanoparticles and with this
i i'm opening if anyone has any
questions
so thank you guter for your talk so do
we have any questions
i go in sir i'll i'll just jump in with
a a quick question that's a really
interesting talk
um so these these uh nano particles
um are they fixed within the brain or
are they free to move
uh within within the space
uh hang on let me let i have some
trouble
finding out where where is my zoom hang
on
into
[Music]
oh okay i see you now
okay uh say can you repeat the question
i was a little bit
so are the nanoparticles um fixed within
the brain structure or are they
um free to move
well it's a good question they are in in
this neural cells and
because there are is on the order of
like uh the units the tenths of
nanometers
uh the question is if they would be if
this
specific metallation would be occurring
on us on a like a
membrane because once they would be on a
membrane they would be more or less
stuck
or if they would be like in a medium
where you have this flow of the fluid
because we had this observation of this
remnants in terms of from the forehead
to the back side
it looked like that these nanoparticles
would have to be
stuck somewhere along the wall of the
neural
cell i guess if if they are
free-flowing as well then the the
effects of brownian motion would also be
producing eddy currents
well what you are
you mentioned brown in motion which is
basically something which is
causing the destabilization of the
magnetic remnants right it's a common
vibration
yes i'm curious about as to whether or
not
you know some of your calculations if
you've considered that for a free moving
particle
a brownian motion will induce rotation
of the particle
um which will actually create its own
eddy currents because you have
these two two mechanisms of the
superpower magnetic flipping
but also the the physical rotation of
the particle at the same
time which might also contribute to the
production of eddy currents
that's a very good question i i didn't i
didn't think of the
specific moving of the particle i was
assuming almost
all the time that there is a just
particle which is
not moving but the magnetic dipole is
moving as a result of the
phonon vibration but what you are saying
is it's correct it could also have a
effect but i didn't think of it thank
you really really interesting study
cheers do you have any more questions
there are some questions in the chat
okay yeah
that's it i think anita wants to know
how to store
a brain
yeah okay so this
is a there's a question in the chat
there's a there's a fluid uh
it's called formally you know
formaldehyde
uh which uh these you because
normally if you don't if you don't put
it into this fluid it's very difficult
to
handle the brain it's kind of like
really like a
smooshy but once you put it in
formaldehyde it become more like a tofu
tofu the japanese tofu right so it's
it's then you can work with it quite
easily
yes sorry if i intervene yes this is
what i was asking because
uh actually um i was seeing this process
happening i was
i didn't directly measure those samples
but
uh so i observed that if you if they are
stored in the formal diet they
basically provoke an artificial kind of
decrease of the magnetization of the
sample which is already
very very weak as you showed so and also
the
the contamination of the room where it's
kind of prepared the samples that also
affect a lot so
if you put air filters in the in the
room you'll see how big that
contamination it is so that's why i was
asking about the preparation of those
samples because i
it's a very good question and there
there was a study
on her brain uh
about three years ago uh where i was
observing our data with that data
and i could see that their ability to
detect
and report uh like some of the magnetic
remnants signature although samples that
were very weak
were almost like an order of magnitude
lower than ours
so because i could see that once i was
trying to handle the magnetizations
that were reported in that study i could
see that
it's all noise that i could not really
rely
rely on on that data so i was not
including those data in because i i
thought maybe
we did not have as pretty pristine
procedure
we didn't do like uh we didn't
have any like a hepa filters when we
were i mean we were doing in a
in a that hepa filter in it but still i
think there is
some space for contamination
thank you