so ali will just be kind of putting an
economic twist on
some magnetic work and so he's using
statistical machine learning to classify
hydrothermal alteration
so when you're ready can you see that
yeah yeah okay so thank you vince
yeah as vince said i'm olly and i'm a
second year
uh in my second year of my phd which
focuses on the structural controls of
paw free copper deposits
and today i'm going to be presenting a
machine learning a new machine
learning algorithm that i've developed
mainly with nasa mendini in
nazapa nazarbayev university in
kazakhstan
and this will form my first chapter and
hopefully we'll be getting to admit it
in the next few months
um so disclaimer there's
not a lot of magnetic measurements in
the first section of this
but i will i will get there um
so first a little background with the
continued growth in the global
population
expected to continue for the next
century
and our increased appetite for the
latest and greatest technological
advancements
the continued urbanization in both the
developed and undeveloped
underdeveloped nations and are
increasing awareness
and move towards renewable energy
sources which all require
between 20 and 30 times more copper than
conventional energy sources
the society's demand for copper is
actually predicted to increase
by greater than 300 percent over the
next 50 years
and this just highlights the importance
for geologists to develop
uh new methods for discovering deeply
buried deposits
and change the way uh the type of
uh the type and way that data is
collected
and used to increase mining efficiency
in the future
so for those of you that don't really
know
the majority of the world's copper
populate copper
comes and other metals come from
uh pulvery copper deposits and
they and the very widely accepted
current model for formation is one where
you have
these large bodies of igneous material
that evolve
over time and in some
uh at the later stages of that
evolvement
you have the breakthrough of fluids
through the roof of the uh
through the roof of these intrusions to
form these multi-phase
portfolio copper stock works and where
this occur
where this occurs there are three main
triggers for mineralization
the first being the cooling and
expansion
of vapor caused by steep temperature
caused by the steep temperature gradient
at the top of these fingers
and that's due to sulfide solubility
being
temperature and density dependent the
second
being the evolution of a fracture
network above the deposit
which causes rapid pressure drops as
hydro fracturing occurs
and the third being the neutralization
of the hydrothermal fluid
as it interacts with circulating
groundwater
so as with all mineral deposits
this fluid flow causes alteration in the
surrounding whole
rocks and the current very widely
accepted alteration pattern that occurs
is this one by soso which was published
in 2010
however both within industry and
academia
these alteration zones play a vital role
in both the exploration
and extraction of the metals but
as until now this is based
entirely on a geologist's eye which as
you can imagine
inherently causes ambiguity because we
all see
and interpret things completely
differently
um uh so
the solution that i think well i what i
think the solution to this
is is being able to cross-reference
quantitative data sets um
which in this case i'm using a magnetic
susceptibility
but would like to bring in more magnetic
data into that
and hyperspectral data
so due to this being based on
quantitative data then this would be
completely repeatable
and reproducible and unfortunate
ultimately actually means that anyone
can collect the large quantities of data
that would make
the outcome more accurate and also give
you a better picture of these
large multi-billion pound mines that i'm
working on um so currently
i have only integrated ip and op
magnetic acceptability into the
algorithm that i'll describe in a bit um
but as i will demonstrate later there
are significant differences between
the groupings that the algorithm
identifies
that represent more than just maxis data
and i'm so i'm
and i'm totally wanting to incorporate
more characterization
characterization mag data but currently
don't have the data
uh quality quantity uh
for the method that i'm using here
um so for the complete this is this
presentation
uh maxus is defined as the ability of a
material
to be magnetized in a low ac field but
i'm
not going to dwell on that at all and
move on quite quickly so
for those of you that don't know uh also
hyperspec
i'm going to also use hyperspectral
reflectance which is
a non-destructive technique which
collects and processes
information from across the
electromagnetic spectrum
and that reflectance when normalized to
a whole
envelope looks something like this
and this is the spectra of asymmetrical
clay
known as alunite if i then
present those for both monterey
montamarillonite and kaolinite
as well and you can begin to see
variations
in the absorption pattern within the
same mineral
group in this case smectite
from these we can extract that from
these we can extract various pieces of
information
by using different algorithms which look
at
four different things and at different
parts of the spectrum
so the sort of things that you can get
quantitative numbers for
is for example the composition which is
based off
the peak position which for example in
this
uh example you can see the
alienate having a peak at 2115
the um montmorillonite having a peak
between 2000 and twenty
two thousand and twenty two at two
thousand two hundred and five
and two thousand two hundred and fifteen
and then also kayla and i having the
same peak
uh at a peak of around 2020
2206 as
and if we then look at those um
peaks we can look at the intensity of
that
composition that's been identified
uh which tells us uh
the abundance of that mineral present
relative to one another
and then also you can look at the
crystallinity which is based off the
full wave half max
at half minimum value so it's basically
looking halfway up
that peak and looking at the
the size of that um heat
so in the study i've done this for the
major and minor
silica and sulfide mineral groups found
most
regularly in the deposit which include
epidotes smectites white micas
amphiboles carbonate chlorides
and also sulfides
meaning that with the ip and opmag sus
data
i have a 29 dimensional dataset
and as you can probably appreciate and
imagine
this is very hard to visualize and get
any useful information out of
without doing some sort of uh
statistical
uh using some sort of statistical method
um
but what i've done is along with
colleagues in nazarbayev university is
come up with this new and novel
uh machine learning algorithm uh
which looks at all this data and splits
it apart into
its most representative
groups of data so i'm not going to dwell
too much on the mat but here is a quick
explanation
so imagine in a high dimensional space
we're going to measure the
similarities between points which is
defined as p i j in this case
and we're going to do that in a way that
we just look at the local similarities
to that one point so imagine a point in
that data set being
x i and then and we
center a gash on over that point we're
going to then measure
the density of all the points within
this
in this case uh on this equation x
i at x j and then we're going to
re-normalize all this
with the bottom which is what the bottom
part of the fraction
on the screen does so when you when we
run this
for all the points in the data set we
have a set of probabilities
of p i j for each
data point which measure the similarity
between pairs of points
in the original high dimensional space
so if the points are close together in
high dimensional space
then we'll have a large value of p i j
and if the two points are far apart
then we'll get a p i j which is
basically
infant decimal so now imagine
a two dimensional xy plot which
i'm saying is low dimensional space and
this is what we want the data to be
simplified down
into and represented in
and i represent each high dimensional
object
in this low dimensional map with an
arbitrary position point to begin with
and repeat the same thing calculating
the procedure
uh calculating to produce a similarity
measure
of q i j in the low dimensional space
and then if we take
this curvat libra divergence we're going
to measure which measures the difference
between the p
i j value in high dimensional space and
the q i j values
from the low dimensional like space
um we
want as iterations of this algorithm
take place we want the
curvature for diversions to become as
small as possible
with the aim to be getting it down to
zero
um but obviously that doesn't always
take place like
and you just have to stop the algorithm
when it gets close to zero
or flat lines so currently
i have a magnetic accessibility and high
spectral data set that
is 5018 at 5814 strong
with a further 4581
still to measure um obviously this
becomes
quite computationally expensive to run
um
and it takes currently about five days
with the current data however
so that you can imagine the picture and
imagine a picture what is going
on uh with the different iterations i
have put together
this sort of interactive graph which
goes through
periodic in uh iterations
up to a total of like 400
um where you will see the curveback
libor divergence
being stopping at 0.49 but
if i let uh this run fully
until the curb liver divergence is
actually at point stops at point zero
three
um you that's my final
outcome which once this is finished
i will show you yeah
so that's that finished and this is the
outcome where the colors all represent
uh the 12 different clusters that have
been identified
so let us first just concentrate on
these the three green clusters here
which would all fall into traditional
propriolytic alteration zone as can be
seen with these three sample images
which i don't know about you but
i wouldn't necessarily always be able to
pick apart
or identify them as different things
there are slight differences but yeah
um so now if we first look at some
ams data then we can see for this purple
point down in the bottom
left of the gra bottom left
cluster
we have unique ip and op results
which isn't the case in the other two
clusters
however the other two have very
different tx results
where you have this group being
dominated by magnetite
but with very little change in
mineralogy and heating
and in complete contrast with the upper
cluster here
then we have
magnetite present but with the heating
forms uh no new phrases
so yeah that bottom bit you've got
pyrotype forming
with another phase and in the upper one
you've got not much forming it's
almost reproducible so if we now
go back to the full graph
and we uh
focus on this blue group which would
fall into philic alter
into the traditional phillip alteration
zone
again which can be seen by these two
data points that i've got images for
then we can also have
distinct ams results as well where
this group has
orange data point has distinct ip and op
ams results
however in this red group below then you
don't have
distinct ip and op ams results
timing there ali okay um
so now if we go back to the full graph
and isolate the orange group again and
this is the
our gaelic and advanced argument
alteration again i'll
go through all these for timing uh
but if we look at uh the tx results here
then we can see that this
top one you get the
complete er
you get the complete uh destruction
almost of magnetite
but then no parasite forming but in the
bottom one here you get pyrotype forming
from the magnetite
that was there originally
and so then go back to this last one
and we focus on this potassic alteration
which
actually is different to the others
because it's
got a very large statistical difference
that's been identified
between this one and this sample
um and then we actually this time look
at field dependent ams
then we can see the top top clusters in
the
minimum and intermediate axes then
it is field dependent in outer phase but
not in phase
whereas in the in phase and outer phase
for the
bottom uh cluster then it's neither
field dependent in either outer phase or
in phase
so what's next with this so as you can
see i've got a lot more work to do
to collect a suite of magnetic
characterization data
that will allow me to determine the very
subtle differences that the algorithm
is identifying between the different
clusters
and maybe even incorporate some more
magnetic statistics into the algorithm
i would also and it would be really cool
to be able to identify
um uh incorporate textural analysis
into the algorithm as well so the
clusters are based off both the rock
texture as well as the quantitative
mineral data
but let's um just leave you
with the final thought of my end goal
here
which is for the usefulness of this
method within industry to be fully used
to
help aid in more detailed mind modelling
and ultimately more efficient extraction
process
to achieve this then the collection of
the data
that i'm using will need to be fully
automated and
allow for multi as i said large
multi-billion pound mining projects
to collect large quantities of data um
really quickly and easily are there any
questions and thank you for listening
right question yeah
yeah very nice talk again thank you um i
was gonna i was wondering to what extent
that the addition of the magnetic
uh component to your 29
parameter space makes a difference i
mean do you have you compared the
clustering
output that you get with and without the
magnetic
input so just based purely on the
spectroscopy versus
spectroscopy plus the magnetic i mean to
how how i guess what i get trying to get
is is how much is your clustering
dictated by the
sort of the spectra the spectrum so i've
done
uh how much
additional added value do you get by
adding in the magnetism
yeah so with the um with the
algorithm it basically calculates that
uh how much
it's been dominated by each of the
different um
inputs and so the outer phase and in
phase
you get back it changes slightly
depending on the exact data set that you
run and how large that is but it's on
the region
of like with in phase and out of phase
of about 33 to 40
so it's quite significant um and that's
one of the reasons that i'd like
to incorporate more magnetic data
because actually
then hopefully that would produce more
data there to pull apart the differences
that
are obviously present statistically but
i haven't got the current data to sort
of
do that if i make it and i hope that
answer is yeah no
that answers exactly my question you can
actually quantify it you know
yeah thank you
hi oliver i i mean i've got a sort of
similar um
uh questions i mean yeah i'm assuming
that um
you're on mixing algorithms essentially
it's kind of an unsupervised
um algorithm so it's essentially
fitting the the end member spectrum
based upon the data that you
input is that correct yeah i mean have
you tried so that there are
you know catalogues of uh spectra for a
wide range of minerals
um because they often will have a a um
a defined um uh spectrum for for the
individual minerals
there's some variation there but have
you actually tried doing a sort of semi
supervised on mixing where you
are using a library of the spectra for
uh the minerals and then you're using a
essentially trying to find matching um
your data to this
library as opposed to to taking all the
information purely from
uh the the data set yeah
yeah so i have tried that and one of the
sort of
issues there is that obviously you get
a spectral measurement for a bulk rock
and the mineral libraries are single
minerals and therefore you can
very easily like identify
um minerals that it thinks are
present but are clearly not um
but like um going into the future
like it would be so the the actual
algorithm
that the statistical algorithm to
cluster
will learn these as more and more more
and
more data gets like run through
then it will learn where these clusters
are appearing
and um
like that will then form the beginning
part
of the new like data that you run
through if that makes sense i
does that fully answer your question i'm
not entirely sure but yeah