is which is from simon martin on
uh using ams for understanding flow in
analog
magma intrusions so
i have seen simon's name somewhere can
you see me
i have started sharing my video but it's
not coming up
no we can't see it right now oh i can't
one second let's just go back to this
i did that thing we were told not to do
there we go
yeah yeah we can now cool
me there we go you got that
no it's not changed for me just try
display setting it up
it has now yeah yeah you got it cool
apologies so um um
uh simon i've recently finished my phd
from the
university of liverpool with janine
cavanagh and uh
andy biggin and uh this is some uh the
work i did for one of my chapters
on uh using ams for understanding magma
floor
in analog magma intrusions it's some
work i did with a guy called procup
zavada
at the institute geophysics in prague
so how do we study daikin placement in
nature
we use a combination of geophysical
surveys uh
field studies ropey floor structures and
map across
other macro scale fabrics and uh micro
scale fabrics like crystal alignment
and also then uh magnetic anisotropy
so in the laboratory we study it through
two different models either a viscous
indenter model where we use a granular
horse material and a viscous fluid
or we use the hydrofracture type model
where we have an elastic host
and then uh either a newtonian or
monotonic fluid
um so some examples of viscous indenters
we have uh
this one here where we look to look at
complex intrusion morphologies we have a
there's an
igneous green black powder um and
we eat golden syrups injected into it
and to create like
complex dike like structures little sill
bodies
and cup structures and shape sill type
but you can also look at the horse rock
deformation so here you've got a silica
powder
um and it's been injected with golden
syrup and using digital image
correlation you can
look at the how the how different
particles move
during the experiment in terms of
elastic models
the most common ones are um using
gelatin models so this is a block of
gelatin here
uh it's dimmed because it's in a
darkened room
and then within the injected fluid so in
this case it's water
um in this case it's water uh you
put small particles which can be
illuminated by a laser sheet and then
you can use a
particle image follow symmetry to track
where different um
where the particles are moving through
time and you can
in this occasion we've actually showed
that there's a jet forming uh through
the center of the dike and then you have
uh
floor down floor at the edges of the
dike
so uh the aim of this project was to
understand the process that gave rise to
magnetic fabrics within intrusion
analog intrusions and my experiments are
different because they look at a
combination of intrusion morphology
and the associate magnetic fabrics that
are formed and
and then these magnetic fabrics can be
directly compared
compared with the ones we see in nature
so the materials that i use uh i use a
fine grain wheat flour about 420 kilos
of it
and for each experiment luckily it is
uh reusable or the majority of it's
reusable so it's not
as expensive as it sounds um it's a
cohesive granular material which deforms
under sheer intention
and then for the magma analog to use
plaster of paris um
with a mix of about 14 k 14 kilos of
plaster and seven kilos of water
and then it's a pseudo-plastic fluid
with a yield stress and it's seeded with
magnetite
with the magnetite dust and then uh it's
also had we also had a retardant
which which then delay solidification
from about half an hour which from the
time scale of experiment
up to several hours so all
solidification is post and placement
the magnetite particles that we use uh
here's an example from
uh paperback nov reptile and this is
um it's the same stuff we use here it's
uh
like filings from from magmatite from
the production of uh
i can't remember exactly what but um
and you can see the shapes and the sizes
and so you're we're talking
pseudo majority suitable singing go to
multi-domain
material so
the experiment set up uh we have a 1.2
by 1.2 by 0.5 meter box
with a piston inserted below and then
the uh the plaster is in a chamber
down down here and
it's injected at a constant rate and
then you've got
gopro cameras monitoring the surface
um some of the things we can change you
can have that include a membrane but
various depths within the tank and we
can change the mixing ratio of the
plaster so
lower viscosity fluids are higher
viscosity fluids and
and we've colored it in different ways
so using the concentric colouring you
can look at the internal fabrics and how
they develop
or with the sequential colon
cochlear we can look at time scales of
emplacements of which parts of the
intrusion form at what time
so uh here's the results from one
experiment
um from the suite that we did it's got a
two point one mixing the two to one
mixing ratio
it's got no membrane present and it uses
the concentric coloring
type pattern so at zero seconds
uh this is this is the box full
and it's covered with a colored sand
this is the surface like scattered on a
bit like a jackson pollock painting
and this is so that you can track
multiple multiple cameras can track the
same points at the same time
and the ground this is the area we're
going to focus on for the next uh
the next images and these ground control
points are 40 meters
40 centimeters apart
so this is that section and at 480
seconds
time lapse this is actually a fracture
system starting to form down here
in this orient in this formation so
just go back so you can see that and
then at 985 seconds you've actually had
quite a lot
of deformation the uplift of this
central section is uh
several centimeters and you've actually
got quite steep
ring fractures formed and then
at 120 seconds they've actually had the
eruption
and the subsequent lava flow form
so once it's run leave it to solidify
for for several hours we usually just do
it leave it overnight
and then so it's then excavated
and cleaned up and this is the sort of
structures we see
and so this is that same lava flow at
the top of the surface
the injection point is from below
um is a radial dyke system it forms an
initial radio dank system which the the
third radial intrusions out here you've
got one
and the other two there uh there's like
a central magma body which is like a big
solid blob with like a cup
uh cooked up a surface and then uh
convert to the
conduit to the surface and it's in rare
occasions we also get rested dikes
so dikes which are formed but don't
propagate all the way to the surface
um so looking at this section down here
uh this isn't blown up uh
you can on the surface of this you can
see some consent uh
some curved ridges and these are
actually asymmetric in shape and
in profile and i think i'll get to that
a bit later on
um yeah
and then so then using slices taken
perpendicular to the floor direction so
flow in this image here is
uh right to left and same right to left
here you can actually
look uh see how the internal fabrics
in terms of the colouring have developed
and you get this localization
here it through the core of the
intrusion
so here we now have the magnetic fabrics
and in the top right hand corner is the
ams ellipsoid and so
here we have slices a b and c
and what we do is we take five
millimeter diameter uh
cores from each slice as many as we can
possibly get
um and then from these uh
using a we can then look at the ams
and so this is what
these equal area plots
show magma flow is the arrow in the flow
direction
um the star is the initial flow
this is the long axis and these are the
short axis of the ellipsoids and circles
and what we see is uh this this
red area this is uh the imbrication the
maximum implication for
floor for the left margin and the green
is is the floor for the right
uh right hand margin uh and these so
floor is coming out of the page in these
images
and what we see is samples collected
from
the left margin uh imprecated in the
correct way of
inferring floor and this is the same
across
all all slices through here
as well with a slight a slight dip
uh something to note is that all the
samples are oblate fabrics
some of them quite oblate and then so
the diamonds down in this corner here
these are from the central zone and so
these are more triaxial to
prolate sort of fabrics
so if we want to link this to nature
which is something we can do with these
experiments
what we actually see is so these this is
uh four examples of dike
dykes with lateral flow from nature
with the long axis and short axes and
and these
uh what they what they show
is that they fit within these um
implication zones
and then they also match up nicely with
the implication that we get
from this model which supports the
interpretations from nature and also
backs up the mod
the analog models that we've performed
so the employment model that we've got
and so initial
this is this is what i've sort of
developed and it's
initially placement with the plaster
through the center with the floor
profile
and and then we get a build a stress
builder put the tip and a breakout
which is then creating these asymmetric
ridges on the sides here this is because
this is a top-down view and this is like
this asymmetric ridge in profile
and you get floor concentrated through
the center of the
of the intrusion with uh then of the
oblate fabrics
which we see developed at the edges
which created them by compression and
shear of the
plaster and the magnetite in the plaster
along along those margins and in those
margin regions
uh with flow focus through the court and
then uh
this happens again here
so flaw is further focused through
through the core
and it gradually it's gradually building
an increase in the thickness
up to a maximum thickness of about two
cent to about about three to four
centimeters
uh for the thickness of these intrusions
with uh multiple breakouts creating
multiple ridges and and
those multiple stages of the floor
so uh magnetic fruit uh some conclusions
of the magnetic fabrics in the intrusion
course of just lateral flow along the
dike which is
uh supports what we know and the
orientation of the dike compared with
um the injection point the oblate
fabrics in the margin suggest a
compression of the plaster and
implication of the flow towards the dike
tip
imprecrated fabrics in the intrusion
margins correlate with studies of dikes
from the
from nature and a range of external and
internal structures
observed in the experimental intrusions
helped test emplacement models as well
thank you very much
thank you very much simon has anyone
got any questions
at all
yeah all right okay go ahead
well nice talk simon thanks so much for
that that was great
so so based off the results that you
have
here the used what sort of
data set or or do you have kind of a
field area in mind that you can
most readily compare or that you'd like
to sample to compare to these results
to try and really unite the analog model
with
with the field exam
um in terms of dykes i think this
uh this can be applied to
any any dyke so any
wherever you've got really good exposure
of dikes with no alteration which is a
which is a key point um then
uh you can wait so you can get primary
floor and
and things like from the dike then yes
there's this
whole host of places you can go and i've
also done
experiments or an experiment where i've
also created a lackluster
body and so i've not sampled that for
the ams yet
but for that i'd like to compare that to
somewhere
potentially like sand fell or like a
sill type body like
uh like mult like the big uh where
you've got
really nice several kilometer exposure
of the same
sill
yeah it's funny you say that i happen to
know a guy who's got a good ams data set
from sand phil
yeah so do i
[Laughter]
fair enough
any other questions
um can i ask a quick question if you can
hear me
yeah we can uh i said i i didn't get to
meet you there the last time you opened
said andrew simon but um
just like because interesting talk just
you know the way
you your fabrics are comparable to the
field examples
when you do this um this modeling is
right
was there ever an example of this
post-emplacement sagging or collapsing
uh you know like a kind of a downward
flow being captured within these fabrics
or
um so i did run an ex
a trial experiment with a mixing ratio
of for plaster of one to one so it was
uh it was very very liquid and as we
were injecting it
um when we stopped the injection there
was down floor
uh back down into the um back down is
the conduit
however with these large uh with the
larger intrusions
uh we sorry with a higher mixing ratio
uh left the gopro cameras running one
time like way beyond like for a couple
of hours afterwards
and from what i remember i don't think
we saw
much much sagging out so even in the
lava flow at the surface
i don't remember seeing much like that
and then from
and also from um
just from leaving it and going in the
next day
the shape of the material in the conduit
seemed
very similar there wasn't a massive back
floor into the conduit