next one who is which is from
craig martin on paleocene latitude
of the koshan lad arc arc
an initiate indicates multi-stage indian
eurasian collision
whether i pronounce that all right i
have no idea but i'm
sure i'll find out all right let me just
share my screen
can you all hear me and see see my title
slide
yeah we can alright well i can
great that's that's enough for me no i
hope you can all see it um
so yeah i'm very excited to be here or
here in 2d today
to present to you um some of our
paleomagnetic results from the western
himalaya
which we believe indicate that the india
eurasia collision was actually a
multi-stage process
rather than a single stage continent
continent collision event
so before i start i'd like to
acknowledge that this is the work of of
myself and a number of co-authors i'm a
student um of professor oliver yagoots
at mit
and the work was supported by the nsf
and also some internal mit funding
um so the closure of oceans and
subsequent continental collisions are of
course a fundamental component of the
wilson cycle and and are
important in plate tectonics and
our most spectacular example to study
the processes involved with continental
collision
is of course the himalayan karakoram
tibet origin in in
south south asia and so i'm showing you
a map here of
um the sort of western half of the
himalaya it's it's a
kind of tectonic map um
and the closure of the near tethys ocean
which once separated
india and eurasia is now preserved along
the the narrow suture zones which
transect the himalayan belt they're
shown in thick black lines on this map
and so in the central and eastern
himalaya india and eurasia are separated
from each other um along just one suture
zone the sangpo sutures
and but in the western himalaya the
tectonic sort of arrangement is
different
so there india and eurasia are separated
from one another
and by the remnant of a jurassic to
cretaceous age
intraoceanic subduction system
which is now sandwiched between the
indian and eurasian continents
and so in the western himalaya
the intraocyanic terrain is separated
from india by the indus such a zone
and from eurasia by the shaykh such a
zone
so the timing of collision is well
constrained
on the northern indian margin to the
paleocene
between 55 and 60 ma
by the arrival of volcanic archdetritus
into indian margin sediments
and some other proxies but
the metamorphic response to collision in
in tibet is not really observed until
the the
the mid-ear scene so around 40 to 45
ma um and so
the age of the shaykh such a zone which
separates the cursed arc from eurasia
is still disputed so that has been
argued to be as young as 40 million
years old
to as many as old as over 80 million
and so the differences in how we
interpret the ages
of of collision events and the ages of
these structures
has allowed two conflicting collision
models for the india eurasia collision
to persist
so in the in the standard model the
india eurasia collision is considered to
be a single stage continent continent
collision in which india moved rapidly
northwards across the near texas ocean
and impacted the southern margin of
eurasia in the paleocene
however plate reconstructions show that
there's
thousands of kilometers of separation
between india
and the eurasian continent at this time
and so accordingly it's been interpreted
that there has to have been a a large
extent of
india that's now that's now lost and
up to two up to an and above two
thousand kilometers of of
north south extra indian continent which
is
referred to as greater india
and so the alternative model that's been
suggested
is that in the near tethys ocean south
of eurasia
a and in the intraoceanic subduction
system
which is preserved in primarily in the
western himalaya
was active at a near equatorial latitude
um
until it collided with the northern
margin of india
in the paleo scene and then final
continental collision in this model
did not occur until 40 to 45 may after
the closure
of um of an ocean basin which which has
been called the shiroda ocean basin
so this this multi-stage collision model
is attractive
because it reconciles the separation
between the indian and eurasian
continents at the time
of collision with the amount of crustal
shortening that's been observed
in in the himalayan belt
and also the the activity of a second
subduction system which we're calling
the transtethian subduction zone
south of the eurasian margin throughout
the closure of the near tethys has been
argued as a as a potential explanation
for the rapid motion the anomalously
rapid motion of india
during the late cretaceous
so crucially each of these models makes
a distinctly different prediction
about the location of remnants of this
trans-tethine subduction zone
um in the late cretaceous and early
paleocene time
so the single-stage collision model
requires that this intraoceanic
subduction system had accreted onto the
southern margin of eurasia long before
the arrival of india whereas and so it
should be situated
at a paleo latitude of greater than 20
degrees north throughout late cretaceous
and paleocene time
whereas in the multi-stage collision
scenario
the intro oceanic subduction system
would be expected to be at a more
southerly paleolatitude
near the equator until it collided with
india
in in the paleocene
so we set out to to resolve between
these two
conflicting models by doing a
paleomagnetic study
of the cardin volcanics in in ladakh
in west india so the canon volcanics are
a suite
of rhyolitic volcanic rocks that are the
extrusive equivalent
of the coast and ladakh arc batholith
which is this intraoceanic
terrain in the western himalaya um
and so and we
studied the upper section of these of
these volcanics because
um the presence of ash horizons and and
sediments
interbedded with the the rhyolite
volcanics allowed us to
get a a good estimation of the paleo
horizontal so these rocks
are tilted towards the north and so
in the south the carbon volcanics are
bounded by
the plutonic rocks of the of the
batholith and then in the north they're
bounded by the structures of the shark
suture zone
so that's the the sort of structure that
separates the arc from the eurasian
margin
so we did some ex some precise uranium
lead zircon geochronology
um from throughout our sampled
section and we were able to constrain
the age of our
volcanic rocks to between 61.6
and 66.1 million years so this puts it
just before
the collision uh that just before
collision began to affect the
northern indian margin and actually the
age range overlaps with some of the
first
uh ophelite abductions onto the onto
india in
in pakistan so
the 44.5 ma age range is long enough
in theory to average the the secular
variation of the geodynamo
um and the the age of these rocks
is should help us resolve between the
two models because it constrains the
location or will help us constrain the
location
of the intraoceanic subduction system
shortly prior to
the india the collision initiation on
the indian margin
so for our paleomagnetic sampling you
i'm assuming most of you will be
quite familiar with this we sample 5 to
13 oriented calls drilled from
individual volcanic flows at each of our
sites
we demagnetize those samples using
alternating field and thermal
demagnetization techniques at the
mit paleomagnetism laboratory
and then we use principal component
analysis to isolate individual magnetic
components from our from our samples
and a combination of the unblocking
temperature and hysteresis experiments
shows that the the primary carrier of
magnetization in our samples is
single domain or pseudo single domain
magnetite which are good
paleomagnetic recorders and so
our results as you can see here define
two antipodal populations this is the
results in geographic and tilt corrected
coordinates we have
18 site mean orientations
and these antipodal populations when
plotted against stratigraphy
and resolve all but one of the expected
magnetocrons for the for the age range
of our study
and so the presence of these expected
magnetic reversals is a strong
indication
that the uh magnetization of our samples
is a
is not a post-depositional overprint
and because such an overprint would of
course be expected to
over to completely obliterate the
reserve the reversal record
and to further confirm that our results
are primary we conducted conglomerate
tests at the top and base
of our sample section so this is an
example from the
test at the top of the section uh on the
left here
and as you can see from the distribution
so in a
in a conglomerate test the you would
expect class magnetization directions
to be randomly distributed and because
that's how they should be
from from being transported and then
redeposited
and as you can see on the left our class
magnetization directions are indeed
randomly distributed and we confirm this
using a watson test for randomness which
which passes in all cases
so because we're confident that the
magnetic
the magnetization directions of our of
our samples are the primary
record from when the volcanic rocks
formed
we can use them to determine a
paleomagnetic pole for the cardinal
volcanics
and therefore the transtation subduction
zone shortly prior to the india eurasia
collision
and the uh uncertainty angle of uh um
of our paleomagnetic pole is within the
acceptable uh constraints of dean in a
tile 2011.
and so this pole allows us to constrain
the coast and ladakh arc
and and therefore the transtethian
subduction system
to a paleolatitude of 8.1 plus or minus
5.6 degrees north
in in the time range between 61.6
and 66.1 million years ago
this paleo attitude is is in our view
significant because it allows us to
construct to
choose between the two uh conflicting
collision models
our results are uniquely compatible
with a multi-stage collision model
because they place the inter
oceanic subduction system significantly
south of eurasia
at uh the in the at the cretaceous
palestine boundary
so that's our plate reconstruction
showing the coast and ladakh arc
um and it's positioned between uh
600 and 2300 kilometers south of the
contain
contemporaneous eurasian margin
and so the presence of this oceanic
plate
between india and eurasia after 50 to 55
ma
explains the explains the
difference between the amount of
convergence expected
in the in the india eurasia collision
and the amount of observed crustal
deformation
in the eurasian and indian margins
and our results also put a firm upper
boundary
on the maximum size of greater india to
less than
900 kilometers
so here are our results again presented
against the
um plate reconstructions from van
hensberg hotel
uh 2019 um and this black line
is the predicted paleo latitude of the
intraoceanic subduction system
using the double subduction model of
yaguza tile 2015 so this is modeling the
double a double subduction system
and as you can see our results are in
good agreement with that with that
prediction
and also a multi-stage collision model
is in good agreement with the available
plate reconstructions
so we believe that our debate our data
supports a multi-stage
india eurasia collision model in which
first
india sorry india collided with an intro
the inter-oceanic subduction system
at 50 to 60 ma and then continued to
move northward while the shiroda ocean
basin subducted beneath eurasia
before finally colliding with eurasia in
the continent continent collision at 40
to 45
ma that's 15 million years later than is
generally assumed
so this collision chronology
is well preserved in the western
himalaya where the indus suture zone
records the first stage of collision
between the intro oceanic
coast and ladakh arc and the northern
margin of india this
sushi zone is well constrained to 50 to
55 million years
so final india eurasia collision then
therefore occurred along the shaykh
sangpo sutra zone
not the indus sancpo such suture zone
and it's constrained
in the western himalayas to between 40
and 45 ma by the chemical changes in in
the ladakh batholith
so with that i will uh i'd like to thank
again my co-authors
and and and sponsors um i'd specifically
like to thank
my undergraduate field assistant jade
fisher who was incredibly
helpful in the field and and also my
hosts serwang dorje and stanzan kando
who
who graciously accommodated us in in
ladakh during our field season
so with that thank you i i'm happy to
take questions um and if you're more
interested in this work and don't get to
ask a question and though
it is published in the proceedings of
the national academy of sciences now so
you can find it there and i'm also happy
to answer any questions by email
so thanks very much
thank you very much craig so
has anyone got any questions that they'd
like to ask
yes i have some questions
uh did you consider uh
from anaya so if you look at repellent
network from
third schema it suggests
[Music]
it's already a part of the tetramena at
60 ma
so remaster clad before 6
mma so sorry which which which
measurement are you talking to you cut
out a little bit i i i i miss you
there are a lot of a lot of magnetic
data from
test human iron so they're highlighted
at 60 ml is either same are the data
from an
attack so that means they are already
together
you mean the the work from pakistan
no not from pakistan
from the tether similar sorry i'm i'm
sorry if i'm i'm misunderstanding okay
so
the the the data from the tethys
himalaya
is um well that's that's
sort of been interpreted to show that
india that greater india extended
hugely you know the the greater india
extension was large but
i'm not sure of any tethers himalaya
data that would
constrain the location of the of the
ladakh system
i would argue that our data is from you
know
from igneous rocks and for you know
i i see i you're right there is a there
is a problem in the in this
sort of field because we have some data
from the tethers himalaya which is
primarily
sedimentary originated paleomagnetic
data which puts
a large extent on greater india
whereas and our data conflicts with that
but i would argue that
um the a smaller extent of greater india
not only agrees better with the
paleomagnetic data particularly
particularly from from our study but it
also
matches the amount of under thrusting
beneath the
eurasias so the the seismic
imagery beneath tibet shows that the
indian continent is only subducted by
kilometers so i i think it's quite hard
to imagine
why um it's quite hard to see how you
lose
over a thousand kilometers of
continental crust
um in the in under thrusting so i think
it's it's important to now
look at that paleomagnetic data and ask
well why is it giving us
latitudes that are so far north it's
possible that those sediments formed
you know in association with this
intraoceanic system
at least that's what i would argue
and also i think the paleolithic you
used for nasa has some problem
because a lot of magnetic
data suggests resolving your asia your
lasso block is located at something
about
15 degrees not 30 degrees so
i mean so we compared it to the that
means
the starting ratio is my
you're right so you're right if if you
raise your sorry you've got a set
then then it it makes it harder to
distinguish the cursed in ladakh arc
from eurasia so
we're comparing our results to the play
reconstruction of van hinsberg and hotel
which incorporates much of the most
reliable
as far as unaware all of the reliable
paleomagnetic data
from from tibet so that that from lasso
particularly so so that's the
that's the uh that's the latitude that
we're comparing our data to
okay thank you very much for the
question there's another one from
connell in the chat who said how do you
decide
the hemisphere it also it's also
consistent with greater india
with large rotations dot dot dot
yeah that's that's referring to the the
um
the the are you referring to the the
data from the tethers himalayan or the
or the data i just presented
i have no idea so we know that so we
we
are another hemisphere because um of the
inclination direction right and
these rocks have not been rotated 180
degrees from
from their original orientation
i i guess my question how do you know
that
how do we so well i i mean the
because they form aren't you know that
they're still the right way up right and
if you
have twisted them around completely like
there just isn't structural
support for that in in the in the field
you know you can follow this unit across
tens of kilometers of the region we work
in in northwest india
and it you know to to rotate the whole
carbon volcanics by that much would
would be
you know it doesn't make sense in in the
field i would argue