the talk i would like to give today is
on
the topic of my phd which is
a new 3-axis automated stepwise
thermo-magnetometer system
which i have named smarter
so a bit about me um i started off
as a mechanical engineer and then
i got turned into a paleomagnetist twice
once when i was in undergrad because i
worked with uh professor joe kershwink
to create a in-situ field magnetometer
system
which we then used to study um
figurines in guatemala which
apparently you can tell the
apparent sex of the figurine heads
by looking at where they have a
lightning strike
simultaneously to this in 2015 i started
a master's
degree also at caltech where my
specialization was in paleomagnetism
then when i was applying for phds i
decided to combine
the two and became a paleomagnetic
engineer
in effect my thesis is
prototyping the next generation
versatile paleomagnetic laboratory
i finished that in september of
2020 and one of the main results from
that
is the new automated magnetometer system
that i'll be talking about today
so in a normal paleomagnetic laboratory
you have a few options for what type of
equipment you want to use
and you have a very cheap
very robust but also very work intensive
option
of the jr6 spinner magnetometer this is
a extremely good piece of equipment
um if for example a lab is shut down for
seven months due to
unforeseen circumstances and then you
want to reopen the lab
the first thing that will work is the
spinner magnetometer
to go with that you also need a way
to get either
um a thermal demagnetization
or an afd magnetization and so you then
need a separate piece of equipment
to actually demagnetize it to then
measure everything on the spinner
magnetometer
for scale on these two pictures
the squares that are made by the
cages are 2 feet
on each side or 60 centimeters
there's another option it is faster
and sensitive but much more expensive
and this is the rapid system
this is a picture of the one we
currently have here
for scaling purposes it's the same
60 centimeter squares
and the sample changer lets you use up
to 99 specimens at a time
that will then be automatically measured
um which is extremely helpful it means
that
for example you can give a presentation
at magnetic interactions
while something is running on the other
side of the lab
and okay so that's great
still very large and
there's um another option to go with
that
where if you want to avoid having to
pay much attention to it you can run
each sample individually in situ
and in the case of the rapid this is
done with an afd magnetization coil
which is built in this is extremely
helpful
because it means that you can get an
entire paleo direction
by clicking go and never having to come
back
and the other option is used
pretty much exclusively by the
university of liverpool laboratory
and it's the tristan microwave system
this is a stock photo because the system
is currently down for maintenance
but the idea with this one is
you can get one paleo intensity estimate
at a time
so you can fine-tune the data
and the experimental procedures after
you get each data point
so then the question is we have these
two ways of doing it we have a good
system
to get alternating field
demagnetizations quickly
we have a good way to do paleo
intensities
um with the very specialized microwave
equipment
but then the question that comes after
that
is can we take the best parts of each of
these
and turn them into something new
so in order to do this we need to then
get
a temperature range that will cover most
magnetic minerals so at least 600
degrees in order
to get uh magnetite
or um 700 degrees if you want to also
get hematite
then there are um
another requirement that we need our
three axis full vector
uh measurements both paleo direction and
paleo intensity data would be best
a goal is for it to be solid state so
there's no movement while measuring
um one goal would also be no movement
while heating or measuring to do the
same in the same place
this one does not do that we wanted
specifically
to see if we could do this using high
sensitivity squid sensors
and most importantly we wanted a more
moderate cost
uh there's no way we're going to be able
to get this as cheap as a
jr6 spinner but we're trying to get
something
that isn't quite as expensive as a rapid
system
so this is the very prototype design
it has um an automated control system
it can give you a thermal
demagnetization and give you a paleo
direction
in about 30 minutes using 30 degree
temperature steps it will give you full
vector 3-axis magnetic data
and you will notice that all the parts
used are non-magnetic such as the
aluminum rf shielding
or the wooden quad pod
and the metal shield of course is
extremely magnetic on
the flip side as our primary source of
shielding
the control system for it is relatively
straightforward
the temperatures are input or calculated
as
the case may be it gives an output file
that outputs squid voltages
and it can be run in different modes
depending
on how many squids are installed
in mine i have two installed but you can
have up to three
as a function of the actual squid
controller box
and so the squid sensors are the
part that makes this more difficult
and that's the internal part and so the
superconducting
quantum interference device sensors have
to be
extremely cold in order to operate
we use a high sensitivity um
squid sense high temperature squid
sensors that have a lower sensitivity
than the ones you find on the rapid but
the flip side to that is they only
require liquid nitrogen temperatures
instead of liquid helium and
for this design that we have here
we can use between 8 and 20 millimeter
outer diameter specimens
10 millimeter is the preferred but
for some applications 20 millimeters
will work
but the main limiting factor since a lot
of paleo
intensity studies are done on basalts is
that anything
substantially larger than 10 millimeters
tends to saturate the squids
the one drawback to these squids is that
they operate in the radio frequency
the radio spectrum and that means
that they're very sensitive to any
external interference
such as someone having a cell phone
someone being on a computer people doing
building work
police sirens going by and
that's where all the thin aluminum
shielding that you can see on the
internal and external diagrams
comes into play
so one of the great things is that we
now
have preliminary demagnetization data
all these data
came um during the
pandemic basically because it started
operating
in february and on the left
we have two example orthogonal plots
from two of the samples that we've been
running
these are from hawaii so they are
young and real samples but we gave them
laboratory
um trms in the down z direction
or in the up z direction depending on
the exact experiment
and as the orthogonal plots
generally have a trend of being
downward but it's not perfect
on the right side uh plotting these on
equal area plots the equivalent data
from the rapid
are extremely good almost exactly
what it should be within the margin of
error
of just the re-magnetization process
with smarter the data are a lot more
scattered
but the correct answer of
an inclination of 90 falls within the
alpha 95
so is it a replacement for the rapid no
can you get quick estimates from it that
seem
generally reasonable on average yes
so then the next step is can we get
preliminary paleo intensity data
and the answer is
maybe so the protocol used
is a stepwise demagnetization in smarter
followed by an external re-magnetization
in
one of the um magnetic
measurements thermal demagnetizing
systems that i showed previously and
then a second
stepwise demagnetization
these diagrams that i show here are
meant to look similar to arrive lots but
they are not
the same um
plotted here are the
relative magnetization
of the first attempt at where it was
supposed to be a
40 micro tesla lab field then a 60 micro
tesla lab field
and from the slopes we can see that
there are estimates
that are in the high 50s which is pretty
good
considering we were trying to pull out
but the r squared values are
relatively poor
and because of that i doubt these data
would really pass any type of selection
criteria
nor would they would most um arrive plot
selection criteria
really be able to apply correctly to
these
so this is still the work in progress
that i've been working on
um since everything started reopening
so the question then comes how did how
did we do
compared to what we were wanting
we get the 600 degree temperature range
thereabouts
we don't get the 700. we have automated
measurements
we have believable paleo direction data
on
average maybe we can get paleo intensity
data
from this to be determined we do have
solid state there's no measurement while
moving
there's a measurement before and after
there's movement before and after
measurement but it doesn't require
spinning or vibrating the sample while
measuring
we do have our squid sensors and the
cost is relatively
moderate um unless you include
the cost of my international tuition
here in the uk in which case it probably
costs more than a rapid
and so in summary smarter lives
you can get the 30 minute
demagnetization that we wanted
paleo intensity is still in the works
it is ideal for pilot studies but more
precision
is definitely desired and as you can see
the design
is very prototyped considering
the quad pod is something we just had
lying around
and so the design will need finalizing
before this really can be
taken forward thank you for listening
um i'll take any questions that you
might have
thank you for the talk so do we have
anything any questions
yeah if i i've got a question where i
can jump in so
um i have two questions actually so you
talked about directional data
maybe you said this and maybe i missed
it but if you're doing directional data
what size of the samples because you
know the smaller the samples
the harder is you know there's more
handling
errors in you know putting the sample in
and stuff in terms of getting directions
so
uh so the ones that i used are 10
millimeter
specimens so that they are
sufficient that you can actually orient
them
unlike the tiny five millimeter
microwave course
that are basically unorientable
um but these are big enough that
you can actually put for example a
circle on them and orient them
but with some of the more sensitive
applications
you would need to use the bigger sizes
that are
possible with this okay
okay i have another question so so you
so so this system doesn't you can't
apply a field so you can't apply
a trm so like i think the triax system
which is out
being advertised outside and the put i
mean that can apply a field so is
are there any plans to to put that
option
into the instrument so you don't have to
take the samples and
you know induce a trm or something else
where
so there is currently um a way in fact
to apply a field
in it um the current data do not take
advantage of this
because um i tested it
back in march before everything shut
down
and the oven design that's used
um takes advantage of the actual
helical design of the oven
and part of the advantage of being in
lab is i can show you things
so this is an old oven that as you can
tell is not coiled very well
but inside the oven is a counter coiled
wire the oven itself is non-magnetic
because it cancels itself out
but we determined we can actually run a
field along
this helix which itself is not
counter-coiled
and we can get a applied field
um in the oven space precisely but
not near the squids
okay so so in the future it might be
possible to do
all the all the the intense experiments
entirely inside the instrument
is that yes that's the so okay good