uh let's talk first paleomagnetic data
from the
bleismeier darlor
exactly just what i said so when you're
ready there adrian take it away
uh thank you conor hopefully you can all
see my my screen there
so this is work that was done with uh
morton resources and now at the
ferrari's geological survey and connell
who's just been speaking
um there was a number of uh summer
students
imperial so stefan mathia and hassan
who's now doing his phd at uh
cambridge who helped all the
measurements plus uh
an m i think it's ms or msi
student at in oxford called carrie who
also help with the measurements
um so why did we go to
northern iceland and collect some
samples and what was the point so
let's just go back and have a look at
paleomountains and 101
um one of the things you first learn
when you do paleomagnetism is the idea
that the magnetic inclination we measure
uh tells you about the paleo latitude so
tan i equals two time land and we all
know that
and this is based on the assumption if
we average the geomagnetic field over a
long enough period of time
um we end up with something called the
geocentric axle dipole so we essentially
have a dipole field
which is aligned with the rotation axis
and hopefully everyone who's in the
audience should be familiar with this
now the question is how long do you have
to average the field so
here's uh some some different uh periods
of being
of averaging so in figure a we have up
here we have
historical data and you can see we don't
quite have the guard
is what we expect to be the proper guard
field and we don't
quite have the guard here if we go from
zero to seven thousand years
again it doesn't quite match match this
and if we go over a longer period of
time so and work by katherine johnson
and catholic constable
they looked at a period of five million
years then again you can see it doesn't
quite match up with the
with the gadfield and if we have a look
at this
in a little bit more detail um
so this is now looking at the deviation
from the gad field as a function
of latitude this is for directional data
so
it's just deviation so that a perfect
guide field would be plotting the data
should be plotting along this line in
the middle
and you can see that it seems to deviate
as a function of latitude
um and we have to fit components
permanent components of
um of uh quadrupole and optical
components down here six or
three percent to get the directional
data to align
uh to accommodate this data um
i presented some of this data at a
meeting in cape town 2017 it was one of
these sessions that was combined
modelers
and um and data people
and i presented the data and data didn't
agree with their
theory and i was told the data was wrong
which i think was
i didn't really agree with the time
because you know the model should follow
the data not the other way
right so that's the directional data but
if we look at the paleo intensity data
that the deviation is even bigger so
here we have in this
figure here we have the again we have
the bin data it's been folded around so
suddenly the northern hemisphere data
is combined together and we have the
green points here
are the uh of the data and to try and
get anything to sort of
so here we have gray line we have the
dipole models this is what we would
expect we'd expect it to
the intensity to increase from the
equator up to
um up to the uh northern latitudes
and if you look at the data which is
which is for the last five million years
uh collected from the pint uh database
which andy biggin and the guys in
liverpool
um very kindly administered for the
for the entire community um you can see
that the
we don't get that trend we kind of get
something that comes kind of
sort of increases and then a very high
latitude it seems to go down
um now one of the one of the complaints
up against the period intensity data is
there isn't that much of it especially
at high latitudes there's a lot of data
here
so this great this green band here shows
you
the sort of error on these estimates and
you can see that there's a lot of
very narrow bands here and the reason
for this is because this is where hawaii
is and
people like to go to hawaii and sample
the rocks there but
to go to other latitudes you can see
there's quite large errors and
one of the complaints of them the
modelers have said well you're the
reasons your data doesn't fit the model
is because you haven't got enough data
points
and so this is particularly interesting
at high latitudes um
and paleo intensity data is particularly
sensitive at high latitude so here's a
figure from catherine constable
where she when in this figure if we have
these different sampling points we have
a look we have an equator a mid-latitude
and a high latitude depending on what
parameter we're looking at declination
inclination or the intensity um
depending on that when we project the
sampling
area of the at the core mental boundary
of the field that we're actually
sampling project down onto the commental
boundary from what we're measuring on
the surface
you can see that the intensity data when
we measure high latitude is really
sampling a very
high latitude data whereas if you look
at the um
it's affected by this region here so
we're actually if we measure the
insulation that
in iceland say then we're actually
being affected by this large area here
of the field where it's generated
and the declination is even even worse
so you really lose
the intensity data is the most sensitive
to
to high latitudes variations of the
field
so we wanted to locality
with high latitudes uh lots of
continuous lava sequence and something
that's relatively new modern so if we
we want something where we can
essentially ignore plate tectonics so
iceland is the perfect locality and it's
a very simple geology you have a sort of
spreading ridge down the middle
the further you get away from that the
older the rocks get so this is nice
simple geology um so we decided to go
there and
sample some rocks now you can't mention
field work in iceland without mentioning
leo christensen who unfortunately died
earlier last year
from from cancer um he just retired
that's really quite tragic well not just
retired but he'd retired a few years
before but
he was still quite young as that was
quite tragic um
now leo has done amazing field work in
iceland he spent the last 40 years going
everywhere and we've been to some of the
localities that he's been to and
they really are quite hard to get to so
he's really a great field geologist but
leo never really liked paleo intensity
work
he didn't really believe in pearly
intensities i thought he didn't work
very well so
all the work samples that he's collected
and done the literally thousands of
sites that he's sampled he's always
focused on directional data whereas we
think
the intensity data is actually more
helpful in this case so
while there's a wealth of data for
iceland there isn't actually that much
paleo intensity data
so several years ago
with colleagues martin connell and also
audi dussing from
dtu in denmark we started sampling
various locations in iceland so we
started off here
in east iceland and we published a
couple of papers down here
on the work there we did a phd project
in
in central iceland here with a student a
come still yet to publish that
data unfortunately we took a long time
to get the organ dates so that's why
he's been a bit of a delay in
getting getting that published um
but what we wanted to do as part of this
study was to try and tie up
the the a to get some continuous
sequence so we wanted to tie up the
sequence with the
the sequence over here so we wanted to
collect some samples that were
slightly younger than the ones who have
been sampling as part of a's phd thesis
so here we have is blake's blake's me
red de la and i'm sure conor's going to
correct me for that
and this is the valley that uh eight did
his phd it was even harder to pronounce
the ear fjord
the law is where we did this work and
connell's done
field work in there and also brendan as
part of uh one of
his uh msi project when he was in oxford
also helped to sample some of these
localities here so these are the ones we
studied before
and we wanted to sort of tie something
in it was quite close but slightly
younger so we're injured in this valley
here
now this valley is very very easy to get
to there's a dirt track road that dries
up you just take a four by four you
drive along it's quite simple to get to
blake's mirador which is this one here
is pretty much uninhabited there's no
roads there's no nothing
so even though it's not very far to get
to from here to here it's actually quite
hard work so
we ended up having to drive quite a long
way across this kind of surface here
which took us an awful long time so it's
not
that it's a long way it's just that it's
kind of hard to get to and remember
driving off roads can be dangerous so
you can see down there that
someone else a little bit less care
careful than we were we're getting there
so i just want to stress that getting to
this valley is actually quite a lot of
work
um we spent just over a week there
sampling
uh spent our time crossing uh rivers
which are just above freezing and
getting this is connor here and this is
me on on the right get eaten alive by
flies so it's a wonderful
sampling place but um there's some great
sections so
you know those we've found three great
sections so i mean morton had actually
been at the the year before to the same
valley and mapped it all so we we knew
what we're going for when we're actually
sampling this is one of our sections so
we typically
collecting the lavas we start at the
bottom just work our way up
connor likes to drill and the rest of us
kind of follow him
up the hill um
so we did standard the paleomagnetic
analysis the the data is very
very nice all the data from iceland
tends to be very nice you have a little
viscous component and then
bang straight to the origin whether it
doesn't matter whether it's thermal or
af it tends to be very well behaved
unfortunately for this particular
week we were there we got very little uh
sun so we had very few sun orientations
and
for those who are used to working who
know about working with
large sequences of uh you tend to get
quite large magnetic anomalies
um associated around that and work we've
done in
elsewhere in iceland you can routinely
get values deviations of
20 to 30 degrees so unfortunately this
particular the directional data that we
got wasn't
really good enough to do isn't really
good enough to do directional
analysis of the guard field but it is
good enough to do we need to strike a
few so we need to build an age model so
we've managed to
use combining the studiography in the
field with the minitos trigger field we
started to build an age model
um again we are waiting so the age model
isn't complete but we we know the
the ages are between something like 3.2
to 2.5 million years
i'm not going to finalize this because
we're currently
uh getting some samples stated in these
called bride
um argan samples are organ dating and
they've been with them two years now
they said it happened by december 2020
and we haven't got them but i can
happily wait another month or two for
for that and so that the age model isn't
quite complete but hopefully that will
be soon but the main focus of our
uh what was really um the paleo
intensity work so
unlike liverpool it's like doing a multi
uh protocol
technique and i actually do like that
approach doing lots of protocol the
problems and you've got lots of samples
do
you do how'd you do it so we've we've
just attended to try and process a lot
of samples just to stick to techniques
that are tried and test
tested and don't give any problems with
the
with the reviewers so we've done the
izzy technique which is a type of tele-a
method
and we made attempts at getting a paleo
intensity but we only end up with 52
estimates which was a little bit lower
than what we'd hoped for because in
previous
work in iceland we had a success rate of
up to about 60
for the for the rocks but but these
particular ones we had a success rate
of less than uh 30 percent anyway i'm
just showing you typical arrive lots
some curves i'm not
um
okay so then to jump to the results
where we had all these samples we ended
up all these
individual sites we ended up with nine
estimates for the uh
paleo intensity from from only nine
sites something we had to chuck away at
the
site level as well as at the individual
level
so if we look at the pint database here
we can see this is the
for the for the same bin that we're
looking at we can see the mean pi
is here and this is the data that we've
collected so in the whole it's slightly
lower than what was
there before but not that much lower
okay oops so how does this relate to
the data the figure i showed you so
here's the figure i showed you earlier
with the data we're interested in this
particular
what we're doing is just sampling this
point here so before there was
i think a total of about only 48 per
intensity
estimates that's from 48 sites make up
this particular point in the pipe
pipe database after you've put in some
criteria to select points so you know
minimum number of
uh estimates to make a site reading that
sort of stuff
so the argument from the modelers was
that our this data point
should be further up should be closer to
this dipole curve and the reason it
wasn't
higher is going to have enough data so
the idea would be if we added more data
added more data we should be going
moving this point
up now of course i've just shown you on
the previous figure that
our data actually lies beneath that so
it's down here so it's
lower than the average so of course when
you add in
uh sorry when you add in the extra point
rather than moving this
so so this blue point is now the
combined mean of what was in the
pint database plus uh our new
blix mirror you can see that we've
actually moved
the screen point has moved downwards to
where the blue point is so if anything
we've moved
away from the gad model so it would
appear
that this small contribution to the
total data set is
suggesting that the data is not actually
uh it doesn't really fit this dipole
model
so just i said it's going to be a short
talk so just to wrap up the conclusion
there's obviously still
more work to be done here i haven't
shown you any any rock magnetic data
which i
have measured but not really analyzed
yet
um and we obviously need the organ dates
as well
um so the new data does not support the
guide hypothesis at high latitudes
and you can tell i just added this uh
the second point
following on from andy biggins talk
yesterday so the models i've shown you
these calculations for the
for the contributions from the octopus
and uh
quadruple field these are these are
calculated using the giant gaussian
process models
and a lot of people have used those uh
lease attacks and
kathy constable and i've in the paper
that i published i
i used one of the one of these models to
to do that um and perhaps
we should be not using these types of
models and moving away to some of the
ideas that andy said about
trying to um yeah trying to use maybe a
dynamic model to try and predict
the behavior especially at high
latitudes okay thank you for listening
bang on 15 minutes thank you for that
adrian it's a
very interesting talk so we time for a
quick question or two
i'll i'll ask a quick question if i may
um just about the um
uh your selection for the for the for
the gad model
um from pine what um were you specifying
certain age range were you
um strict on the data selection
technique so on
i wonder what you're comparing against
um
this is from memory because it's from
the 2017 paper but it's
it's we tell a data only so that's
obviously chucks out quite a lot of
stuff
zero to five actually it wasn't i think
we we removed the first thirty thousand
years so
thirty thousand years up to five million
years because obviously you buy
there's so much data from the first 30
000 years um
and then i think we have to have at
least three estimates
from a site to give it and then
obviously the
deviation less than 25 i'm not sure what
the value
is of how many having three points and a
deviation of less standard deviation
less than 25 percent that's getting a
bit
dodgy on the stats but that's thing that
was the criteria i'd have to check
what the other ones were yeah i think
those are the main ones
okay fair enough yeah um yeah now i'm
looking at
the databases should give you a fair
fair sampling from
russia and um and greenland and stuff
yeah i mean
just really very surprising results that
you show in that region like very
very low paleo intensities for such high
um high latitudes
so yeah i know
and well we know the thing is the new
data we've got
is low as well but it it doesn't really
disagree that much with the previous
data which is also low so you know i
don't think there's anything shocking
it's more
it's just a question of what's really
happening to the field at high
uh high latitudes and you know if you
look at the
if we just assume a gadfield at high
latitudes if you do a paleo
reconstruction i mean rna estimated that
you get a up to 500 kilometer
you know mismatch in where you're
predicting it should be
whereas if you've got a field that's not
quite a you know with a five percent
octopus quadruple component so you know
it could be
an issue for people who are using gad
we all a lot of people use gad right as
part of the as part of their paleo
geographic reconstructions and maybe
need to be a little bit more careful
with that in terms of
you know what's the error on you know
maybe it gives you a chance to move
things around a little bit more in your
reconstructions i i mean you know
potentially it could be because you're
between the flux patches right so your
high latitude flux patches which are
dominating dad you know or dominating
the the dipole
i suspect it is the flux patches and i
suspect you know using a dynamo model as
you were talking yesterday might be a
better way to try and make predictions
of what's expected at high latitudes
because i'm not sure these these
gaussian models are
i mean they're quite simple right so you
know not really capturing all the
features
yeah but it would be dynamo models would
need to have some
uh heterogeneity on the core mantle
boundary
to uh to to to get the flux patches to
be
stable i was going to say the flux
patches would have to be stable and
long-lived but that does that's quite
quite possible at least on these sorts
of times girls
tens of millions of years
you can just make time for just one more
quick question and we'll move on to the
flash posters
uh i have less of a quick question and
more of just a
blatant self-promotion but the new ggp
model that
we put out does have a sort of
some zonal non-zero components that do
try to match
at least um the the cromwell
uh inclination anomaly record so like i
said blatant self-promotion but there
are some ggp options out there that do
kind of
capture some of this that was about it