the next talk which is eduardo davine
uh talking about testing the reliability
of sedimentary paleomagnetic dataset for
paleogeographic reconstructions
uh take it away can you hear me all
right
yeah i can't perfect so my last name is
i know sorry it's italian don't worry
sorry
i'm used to that so can you see my
screen
yeah we can perfect
let me just
yeah okay so i want to talk to you about
um
it's basically a paper just got just got
published a few weeks ago
and is yeah it's about how can we
possibly test the reliability of
sedimentary paramagnetic data set
because
i mean sediments for the temporal and
the spatial distribution are very
important for parallel geographic
reconstruction so we want to be sure
that
the data we use are reliable
and why
so for people that were listening to me
last year they made my remember that i
was talking about um
new caledonia so some sedimentary data
from new caledonia and they're very good
in terms of magnetostratigraphy
so the direction themselves are reliable
they appear reliable at least but we
have a problem
especially about the inclination
inclination is not fitting with the
expected one
and also we have something to say i
always say something about the
unresolved availability sustainability
so is there a way
to assess the reliability of this
data so the problems that really is not
purely theoretical
stuff from real data and
how do we do that we want to investigate
the effects of
finite strain on simulated distribution
and we see different cases
and then there's what do we learn from
that what we see in the end so
it's just to see the outline of the
presentation
so it's just a bit off let me just set
up
uh the frame the geographic frame new
caledonia is in the
is a small island in the southwest
pacific so it's a
it's a portion of the norfolk reach so
all these
continent that you see here is called
zealandia and it's mostly submerged
but it's quite important for
understanding the dynamics of the
subduction initiate initiation of the
pacific play beneath the australian
plane so
since there is no much cropping out so
you either go and read as we did
with iodp expedition or you study
whatever
is cropping up and new caledonia is just
one of the few places where you can
study these sediments and
there is a section in particular in the
northern part of the nile of the island
with this this
transition between pelagic uh microsoft
carbonate sedimentary to a summary
plateau
to turbidites and it's this transition
is important in terms of the
regional geology and evolution
but if we focus on the lower part of the
section we have a beautiful data set
there is also some extra slides if you
want with some zyder
so you can show you can see them so we
have reversals we have very
consistent declination inclination
and the age model is quite clear so the
age is about
48 million of years ago around this age
and
so the data itself it does look reliable
especially if we take the direction we
don't take the direction from the
turbidites because they're not as good
as the lower part so we just want to
focus with a good data set and we have a
total of
88 i didn't put the number here but 88
directions
positive reversal test we use a
bootstrap approach
other than the normal the traditional
reversal tests usually
they um they assume that the directions
are
fissure distributed that's not always
the case
so with this bootstrap approach i'm not
going through the details but you
overcome this limitation
but the reversal test is positive and
we can see here that we have the data
set with the bed in implant
if we if we look at the data set in tilt
the corrected
coordinates just look at the blue one so
it's
the blue reference line they're clearly
more the inclination is higher it's a
lot higher like
something about 10 degrees other than
the one that we expect calculated from
the compilation of thor's week
and but we also know that there is a we
measure the unexotic magnetic
sustainability and
it's not um sedimentary
so if you look at the the plane
that lie between k1 and k2 is not
coincided with the sedimentary place so
that is clearly like something that ring
about
in terms of the reliability of the data
in terms of polygeography that's what we
see so this is new caledonia this
paramagnetic
is rotated compared to the the position
that we would expect but we know that
because nucalidon itself
is rotated so it fits with the
with a structural frame or sorry but the
inclination
is so the paramagnetic pole is clearly
off
is also true that the compilation of
tarvy tosvig used
data from other continents mostly
there's only one entry which is
within this time window all the other
data are coming from other continents
and they go through multiple rotations
and this is the parallel latitude that
we calculate with our data this is the
palu geographic
and global reconstruction let's say and
it's clearly off
so where is the problem
is the problem in the compilation or in
our data
we know that uh yeah there is like a
kind of fresh
regional compression but the the
straight are not heavily folded
so there's no indication of like heavily
the full menstruator that you can like
assume that the data are not reliable
so if you look at the literature there
are different phenomena that could
deviate your directions from the
original position the first one
the well-known one is the inclination
flattening
and if we measure the susceptibility of
the it's out of your society in this
condition we would have a
an oblate tensor and then as
we start deforming the straighter a bit
more we can imagine no cell compression
folding direction pointing to the north
we start having different um
fabrics like the weak cleavage fabric
will result in a anisotropic magnetic
stability
prolate in shape and then the
more extreme condition with short
cleavage strong cleavage and we would
have a
triaxial and this is the theoretical
evolution of the inclination that is
being published in some some old papers
so you could have either uh depending on
the flag on the
limb of the four you are you could have
shallowing or sleeping
so now uh we know and andy was talking
about that before the
the direction distribution uh we know
that they're not fisheries but they
they're a bit more complex so one of the
models people
put forward in the last few years is a
tko3
one of the assumption is that the vgps
are circular and that results in a
specific side the direction are not
circular but they are
elliptical and the elongation is
calculated
using the ratio between these two
eigenvalues so we simulated a saw um
a set of directions for different
latitude
they are drawn accordingly to this model
so
in this case we have the inclination
here and the elongation
and we see that it varies depending on
the inclination which in turn depends on
the latitude
and this method has been applied in the
past for
correcting for the inclination
flattening for example
so we gradually can uh increase this the
inclination of a set of direction uh
and the elongation vary until across the
expected values
so this for example is the same data set
as b correct
using this idea for inclination
flattening
so what we did is try to figure out how
not just inclination flattening but
other mechanisms could change
the shape of the distribution so we
started with a circular distribution for
two reasons
it's easier to visualize and
second is not necessarily far away from
the reality because if we sample
one single strata we are not expecting
to ever image averaging out the
circular variations so we would have a
fisherian distribution which is not
far away from a circle so we applied
different scenarios
to this circuit distribution which is
inclination of 50 degrees
and radius of 30 degrees we applied
first a flattening
and then just a pure shear
simulation and what we see for example
in this this
this is the gradient diagram where we
see the inclination and the elongation
this orange area is the area where you
would have
directions that are only affected by
inclination flattening
so they are potentially they potentially
can be corrected with
the method that we saw before
everything that falls here is not
reliable so it's clearly affected by
some problem
and yeah what we see is that when you
apply
a pure shear we immediately jump
to condition that is not realistic
anymore but it's not entirely released
so we wanted to we know that we also
have folding
so what we have to do is also apply a
folding to the data
what we do is just apply a minimum
tilting of the strata
and then we apply the pure shear
to both the direction and the bedding
and we get into a situation that is um
very similar to the one predicted by the
model
that we saw before so we can have either
depending on the limbs
on the fold that we found ourselves we
could have shallowing
or steepening it's very interesting that
this problem
is higher when we have a
pursuit a compression let's say that
it's not parallel to the declination
so it's affecting the shape of the
distribution a lot more but more
importantly
we don't have an elongation that is
neither parallel
nor perpendicular to the average
declination
but it's crooked and you can see that
from here
so the ellipticity is reflecting the
shape of the distribution
and that because that's what we expect
either from the model or for
the data that are just affected by
inclination flattening
either parallel or perpendicular when
it's not there is clearly something
something else affecting the data
after that okay we decided to work on
the generator the simulated data set to
see something a bit more
realistic in the first case we did we
applied again
just a pure shear without tilting
which is not entirely realistic i know
but is uh
it shows very well how the shape of the
distribution change
and one of the things that we can see is
that as soon as
we have an angle between the the
compression let's say
and the declination the directions
immediately jump
into distribution shapes that are not
acceptable
so they don't go we have some situation
where we can have something that is
falling into this
sedimentary kind of state
so increasing flattening state but in
most of the case
when you have an angle not even that one
there's a few degrees
you jump straight to directions
distribution that are not reliable
but we know that it's not entirely
realistic so we decided to do
just for two distribution 10 degrees of
poly latitude simulation simulated
latitude and 40 degrees
the series of events that could could
happen in reality so we apply first a
complex
compaction flattening of 0.6 and put it
here but i saw the standard let's say
sedimentary
flattening and then the possible weak
cleavage
and strong cleavage in both limbs of the
fold
and see what happen and
these the the red and the pink
um ellipses are the original
distribution they are lie
on the expected and we can see that when
we are so here
we can now go through all the diagrams
and photo but we can see basically this
is the
weak cleavage state the strong cleavage
stay
the front limb and the back lean and
they all create
different situations but
yeah we could see them when we apply um
like strong deformation they generally
jump over to the situation it's not
possible to correct anymore
and this is a lot stronger again
when we apply um stress let's say
finite strain there is no parallel to
the declination which is a very likely
situation i would say
and all the distribution you can say you
can see they jump immediately to shapes
that are not realistic with this model
i'm talking about this mod
and one of the thing is again the
elongation is crooked
so it's not it's not parallel to the
declination
as we would expect so this could be also
used
as a reliable reliability index so that
the
the elongation in this diagram is
represented by the dotted circle
where in some cases like for example is
passing through the center
and that will be parallel with the
declination
some other cases not clearly
so going back to our data
can we apply this kind of uh theory to
this so what we did is just so uh we we
say we have
88 direction which is not a lot this is
a
reasonable number but it's not like um
the problem is i want to calculate
confidence confidence margin
and the only way at least the one i know
is about bootstrap
using booster and we can see that this
is a 90
confident boundary it's quite wide but
still
um from the complete data set
we also filter some direction that i had
some criteria
i can yeah i can show you maybe like uh
if you want
so it's mostly
yeah and what we see is the the complete
data set
it looks reliable if we feel that the
data is a bit less reliable
and then we try using the direction from
the
magnetic susceptibility tensor to
unstrain the direction to see what
happens
if we apply an unstrained technique
this direction and what we see is that
we entered the condition
of elongation parallel to the
declination
with very similar results but still we
are far from the
expected inclination which is this one
so um
final remarks we're still in a pico
about this direction because we we are
more inclined to consider
the the direction not reliable because
of the
ams measurement something that i want to
outline without the unexpected magnetic
sustainability
this dataset will look reliable so
there's something that
should be always presented when we use
the direction for parallel geographic
reconstruction
and that should be done together with
adequate um with a
proper number of direction normally a
hundred
it's considered and some other standard
reliability tests like the usual
fault test and and we recommend also to
you to do also the distribution shape
analysis
and with new caledonia it's probably we
need more data from the area because
all the data are rotated so yeah they
are probably more correct this one even
if they are rotated but we are still in
a situation where
there's no data from the area
and what about the limitation of this
method you need a lot of direction to
have
nice confidence margin and
we actually don't know i think if this
model is valid
always so
that's it i always finish with a picture
from new caledonia
oh thank you very much has anyone got
any questions yes
go forward hi that's great talk thanks
um i was wondering there's i i've also
had some
some strange inclinations in the eu
scene and i think they're reported for
many parts in the in its ethium belt
do you think that maybe it has something
to do with that my inclinations are
always very shallow and they're
in volcanic rocks and i think they find
them from
from spain all the way to the east
i was wondering if you have any idea ah
so you may
i have a kind of blood memory in the
past that read some paper that i say in
the
in the some part of the cenozoic maybe
the three was not that polar at least
yeah i think there's a paper of westfall
and also of kanye that's
um speculate about this but i yeah yeah
because this thing is quite new so it's
uh
yeah it would be interesting to check
that
i i have no answer right now so yeah no
worries