come now to the law session of
this conference uh
titled new developments in magnetic
theory and techniques
and our four first talk is by evelyn
baker at all title uh prices based model
on chemical remnant magnetization
equities acquisition
and comparisons to thermo remnant
magnetizations
so you can take it away and share your
scheme
everyone see my screen yes
okay cool um so yeah i'm evie um
and we've been modeling chemical
remnantization acquisition by using
plastic theory
um along with my supervisors and we've
also been making some comparisons to
thermal remnant magnetizations
so there we go so first i'm just going
to talk briefly about um what a crm is
um just kind of to remind everyone so a
com is recorded
when magnetic minerals grow through the
blocking volume
and then they record the earth's field
um as they go through the bottom volume
and can no longer respond to changes in
the magnetic field
um and this can occur this occurs below
the kiwi temperature
so there are two main categories of crms
these are a growth crm so this occurs
when
magnetic minerals grow in a non-magnetic
matrix
so examples of this are hematite
precipitation in red beds and also you
can see here in this
um backscatter electron image that um
this is for a marine sediment
you can see that you have these pyrite
um kind of fanboys here marked by the p
and you can see that greg eye is
precipitated here marked by the g
um in between these these pyrite fanboys
which has shown that it's precipitated
orthogenically
and is therefore recordedly crm um as it
grew
and the second type of crms is an
alteration crm so these occur when
minerals alter to form magnetic minerals
these can be more complex because if you
have a magnetic precursor the field
that's recorded
is a combination of the earth's field
and also fields associated with that
primary magnetic phase
so things like exchange interactions and
crms occur in almost all environments on
earth
and in the solar system and so it's
important to kind of understand their
properties and what sort of remnants
they have
and um you know if there's a crm
component to our trms how is that
affecting paid intensity estimates
that's why we're trying to
learn more about them so now i'm going
to talk about
kind of what works previously been done
because there's been a lot of study on
crms
um today so the studies previously have
come from a theoretical or an
experimental perspective
so from the theoretical angle um people
have modeled
or made predictions on comm behavior by
using the al's theory for
non-interacting single-domain grains
and made predictions for example about
the serum intensity um
and the unblocking spectra and some
comparisons to trms
and other other studies have used
modelling of green growth crms so
there's been monte carlo simulations
which have included interactions
um and they've looked at the com
intensity and also again the the effect
on blocking spectra at high temperatures
um and alongside this theoretical
studies there's been
a lot of experimental studies and these
have included a wide range of minerals
and uh looking at lots of different um
types of crm acquisition so grain growth
com and onto the alteration
so in this figure here in the middle
graph you can see that the cm intensity
um you can see how the serum intensity
varies with changes in the applied field
and these are for experimental um
studies looking at hematite so about
90 degrees they precipitate hematite um
either in like a non-magnetic matrix or
or from the alteration of non-magnetic
mineral and you can see that you get
this linear relationship between the
comm intensity and the applied field
which is kind of what we'd expect which
shows that you know cms
should be able to be modeled or looked
at so what are we doing so for our study
we've developed a or we're developing a
model of cm acquisition for
interacting single domain grains and
we're doing this in physics space
and what this allows us to do is it
allows us to use the thought diagrams as
input for the for the model
which allows us to model crms for
specific samples um
so firstly i'm gonna try and give you a
brief overview of
the um thermally activated present model
for randomly orientated single domain
grains which we use
so prysic theory is a statistical
approach to modelling magnetic processes
so instead of trying to model each
visual grain in the sample
we're trying to model the statistical
behavior or the behavior of the magnetic
assemblies
as a whole um and we do this by by using
isaac theory
oh i'll go back again so if you see here
um on the right hand side this is kind
of plasic space and you can see that
it's split into
four regions or three regions so you've
got the field blocked regions and the
super paramagnetic regions and in in
these zones if a particle or a histogram
lies
in this part of the plastic diagram it
won't be recording a remnant
magnetization
and then we have this green region which
is a thermally blocked region and this
is where
um particles or histones which lie in
this zone will be
um recording or will have acquired and
be recording and contributing to the
to the magnetic remnants so
these uh thermal critical curve shown in
black and
and the price distribution here vary
with time and
thermal effect so these move during
monetization processes
um and we can kind of model how these
change relative to each other to to see
kind of what monetization we're
acquiring
so um the way we populate pricing space
is we use a thought diagram so
if you use a plastic diagram which is
kind of similar to a fort diagram but
symmetric concussivity axis
if you you can see how it kind of
rotates 45 degrees and can be used to
populate plastic space here
um and then what this allows us to do is
it allows us to populate isaac space the
large number of historians and then we
can track how these historians behave
during crm acquisition for example um
relative to these barriers and then how
the monetization gets acquired
so each historian has its own thermal
critical barriers which evolve at the
time
which is worth noting and depending on
when they cross depends on the alignment
between the earth's feet or the
magnetization on the field
which affects the the mounted of the
remnants um also another thing to note
uh the last thing i'm going to say about
a slide is that uh
the earth's field or the um applied
field shifts these this part and the
thermal critical barriers
as you can see here by this ha um and
kind of in nature this is actually a
very small bias but i've just kind of
exaggerated it for this for the sake of
this schematic
so now i'm going to talk about how we
can use this model to look at grain
growth cm
acquisition so the start time um of com
acquisition
is when the particles are very small and
you can see that most of them
here's the price distribution most of
the histones are lying within the
superpower magnetic region
therefore they're not recording your
magnetic remnants
and then as the grains grow you can see
that the
the thermal critical curves are contract
contracting
and you can see that we're starting to
move into the remnants region and we're
starting to require a remnant
magnetization
and then at the final volume when the
grains are growing and when the histones
or you know when the
particles have reached their final
volume you can see that now the majority
of them lie within this remnants region
have acquired a magnetization and then
when we turn off the field this is our
final kind of magnetic remnants
you can see that it's um the
thermocritical curves are symmetrical
about the coercivity axis
and the histones which lie in this green
region are
contributing to the to the magnetic
remnants and if we sum up the
contribution of all of them
we get our crm so now i kind of talked
about how the model's built in fighting
space i'm gonna
kind of briefly um so an important part
of our model is the growth rate
so in a crm you know we're we're growing
our inner graduate crm that
the the particles are increasing in
volume kind of what rate should we be
building into our model
so we looked at the literature and a
recent study looking at pyrite fanboys
found that um they grew on the order of
order of days
obviously these are much larger than our
single domain
um particles or magnetotype grains that
we're interested in
but we get a growth rate um by using
this of about 10 to the minus 12 meters
per second as a radial growth rate
um and also if you look in the
literature further there's lots of
studies on like
growing microplate in the lab and they
found that single domain
magnetite grew on the orders of hours to
days which also gives um
very similar growth rates so that's the
growth that we use and we can
incorporate the growth rate into our
model in terms of an effective time
um which you derived which shows how the
how the
rate of growth affects how long the um
magnetization has to align with the
field at each volume step
so now i was kind of going to introduce
you to the outputs of the models
and the way the model works is we get
our final volume distribution from the
fork diagram of the pristine diagram
and then we we shrink these down to
nucleating and all of the grains have
the same growth rate
so therefore in order to get our
variation in volumes at the end we they
nuclear different times so
time equals zero in the model is when
the largest grain nucleates
and you can see that as you increase
time when we get to about 15 hours
um is this is when the majority of the
the particles are now nucleating and we
start to see a visible increase in the
mean radius
and then we actually have to wait until
about 22 hours until we get any
contribution to the to the magnetization
and this is because we have to wait
until these grains are growing through
the through the blocking volume
so as i mentioned we use literature to
look at the growth rate so we kind of
wanted to know
how does our model how does crms vary
with growth right and also
it's we also wanted to you know now
we're using our model to investigate the
properties of crms
so yeah so we looked at how crms how the
intensity changes with the growth rate
and what we find is that for for growth
times on the orders of hours
compared to growth times on the orders
of millions of years there's only about
a two percent
increase in the clm intensity so the
crms aren't particularly sensitive
to to the growth rate um and the other
thing that we we did is we can look at
how the serum intensity changed with the
applied field
and again as we saw in the um
experimental studies you get this linear
relationship and yeah clearly we see
this in our model
too and you can see here that um the
crms have all been normalized to the to
the saturation
isothermal monetization which we can
also um
model um using pisa space and
kind of now is a good time to mention
that we can make comparisons to trms by
using the
for the same price distributions by
using the trm acquisition model that my
supervisors developed back in 2011
um using 563 tlm acquisition you can see
here that they both increase at similar
rates um
so now i'm going to just talk about how
we can change the price distribution
to look at crm intensities and what we
find is that
so we can increase the amount of
interactions in a sample by
increasingly spread in the y axis of the
thought diagram
um of the prison diagram and we see that
as we increase interactions we get a
decrease
in the crm intensity this is because
when you
um increase the interactions you reduce
the alignment between the
um applied field and the histones
magnetization upon blocking so when they
cross those thermal critical curves
they don't align as as well so you get a
reduced magnetization
and the other way that we can vary the
price of distribution
is by changing the cohesivity so this is
the spread along the coefficient axis of
the
of the preset diagram and we can see
that as we increase the cohesivity we
decrease the intensity of the of the crm
so now so if i've looked at intensities
but we can also look at the
behavior of the crm um in response to
demagnetization so we can start to look
at the unblocking spectra
um and we can do this using thermal
demonetization or alternating
field demonetization by simulating these
processes again
in prison space for the samples um
for the for the crms that we've just
acquired and what we see here is that
when we
so the blue line is for this extreme
case of low interactions and the
green line is for the high interactions
and we see that we get a
we seem to get a slight increase in the
stability of the magnetization when we
increase interactions
but again you can kind of see my error
bars it's it's not particularly
significant in the minute and you know
we need to run on higher um
with higher number of histones and
higher resolutions to to really look at
this
um which i haven't quite had time to do
um
but yeah so this is kind of what we see
and we again can see the same thing in
the thermal d-max spectra
um again using the same particles and
they they um
they mirror each other quite well so
so far we've looked at crms we can come
we can make comparisons to the
unblocking spectra of
thermal demagnetizations compared to our
crms for the same price of distributions
so here for quite a high currency sample
with kind of medium to low interactions
we can see that the tm intensity is
higher than the crm which is which you
know
what we'd expect but the demonetization
spectra look quite similar in shape
um however when we go to loco acidity
samples so you know we're getting
towards the
the y-axis of the fork diagram we can
see that now
both of them were unblocking earlier but
also it seems like the
the difference between the serum the
tier may be a bit larger and the crms
are magnetically weaker than
than the terms in comparison it's also
worth noting that at this low cost
the crm intensity is more sensitive to
connectivity changes so now the tm and
the serum test are actually quite
similar in magnitude
but the demonetization spectras look
more different
um so kind of in summary
what we've looked at is we're developing
this model and i've kind of shown some
like preliminary results of what we've
seen
and we can see that crm intensity varies
significantly when we change the price
of distribution in terms of coercivity
and interactions
and both increasing the interactions and
the correctivity caused to this causes
or leads to this decrease in intensity
and we can see that the crm and tm
have different unblocking spectra and
they respond differently and
kind of um by different magnitudes to
changes in
in the price of distribution so kind of
what we're looking to do next is we're
going to apply this to experimental data
so we're going to use for diagrams that
have come from lab grown crms
and they've been acquired in the lab and
then looking at kind of what behavioral
model shows
but this was heavily delayed due to
covert but hopefully we'll be able to do
this soon
and thank you for listening and do you
have any questions
thank you so any questions
uh yeah i have fun um
that was a really great talk uh very
enjoyed that that was uh
really nice work i was going to ask
about so you showed one figure
which was the the the the drop off in
crm as you increase
these interactions it's quite quite
marked and
uh quite an important result i think um
how did how did that graph compare with
the
the equivalent trm i was wondering
yeah so the tlm also decreases with
interactions
and this is something that we're kind of
still investigating because um
it doesn't seem to be so they both both
the tlm and the crm obviously they both
decrease when we increase the
interactions
um but the the way that the ratio
changes we haven't quite constrained
because it does seem to change quite a
lot with the coercivity so the
cohesivity has a larger effect on the
crm to tlm ratio so i'm still kind of
looking into that but it looks like it
doesn't have
um there's a large effect um on the
ratio as they both decrease
so roughly similar amounts
yeah it seems like it but yeah thanks
yeah
so any any more questions
i've got one if if i can go ahead yeah
evie great talk um i know you mentioned
the beginning it had consequences for
understanding of early soil system
evolution
and it might be too early to sort of use
your results to
to further that effort uh right now but
if you were to tentatively say
something right now certainly with
regards to sem acquisition during
aqueous alteration
uh during the early solstice do you have
any um initial observations there
um i don't think i could comment on that
yet
um i think it's something i'm really
interested in using like you know
when we kind of develop this model and
once you've applied it to experimental
data
then we can kind of think about how it
might affect that but i think at the
minute it's quite um
kind of just looked at kind of synthetic
samples so i don't think i can make a
comment but
it would be interesting to be able to
kind of model some acquisition for these
you know yeah because we think they're
really important in the solar system
stuff
it'd be really interesting and hopefully
um soon this model might be more helpful
at looking into that and
how they're affecting the remnants but i
don't think it's quite there yet
so i think i could comment on it awesome
thanks a lot
and that's why i'd like to go with it
but yeah
any any more questions so we have time
for a couple more
well i guess my other question is so
i mean you're modeling the prize at
distributions you'll show
this sort of nice ellipse of uh
where i mean if you look at rand what
the
shape of fault diagrams for um
interacting single domain they have to
have rather a different shape they have
this kind of more teardrop
shape i don't know if you've modeled
that and also when it comes to looking
at the solar system stuff that you know
like the
you look at ursula's poster which has
these framboids and plaquettes and
things like that and the fork diagrams
there
look uh again rather different to the to
the prize at distribution so is that is
that a direction you can go in to
to to model more realistic
uh prizette distributions yeah so
synthetically
we we kind of we're starting to look at
modeling these kind of tear duct shapes
that's something that i'm
kind of trying to model at the minute
but um kind of initially i've just been
kind of
using the ones that are kind of the
simplest cases basically kind of look at
the changes but um
yeah and we started to look at like um
kind of multi-domain shapes just kind of
investigating the parameter space really
um but yeah so it would be interesting
to be able to model more complex fort
diagrams but i think that's something
that will come with the experimental
data
so when we have experimental studies
then we'll be using real kind of thought
diagrams i think then we'll start to see
how they respond to these
these shapes and things so i think
that's kind of what i'm waiting on for
that mm-hmm
if i could just jump in i mean i was the
feeling was that when we were doing this
we should
we're just going to test the model on
some arbitrary forward distribution that
we should just choose some nice gaussian
distribution as a starting point and i
agree these are a bit artificial but
that was kind of deliberately
chosen because if we're just worried if
you chose you might end up choosing
something it's a nice single domain
sample and it's
not really in has a weird shape to the
fork diagram we're maybe
going down a rabbit hole so that's where
we stop these gaussian distributions to
start off with