right into it and we'll actually start
on home ground here in saint andrews and
we'll start with
tobias matson and he'll be
discussing decrypting magnetic fabrics
ams
arm a irm through the analysis of
mineral-shaped fabrics and distribution
and isotropy
so when you're ready to voice
so yeah can you see my screen yep
okay so i'm tobias and i'm a post doctor
researcher at the university of saint
andrews
but i'm also affiliated to stockholm
university in sweden so
i'm a visiting scholars in dangerous for
two years
okay so i'm going to talk about
the source of ams fabrics
in rocks and in particular igneous rocks
and igneous rocks usually the main
magnetic carrier is
titanium magnetite or magnetite and then
you have essentially two types of
fabrics
petrol fabrics that might contribute to
the ams fabric and that's the shape and
isotropic
which is basically that the ams
ellipsoid is controlled by the
the axis of the magnetite and for
example if you have multi-domain
magnetite
uh the long axis of the magnetite
crystal will correspond to the k1
the longest axis of the ams ellipsoid
or you can have a distribution and
stupid controlling the ams and
this is due to the magnetic interaction
between
for example magnetite and ferromagnetic
fiery magnetic
faces and i have an example here so for
example we have a
distribution which is like this in the
magnetite
and this would correspond to a k one
axis in the
ams ellipsoid point in this orientation
however studies on natural rocks
natural igneous rocks have
seen very minor or no relation between
distribution and institute and
ams and they have argued
over the last 20 years that distribution
and entropay is not a significant
process
generating the ems fabrics in igneous
rocks
however these studies have been on rocks
which
have uh have where the magnetized
crystals are
occurring as free-floating crystals and
they are quite far separated from each
other
so they haven't studied rocks where
magnetic crystals are
closely clustered to each other and
therefore you can argue that they
haven't really
looked at the right sample to see if
distribution in isotropy can be a
significant factor controlling the ams
overall
so the the question really that they
want to answer with this
study is can distribution and
instruction
significantly affect the ams mark
and to study this i've chosen samples
which is a trachea endocyte and it's a
porphyrite trachea and design so it
contains
larger crystals which you call
phenocryst
or uh amphibole and also
uh one volume percent of this rock is
magnetized phenocryst
and fifty percent of the magnetite
phenocryst
in this rock occur in clusters so they
our potential here in this rock to see
if uh distribution
anisotropy can be significant in the ems
of this rock
so um we choose because um
analyzing distribution and histography
and shape fabrics can be
quite time consuming because you need to
scan them with
a ct or x-ray tomography
and the separation method takes quite
long so we only choose five samples from
five samples five sub-specimens from
five samples so it's
not a huge date uh sample set but
there's a huge amount of data that we
get out of this
uh and these samples were analyzed for
ams
a irm so an isotropic isothermal remnant
finalization and
an isotope of anesthetic ground of
magnetization
and i used a 15 position orientation
scheme
with uh alternating field of 100 melee
tesla and a dc field of 50 micro tesla
and for the irm i used also 15 position
orientation schemes so the hex positions
uh with single diesels of 20 milli tesla
and i also scan these samples and due to
the contrast between the
these phases in the rock i could pick
out
the magnetite and amphibole shape and
distribution fabrics
using the x-ray ct scan and here you
have a
image of the x-ray city
and i guess when i scan these rocks or
the samples
i got 16 micrometer resolution
meaning that i can't see the smallest
magnetic faces in these rocks i probably
can't see
a single main magnetite
we used i separated the crystals
from the scans using the software blob
3d
and i should set a lower limit of 500
boxes
which basically means it's the volume of
the pixel
times 500 as the minimum
limit for magnetite is it to limit
processing time
and remove also some some noise and for
amphiboles at
a minimum limit for them at house a
thousand boxes
okay so um
to analyze uh the data that i got cut
out from the
the x-ray tomographies of the x-ray
scans
i used the software called tomafab which
was developed by my co-workers
and with this software you can calculate
length weighted crystal axis
eigenvectors
which basically generates a ellipsoid
with the
opposing axes that you can directly
compare with the ams
and remnants fabrics
and then for this paper or this study
i've been with them and developing an
another feature of tomofob
uh where we basically insert that you
can analyze distribution fabric in this
software
and then we used the definition by
stevenson
1994 which basically decides
the strength of interaction so
this is the weighting factor for the
distribution and histogram so we have
the omegas which is the volume of the
two grains
and then we have the distance between
the two grains
and this basically says that crystals
that are
larger volume and closer to each other
uh
gives a higher weight to the
distribution and isotropy
and this is also then presented as an
ellipsoid
with three opposing axes which you can
directly compare
with the ams fabric
so first we look at the shape of the
magnetic crystals so here i have a
backscattered electron image
of magnetite
and you can see that this is how they
commonly look in the rocks so we have
magnetic crystals occurring in clusters
if we separate them
they have these nice cubic shapes
and yeah cubic equine shapes uh
but with some degree of shape and
isotropy anyway so i mean this
this there's a difference between the
longest and shortest axis
um most of the crystals that we
separated or in the size range of
0.2 to 0.4 uh
millimeter long axis so this is the
and yeah most of the volume of the
crystal to be separated
occur in this size range
amphibole is prolate cigar shape
so you can see an image of a separated
amphibole
here's a backscattered electron image of
the amphibole and
you can see at the rims of the amphibole
you have these kind of
white speckles and that's actually a
breakdown ring in the amphibole
which contain magnetite you can also see
there's some
inclusions of magnetite in the alphabet
so this probably affect the magnetic
fabric of the amphiboles
yes here is the ams data from the whole
sample set so the small black arrows
point out the samples that were later
analyzed with the micro city
but what i essentially want to show you
is that
the data set or the samples are
represented for the whole or the
subspecial tissues are represented for
the whole sample so they're not outliers
to represent the fabric of the whole of
the whole rock
i also have a temperature accessibility
experiment
showing that the curves are not
reproducible between heating and cooling
uh but we also see a distinct drop at
around
570 580
degree centi centigrade indicating that
magnetite this or detainer magnetite is
the main magnetic carrier
but we also have uh probably magnemite
which which basically results in that
the curve is not reproducible between
heating
heating cooling
so now i will go through the data from
each
each of these samples so i will start
with
the shape fabric here which i have
plotted in lower hemisphere
equal area schmidt nets so first
start with mankind so this is the long
axis and you can see the long axis
plot in east west girdle distribution
which is then corresponding to that we
have the
maximum axis of the magnetite here and
the
intermediate axis here and the minimum
here amphibole
plots in a cluster
on the distance on the eastern side of
the stereo net
and we have a maximum of shape fabric
available here
and intermediate here if you compare
this with the
magnetic fabrics ams a irm and
a ir a rm we can see that
the maximum is located in the eastern
hemisphere and the intermediate in this
uh
it's already sub like sub horizontal in
the south
um and this basically shows that
the mass here is uh not really
controlled by the shape
completely controlled by the shape of
magnetite
but rather the the shape of the
amphibole crystals but also
the magnetic distribution and histogram
of magnetite
because you can see here we have the
dark gray symbols with uh
dashed outline which except essentially
shows the distribution and historical
the sample and it is
basically coaxial with the magnetic
fabrics in cb50
cb19 which is another sample we have
here's a little bit more complex we have
a east-west
girded distribution in nine tight long
axis so the shape fabric
we have a more of a cluster in the
southern hemisphere
for the amphibole shape fabric
while the magnetic fabrics plots in the
northern hemisphere
so they seem to be inverse to the shape
fabrics but also the distribution fabric
in magnetite
which is shown by these symbols with
test outlines here
so here the magnetic fabrics are inverse
relative to the shape and distribution
fabrics
in cb46 we have a
east and the western girdle distribution
in magnetite shallow smooth dipping we
have a
multi-modal dipping skirt distribution
for amphibole
here why the magnetic fabrics are
steeply dipping north-south
girdle distribution and if we look
at the different petrol fabrics so the
shape
fabric of magnetic and amphibole but
also the
distribution fabric of magnetite you can
see that
clearly the distribution fabric is the
most stupid thing so here the magnetic
fabric seems to correlate
mostly to the distribution fabric of
the magnetite in cb
55 we have a strong girdle distribution
northwest southeast current distribution
in magnetite
and in amphibole we can also see this
strong
distribution in the magnetic fabrics
but also in all three petal fabrics so
the amphibole and magnetized shape
and the magnetic distribution fabric
in cb61 we have a
strong northwest
southeast current distribution in the
maintenance shape
while the amphibole shape
and magnetic distribution have a
east-west moderately
southward different kernel distribution
and essentially demand the fabrics are
oriented intermediate in between the
magnetized shape
and the amphibole shape and magnetic
distribution fabric
so it seems that we have a magnetic
fabrics being a mix of the two
so if we compare these two three or four
and put them into and show the fabric
parameters so the t
fabric shape parameter which shows the
shape
so one is an old blade fabric so pancake
type fabric
and minus one is a prolly so cigar shape
fabric and we can see here that
the mass fabric is prolate
while the magnetic petrol fabrics of the
distribution fabric and shape fabric are
old bait and the amphibole shape fabric
is
prolate uh so this is something causing
the
the the ams fabric to become prolate
and if this might be that we have an
intersection between
uh delineation fabrics or the
magnetite distribution and the magnetic
shape at this point
causing it to become a prolific fabric
um yeah the similar is similar in
cb46 we have a strong old blade fabric
in the magnetite shape and magnetic
distribution
while the magnetic fabric has a little
bit of a weaker
oblate fabric which might be due to the
amphibole
or it's maybe due to an intersection
basically causing uh
maybe that these fabrics are interfering
with each other
basically lowering the degree of an
isotropy and the shape
of the fabric
in cb55 where everything seems to
coincide being coaxial
then we have quite a good correspondence
between
between the mass fabric and the shape
fabric
here of magnetite why we have a little
bit lower
distribution fabric which we can't
really explain
and then in cb 61 we have a
quite strong uh oblate
fabric for all the magnetic fabrics
while the three petrol fabrics have a
little bit
uh less strong oblate shape
and this it might be due to this kind of
mixed fabric
interacting each other and making the
monetary fabric
a little bit stronger if you look at
cb19 we
have the inverse fabrics
relative to the to the magnetite shape
and anti-bullshit
and the mindset distribution and
isotropy
it might be that these petrol fabrics
are basically interfering with each
other
which lowers the anisotropy of
uh the rock or the sample
and makes some for example a single
domain magnetite more domain than
and controlling the ams fabric so to
look at the single domain
contribution or higher cursivity
phases distribute contribution to the ms
fabrics i did
a partial arm using a
a different af alternating field range
and we can see then that
k2 or the r1 or the k k1 and k2
of the the aarm are oriented in this
uh north west south east
girdle essentially showing that
the high coercivity grains have a
preferably orientation in the in the
north in northwestern hemisphere
or the northeast and western hemisphere
and this might contribute to
to to the inversion of the fabric
i'm there twice yep yes so
you have to summarize we have the three
components of the petrol fabric
that contribute to the petrol fabric and
they either interfere constructively
making the fabric stronger so they have
a stronger
degree of anisotropy or destructively
and making the fabric
weaker and this generates the
ams fabric but what's also interesting
is it's that the distribution is
anisotropic also seems to affect the
uh an anisotropy of damage magnetization
so uh essentially the spatial
distribution magnetite also seems to
have some effect on the spatial
distribution
or on the uh the ram magnetization which
i think so far has not really been shown
yeah so thank you for me
so uh do we have any questions
uh yeah can i ask a question
uh yeah very nice talk can i can i think
about how you
calculate the distribution anatomy from
your
tomography data i saw at one point you
showed an equation
yeah that sort of that quantified the
the the da
and it's a function primarily
just the distance between particles
but do you not want to take into account
or in a in a spherical
cluster or whatever i mean how how do
you actually
do that yes i i only heard like half of
your question
because you cut off okay sorry
it's about how you calculate the the
distribution anisotropy from there
from the tomography uh because it seemed
that the equation you showed
was just a function of distance but but
surely the the spatial
arrangement also comes into it in some
way
yeah so uh this this equation is the
it's the the main one that people have
used
just to calculate distribution and
entropy so it's basically you choose the
uh descent the point descent point
between crystal
you take all the crystals that you have
in your data set
but then you weigh them depending on the
the distance between them
and the volume of the because each
crystal
there have been a new uh a new equation
just published i think
a couple of weeks ago by andrea
biedemann
and we haven't really looked into this
but this is the this is the main
definition that people have used
but i i agree that there might be some
some other kind of
a spatial thing that you we need to
consider as well
okay do we have any other questions
uh yeah well let's also just echo what
rich said it was really nice talk
um i was uh curious
why did microc ct because the resolution
is quite
coarse is 16 micro tests
sorry 16 microns um i was just wondering
if you thought about trying ebsd
obviously that's not three-dimensional
to me two-dimensional but then you can
you can map out automatically quite
large areas at a much higher resolution
yeah right so when we started this study
we basically wanted to
have the same sub-specimen and that we
did the ams on
and run it completely to the the ct
scanner
so we basically have a we get the 3d
resolution exactly from the same core as
we did ams
and uh yeah so we wanted to start with
this but
i definitely want to look further in the
future maybe
cutting up these cores and and and and
getting more
into detail with the single domain and
smaller crystals as well
okay i i had another question
many years ago when williams and i
published a paper on
distribution anazotropy and we did a
micromagnetic approach and to
to get it to work we couldn't model
alternating fields so we did
an asexual of srm yeah in a distribution
looking interacting particles and mike
jackson said that
an isotropy of uh high field signals you
can't really resolve
properly something to do with
calculating the eigenvectors and i never
really understood
what he meant and i could never find a
reference to what he said maybe i should
have just asked him
i mean i was just wondering are we so
you're doing this anadropy of irm i mean
some of the results are really sometimes
really quite different to the anazotropy
of arm or or the ams i mean
[Music]
do you have any thoughts on the on the
dangers of using anazotropy of irm
uh yeah i i mean not
not not really because the reason that i
did this was because
or anesthetic magnetizer broke
so i just tried try this and
but it seems like because i could i
could get this very low cursivity range
with this
right and i would presumably get a high
coercivity range with the
aarm so it seems like
if i it seems like that
the fabric is basically controlled by
this very low
the low cursive the crystal or crystal
grains
and this is basically what i think i got
out from the air
i don't have a better explanation or
answer okay right so