yes um yeah so uh i
looked at a lot of samples in the
devonian and the devonian has always
been a very problematic time for
paleomagnetism
um and so this has affected basically
everything in the devonian
the time scales so the polarity pattern
is not very well known
there's bits that are gray and but also
paleo poles have been affected and
there's
um well the amount of paint intensities
is increasing
um and so we wanted to basically uh have
a look
at the uh the polarity patterns so we
selected
three sections in germany canada
uh and poland and we tried to do
magnetosphere on them
they showed little evidence for
remineralization
or significant heating so the chances of
primary directions in these sections
were very good
but we showed that basically there's
still a lot of trouble
all the samples are very weak they
so that excludes the possibility of a
lot of
rock magnetic techniques so we were
basically limited to copper bridge runs
um
and even though the samples
were likely not overprinted because they
had no overprint conditions met
we do see big overprints so we see
everywhere
present-day field overprint and also a
caiman direction so that is the burmo
carbonyl first reverse supercron
and then we basically see three types of
behavior
um so for the section from germany
we see something that might be a
devonian primary direction but we only
have
one polarity and we don't have any field
test because the section is
flat lying for the section in poland we
see both polarities
and for the section in canada we
basically see random directions
and then we looked at all the other
devonian data so we looked at the
magnetostratigraphy
so this is part of the pattern in the
frennie and fermenian
which is based on random data um we had
a look at
a lot of paleo pool paper so i looked at
more than 80 papers
and what we see is basically that the
field in the devonian
looks very strange uh there is
basically no good convincing data
um and we also see very weak paleo
intensities so
we are now thinking that perhaps uh the
field was very weak and in a very poor
shape
and we're asking the question whether uh
there is a link to all these biotic
crises in the devonian
and we're making a call out to everyone
to publish the veronium data because i
think that there might be a lot more
there might be a lot more attempts that
people did but they haven't managed to
publish it because the data was just so
weird
or of poor quality
so yeah please publish your data because
that's the only way that we can
understand the field in the devonian and
i'll be happy to
discuss this at some other points with
anyone
thank you very much who
is is anyone else wanting to present
i could hop on if no one wants to go
uh i think hannah just oh yeah
no hannah you go yeah you know you spoke
up
you sure okay um let me just get
my okay you should be able to see
a poster is that right yeah we can
i can't see what you're seeing so um
yeah
hello i'm hannah and my poster is on the
application of spherical sloping
functions to the inversion of virtual
observatory satellite magnetic data
into localized regions of flow on the
core mantle boundary
so our research is motivated by
improving the international geomagnetic
reference field model
the idrf is updated every five years but
due to our poor understanding of how the
core flow is
changing the 2015 to forecast error was
much larger than we expected
we want to improve forecasts of magnetic
field change by better understanding
individual regions of flow on the core
mantle boundary
study of these regions are motivated by
four main points
the assumptions required when inverting
from field to flow which define the flow
uniquely over part
only part of the corsair core surface
such as the tangentially geostrophic
flow model
flow assumption number two uh
we want to investigate different fluid
motions in different regions of the core
such as
the column above and below the inner
core
three there's sometimes spatially uneven
data collection
and four investigating how features on
the base of the mantle
affects flow and the core mantles on the
outer core surface
so from seismic anomalies and thermal
anomalies
so i've been working with kathy whaler
and kieran beggan
to apply a mathematical technique called
slapping functions
to core flows on the core mantle
boundary the slap-in functions have
previously been used extensively in
geodesy gravity and crustal magnetic
field models as the functions allow a
spatio-spectral trade-off
in order to constrain spherical
harmonics within a region of interest
on the sphere my poster is focused on
the impact of
these large low shear velocity
preferences
um on the base of the mantle which are a
seismic anomaly
and also kind of trying to demonstrate
the current limitations that we have
when uh using the spherical slapping
functions
um we've been incorporating slap in
into our inversions of virtual
observatory magnetic data sets
so that we can directly invert into a
region
as opposed to constraining the flow
after an inversion has taken place
our flow models when using slapping
functions show an improvement
in the presentation in the preservation
of small features
and we've reduced the speeds outside of
the
lsvp patches kind of like here
um but there's still quite a lot of um
flow outside these regions
um moving forward we've got quite a lot
of
plans so we want to keep investigating
different regions
and remove upward continuation as part
of
our inversions and maybe use altitude
cognizance slap in functions instead
which would allow our
functions to be dependent on the
downward continuation and not a step
that we have to kind of work around
but i can explain that more in person um
so thanks a lot feel free to come and
talk to me about slap in functions
the impact of lsvps on core flow
uh inversions virtual observatories or
just to say hi
thanks thank you
well you know what i you know just come
by see my poster i can i can just talk
about it real quickly uh
well at liverpool we've been working on
updating the
paleo intensity pint database a real big
push
and in particular um trying to add the
the qpi
aspect and try to fill in as much as we
can of the pint data set
and so this is a bit of a teaser of that
but
yeah we can yep so um
so my poster is on the paleo intensity
results um
i've gotten as part of a collaboration
between
liverpool and curtin university um from
the 2.6 billion year old rocks
uh from the yilgaan craton um they've
previously been
looked up for directions can i get rid
of you
um by one of the phd students over there
and they
showed that despite the fact that
there's been several generations of dyke
swarms in the area
you do actually appear to have the chrm
component at quite high temperatures
from about like
530 to 565 degrees
and the magnetic mineralogy of the
samples looks really good
um capper bridge and vfdb thermomag
for a lot of the samples i've been
looking at they show you know really
clearly
magnetic curie temperatures um
very fine grains because of the
exhalation
of the magnetite and ilmanite yeah
pretty fine grain based on the
day plot um so i
did paleo intensity on what i could both
thermal uh a microwave teleo type as
well as
shore method and i did do ltd
shaw and thermal tele-a
with the easy protocol but none of the
ltd stuff
passed it seemed to give really terrible
pass rates and none of it could really
be accepted
um but you've got some nice generally i
mean two-slope but
very clearly linked to the overprint in
most cases
and also um the chrm intensity still
represents a decent amount of the
overall intensity of the samples
and yeah um only five sites um
we were able to get passable
measurements but that's still quite
reasonable
um so i know richard earlier was asking
about
um the icn pattern and
uh what it should look like and
um well the oh bear of a tell
2009 the thing that we kind of all talk
about with
um the weakening field leading up to icy
at inner core nucleation
at either sometime between like 1.5 to
1.3 billion years or
1.1 billion years or even 500 ma um
if you're expecting really quite strong
paleo intensity measurements
um sort of around 2.6 ga based on this
they are definitely sort of quite low
compared to what you'd expect
and also um quite low compared to the
wiki mother dykes
the sort of closest in time and location
around 2.4
billion years um but yes so
there has been more recent research
which suggests that actually we wouldn't
see
um a spike in a core nucleation orlando
hotel
2017 paper um so i guess with the low
results you could argue
well you need a lot better coverage of
the precambrian
but maybe we are seeing more variation
and the 2000 and the
weakening field trend is just an
underlying trend that we're also seeing
variation on top of
or maybe we're just kind of putting on a
trend i don't know
um but yeah you can come see my poster i
think i've just explained all of it
sorry
and how do i stop the screen share
thank you very much louise uh dan
you want to go
um let me see
if that works
can you see my pdf yeah we can
okay that worked so this is my yearly
project update
that i do every year at magnetic
interactions i
am looking at paleo intensities in the
edo current period
because in in this period we had some
anomalous directional results and it's
also quite interesting because
because it should be around the area of
it could be around the area of inner
corner creation
so what we did is we did a multi method
in density study well more of them
actually and but now we have about
even over a thousand intensity specimens
that have been measured
with over half of them come from
microwave
and and thermal italian methods and the
rest
is double heating showers to italia or
from wozen experiments
we have success rates that different
depending on on
site and method between zero and
25 and the ones that do pass
pretty much all look look the same we
get our two slope
behavior and have to be quite careful to
differentiate between
too slow behavior and sucking arrived
plots but it is
quite helpful that we do get directional
changes
at the same point where there's a bend
between
between the two slopes and
basically look the same for for thermal
telly
and microwave telly and the results
here the ones that i'm showing are all
lower than than two micro teslas and
microwave and thermal results do agree
pretty well there
if we look at at shaw we can't really
see a
two slope behavior well you can if you
use your imagination and the same for
pseudo delia
but if we compare what we get from from
the three
methods then then they all agree pretty
well
and usually the lowest results come from
from the pseudo-italian method so if we
look at
the vdms at this time period we can see
that all of them are
really really low we have an in orange
here
rigid bonus uh single crystal result
and pretty much all of what we've been
measuring between
600 and 560 ma has been
has been agreeing pretty well with with
that and it basically looks like it's
it's getting even
weaker as it gets older and we get
a bit of different results around 550
so we get higher brilliant densities
here and if we say higher
i'm talking about like 10 micro tesla so
for context the present day field
strength
in this plot would be up here somewhere
and if you look at all of the
intensities the low
and the high ones and compare those two
to younger distributions of dipole
moments then we can see they are
really different from anything we can
see after that
even the hyperactivity periods
do not even close give us intensities
that
that low as we see and in the idiocarin
so what we also did is is look at
directional circular variation and when
we started to do that
it really gave us results that looked
pretty similar
to what we would get from from psv10
apart from the
from the error bars that we see but i've
done a bit more on
that by now and have been a i've been
getting a bit stricter with my criteria
of what to use and what not to use
and i don't have a final result yet but
it looks like
it will give us a model a that is a bit
higher than what we see here
and a b value that is quite a bit lower
than what we got here and
yeah at this point i can give you the
the same conclusion that i've been
giving you
every year namely that the the field was
pretty weird back then
and also very weak but
now we can also say that it looks like
it has been weak over an
extended period of time maybe 40 million
years and maybe even longer
it doesn't and that it seems to change
at the
ethio karen cambrian transition and it
seems to
get stronger there and i think that's
pretty much
all i can say here just come by and
then we can have a chat about details
thank you
thank you very much uh is there another
one
becky let's just put us up please
so i'm now going to take you guys all
the way to antarctica
welcome to the amundsen sea uh so here
is an area of interest more recently and
you may have heard about this in the
news
about weights glacier and its concern
for sort of rise and sea levels and so
this was an iodp expedition that took
place in
january 2019 and i did not say on this
cruise i'll be
up front and but i'm working on you
channels that were collected from
site u1533 which is shown here in the
star
um and so we have fif i've been working
on the pleistocene section
from this cruise to sort of work out
what's been happening recently
and so my main aims are sort of to
refine
the magnesium stratigraphic framework
that was sort of collected
on the ship and try and produce an rpi
record because as we sort of
look in the southern ocean there aren't
very many paleo intensity records from
new channels and sediment cores
that sort of exist and if they do exist
they're quite short
and so trying to work out whether this
is possible here it's like you
1533 and then to look at
the environmental magnetism of this site
and
all this together should be able to tell
us sort of a bit more about what was the
paleo climate like
at fight us 1533 sort of during the
pleistocene
so my results so far are pretty good
and we've refined the magnetographic
framework
and we have all the major polarity
reversals
so for the last two and a half million
years and and
on my poster you'll see sort of that
there's uh highlighted
excursions that have been picked
depicted from a
deconvolution of the record that i've
got
and i've also got a really good sort of
start
to the relative paleo intensity record
so this is sort of highlighted here in
this figure and
so this is my paleo intensity and it
shows really good correlation
to the piso 1500 stack which is a
reference stack
that sort of is sort of from 12 chords
from across the world that's correlated
to
and the oxygen 18 record so this is this
dark
green line on this graph yeah but
unfortunately
so it's only 1.5 million years long
and my record extends further than that
so this
stack here is an equatorial pacific
stack
which as you can see from my gray bars
which correlate
down to the paleo intensity they sort of
vanish after this point
and this could be either because the
pacific stack that i've chosen to use
isn't a good one so i need to find a
better stack to compare to
and or it could be some change in
behavior sort of later on here
so these orange bars are major polarity
reversals that
are shown better on the full poster
and so here is the bruins cron this is
the gauss matiama boundary
and so there may be some sort of change
here
and i should point out this gap in the
record is a u channel that was not
sampled
with the rest of the new channels and
but we will should receive that later on
uh sort of to fill in that gap and work
out what's happening in that space as
well
and so beyond that for future work uh
i'm gonna
validate those excursions that i
mentioned to sort of work out
whether they're true whether they're to
do with changes in magnetic grain size
or mineralogy
and sort of deeper look into the core
descriptions to see whether there's a
physical
visible reason for those excursions and
and then if they are
true excursions there are quite a lot of
them in the bruins crown which can help
tie down the age model better
for the younger section of this record
and then i'm going to
plan to do sort of rock rock magnetic
experiments too to sort of
fill it off fill up sort of the rest of
the
information to work out what is
recording everything
and then see sort of how does that
change environmentally in the anderson
sea
yeah come to my poster and hopefully i
will do better there
thank you very much i think there's one
more
from ben
yeah i'm just trying to show you
okay
cool yeah so in this we've been looking
at um
paleocircular variation off to the pcrs
and so compile the triassic
direction bgp database and incorporate
this into a longer time interval which
we're calling the pctrx and
most other things um we found behavior
in this time to be
very similar to that observed in the pre
cns which includes drastic high
productivity
so there's a bit of background uh psb is
commonly studied as vgp scatter
and this relationship's often expressed
formal g which is defined by
coefficients a and b which given it in
this
equation um on several studies
of um listening to intervals since the
beginning of the pcrs
however most of the trials is not
included in the east
and so these studies looking at normally
a relationship between psp behavior and
average reversal frequency
whether quantifying psv with va ratio
from model g
um however like the nature of this
relationship is still unclear and so
this study is looking at what maybe
traffic psp behavior may be able to
tell us about this relationship and also
making use of a new idea that model ga
promiser may be able to provide
information regarding morphology of the
geomagnetic field
so as well as compiling pulse pcrs
database or compiled the new pcrs
database
just to allow for a direct comparison as
now uh both intervals will satisfy the
same selection criteria
we estimated a vgp scatter and the model
g coefficients for each time interval
and look to how the data selected
influence the observed dispersions so we
investigate
effects of serial correlation and
excluding direct data derived from great
circles
and on top of this we use some
additional selection criteria
to generate higher quality database and
then check the robustness of the
dispersions that we see
and finally our results were compared
with those from other published data
compilations
representing intervals since the pcrs
and so uh in the results what we see
is a little evidence of a relationship
between vgp scatter and light choose
given in figure one and then yeah in
figure two we can see that the the pcrs
showed a strong
increase in scatter with latitude we've
got agreement with the model g fit
and incorporating the things like serial
correlation and great circle data had
little effect
so they weren't really taken into
consideration in the end and then
um yeah this was also true when using
the higher quality data so the overall
dispersion was pretty much the same
suggesting the dispersions to be robust
features of each time interval
and then when compared with other time
intervals since the pulse pcrs
we see the vgp dispersions very similar
to that observed
in the pre-cns this is demonstrated by
the the similarity in the model g shape
parameters
and in figure 3 you can see the nearly
identical ba ratios
and this type of behavior this
latitudinal invariance is traditionally
thought to represent times of high
reversal frequency
such as the drastic hyperactivity and
the pre-cns but here we see there's very
consistent behavior
at the time interval between the two
super crowns despite quite a large
variation
in a point reversal frequency so part
suggesting that uh
any relationship between the vessel
frequency and psp more complex
um maybe future studies should uh treat
this as one time interval
and then also like in the the recent
paper from bigger than others at the
back end last year where
we find share promises don't do not
necessarily call vary and so as a result
maybe the traditional interpretation
appears to be outdated
so from this study as long as possible
the super crowns occur when a is lower
and so actual dipole dominance is
greater
which is the field morphology was talked
about earlier and um
however the cns is only slightly but not
statistically distinct from time of
reversals which from this would make it
difficult to
to say for certain and then if you were
to look for like a new meaning behind
model g
b parameter perhaps then that could be
related to field intensity or average
vdm
where you see the lower values um in
between the two super crons could maybe
roughly agree with an extended metastory
dipole however we need a lot more paleo
intensity data to look into that
and then finally it would seem that the
pcrs is a unique time interval
um or at least the last 300 million
years or so regarding psp behavior
uh estimates of the model g promoters
are very different and statistically
distinct from terms of reversals
and using the polar associated with
model g a promo
was just a time of like unique um axial
dipole dominance
so maybe this could be responsible for
its extended duration compared to the
cns or
maybe an artifact for the long length of
the super chrome
so yeah if anyone's interested come and
find me