uh thank you for
coming to the talk so i'm just going to
talk about
bio magnetic monitoring and
why do we need a different different
proxy
to monitor air pollution so this this um
this graphic over here basically
explains that right
you know the traditional methods used to
monitor air pollution
um uses very spherical
unified diam you know
part particles where they take into
account particulate matter
in terms of their diameters which is
basically
either pm10 which is
all the particulate matter which is
less than 10 microns then we have pm 2.5
measurements which you
might have seen which are every every
other particle which is
less than pm uh which is less than 2.5
micrometers
and then comes the more ultra fine
particles
which um my research would basically
focus on
is is which goes neglected when we are
monitoring air pollution using
traditional methods we would only hear
about
particulate matter in terms of 2.5 or 10
measurements um so what why do we need
uh what's the big picture
that right now there the concentration
of anthropogenic particulate matter
is increasing and it's an increasing
risk
to public health and with with
increasing urbanization and
um people you know the cities developing
even though there have been stricter
stringent policies to
curb air pollution they're still there
still more exposure to
air pollution than it was before and
this would increase year on year
so the traditional air pollution
monitoring monitoring systems do not
give a full picture
of the pollutants present they do tell
us about
the amount of particulate matter um in
terms of
um in terms of their mass uh per unit
volume
uh but that is something which could go
more higher resolution and that is where
we come in um using magnetic and uh
you know microscopy techniques we can
[Music]
you know find pick up these ultra fine
magnetic particles which go unnoticed
and biomagnetic monitoring is one of
those things where
we can use trees and leaves to find us
find tell more about the source of
particulate matter
and the aim is to basically mitigate air
pollution
um you know using specific tree species
where some tree species are better at
accumulating particulate matter than
other species
and obviously the height comes as a
factor because after a certain height
there could be a vortex
created where instead of mitigating air
pollution
the trees actually inhibit
more inhibit air circulation which can
increase
local concentrations at a particular
road or
a building so why biomagnetic monitoring
because it can
be used as an estimator of ambient pm
concentration
it is a good interface for both dry or
red
deposition but deposition is in terms of
rain
could be snow could be anything it could
be
suitable for spatial studies and
can also you know provide a way to
you know exhibit magnetic different
magnetic parameters across different
cities
where some cities might have more
vehicular related pollution while some
might have more industrial related
um the aims are to
find a find out about the nature of
magnetic carriers
in air pollution at the nanoscale also
develop
and interpret more like the magnetic
proxies of this air pollution
uh go to cities uh where air pollution
is a
bigger problem and where we can quantify
it and then
kind of use it in uh you know cities in
the europe
so lahore is one of the cities we might
be focusing on
um and then basically
the the final kind of aim is to actually
mitigate air pollution
using the data we might have
we might get from from these monitoring
techniques
so this is um basically not my data this
is from a paper
it just gives an idea of what is
actually present
and what particles might give us a
magnetic
signal and how how different are the
morphologies under
different microscopy uh tools so
these pictures are taken um from
uh from a paper from delgado at all
and this study was done in italy and it
basically
shows different kind of particles
present
a good one which is also magnetic is
ferrite over here
it's an iron oxide and it's usually
associated with
vehicle parts abrasion and stuff like
that
some more different particles
over here you can see how some
industrial related
particles are have a very distinct
uhedrill
grain over here some of them might also
be
magnetic that is what we're here to find
out
so this is some some air filter samples
i had where
i just had one day on the sem because
that is what i could get
and this is a typical sem image of
what you might have in a in a town or a
city and you can see that
how these grains have this bright
sub micron or nano scale particle that
could be magnetic
in in nature you could see some of these
over here as well
and um
another slide which is from
a different paper it's basically
applying tm
to particulate to look at particulate
matter and this is
how you can see the scale over here is
on nanometers
so we can see how important are these
you know these ultra fine particles
super which
would have a super paramagnetic you know
signal as well attached to it
and this is what we would focus on these
are not my pictures
but this is something so there is a case
study i am going to talk about which is
actually
the work i did over the past few months
and
it is from padua italy and
the location was their
department of chemical sciences so fifth
floor they had this extractor
attached to the building where they
sucked air into the sampling room and
that's where the sampling
took place i got hold of these from
the department of chemistry at cambridge
and the background motivation is
basically to relate the chemical data
to magnetic and microscopy analysis
uh key questions we were trying to
answer were what fraction of particulate
matter
is magnetic and how
are they related to certain pollutant
sources and whether
there are any magnetic minerals on a
nanoscale
so different methods we used um
hysteresis loops
forks done on on an atm
and microscopy is to be
still done so i'm just going to present
some magnetic
measurements we face some challenges so
because
there is very little um
you know material present on
on the air filters we it had a very weak
remnants and there was a
we noticed there was a background
remnants coming just from the blank
uh probe so what we there was also
difficulty in optimizing the
sample mounted on the atm so we came up
with a measurement protocol where we
measured the blank filter
blank mount with the grease on and then
we corrected you know our um
our our actual measurement by
subtracting those averages of the blank
samples to ensure
the sample signal was accurately
presented so here
you can see that these are the blank
measurements and you can see it's not
purely dye magnetic there was some
remnants over there
and this is what could have you know
contaminated our data so we subtracted
this from our
measurements over here and we slow
corrected our hysteresis
which is present over presented over
here so these are the winter samples
on the left the summer ones on the right
you can see the winters one
winter ones have a higher total magnetic
moment which is what we would expect
because usually winters are usually
higher more polluted
so um these are the averages of all the
winter samples like 15 samples
and all the summer samples and
what we can see is basically is that
you can see that there's a there's a
super paramagnetic
uh signal over there and that there's a
sd
it's extending into a single domain a
stable bridge
and you can see there is a course uh
pseudo single domain to multi-domain
background signal
in these winter forks uh so the summer
ones
you could it wasn't it's not well
defined because the measurements are
still going on
um so it's a bit noisier over here but
it still has some super
paramagnetic um signal
which is present and a more pronounced
psd signal
in the summer ones so these are just uh
some
to uh some sample uh an individual
sample where i just want to mention how
the and the derivative of the dcd curve
shows us that
it goes beyond the coercivity
distribution goes beyond
300 milli tesla so probably highlighting
as something else present other than
magnetite
this is the summer one you can see at
around 300 we can see
the coercivity distribution so presence
of magnetite probably
so the coercivities for both of the
samples
were very narrow between five to eight
milli tesla
so typically of a soft magnetic fraction
such as magnetite
and this is a day plot basically
uh trying uh basically showing that it's
lying within the psd to md range and
ultra fine you know super paramagnetic
contributions
at this part you know could be present
in the
winter samples so these
are the total uh this is a kind of a box
and whisker for
the total magnetization for each of the
samples
and you can see that even though the
winter ones are a bit higher
the the median isn't very much different
from the summer
sample there was no correlation found
between the total magnetic moment and
the mass of
pm this is for the winter samples
so we failed to reject the null
hypothesis that
their the magnetic movement is related
to the mass
so what are the challenges we might have
um
different bio magnetic proxies have
different signatures
and we might have to calibrate that for
different species we need to
correlate the magnetic signals to pm
concentrations and
they might not be true from cities to
cities
this is a leaf sampling campaign which
we are planning to do in lahore pakistan
so it's basically picking up some leaf
samples and
at different heights and a different
length of the road and then
kind of taking their sirm measurements
and their sar
measurements to it as one of the proxies
to tell how magnetically
they're different and also microscopy on
these samples to tell
us about the different morphologies of
particles present
i would like to thank my supervisor rich
harrison for
for helping me with some of the stuff in
this
and thank you for listening
well done that's a nice talk it's quite
an interesting uh
twist on things at the end of our
session so uh thank you very much
um does uh anyone have questions so uh
adrian
you use your hand up there first i
believe
uh yeah it's more of a comment so a lot
of the questions
that were being raised and asked i mean
there was a
20 years ago there was a eu funded
program called magna it was
there was about 10 post stocks all over
europe working on this and
many of them did a combined biomagnetic
uh study looking at the pollution all
these different cities and looking at
different
type different types of trees and stuff
so
a lot of the questions you're asking
seem to have
been sort of looked at already so i
just think there might be a case for
going back and looking at literature
there's a lot of work done 20 years ago
on this sort of thing so
um you know you the way that the way it
was phrased it felt like a bit like a
lot of these things were new
but it didn't come across as
particularly new and
i guess my question is i mean if you've
got all these very
low temperature particles
sorry small ssp particles i mean have
you thought about doing your low
temperature measurements because if
you've got particles which are
30 or 20 nanometers you're not going to
see them
doing room temperature measurements you
need to really have you thought about
doing your low temperature
so that is that is one of the thank you
yeah and uh thank you adrian the
we we i have looked at literature and
i've seen
most of this stuff is done so what i'm
trying to do is build up upon
what is already present so um the
questions i'm trying to answer
are gonna look more on the on the ultra
fine or the nano scale bit of it so that
is something which
that those studies didn't look at and uh
doing low temperature measurements is
something which is uh
excuse me i don't think that's true
actually i mean i i did moss bar at low
temperature
and we looked at particles with less
than 10 nanometers so
to say that is to say that it's not
being done is is just
wrong sorry i mean obviously there's a
lot more work to be done but
i mean there has been work done
sorry i would just say i would want to
build
the work which is already done okay
yeah thanks that question i think i
think it's a fair enough comment that
you wish to be constructive and build
upon the work that's been already done
that's fair enough i think
uh professor williams would you like to
pitch in with a question or comment
there
um yeah it was similar to agent so you
know my memory is
getting worse by the day but uh i'd
remember that agent had done some work
in the past and also barbara mayer
but i mean i think what you've done was
quite interesting son and um
from my very poor memory of previous
work it did concentrate on particular
types of material i think particularly
uh
leaves and trees and i remember some
studies talking about how far
back the trees were the lines of trees
from the roads and which way the wind
was blowing and all that sort of stuff
but from your work it looks like you've
looked at a much wider range of uh
material you talked about mosses and
other material
so but but you haven't yet been able to
look at
any uh trends with any on these
particular material
that accumulate on any different type of
organic matter is that right
that's something you're hoping to do
thank you thank you for the question so
the mention of mosses and legends are
that's kind of a bathroom review on
what's been done
i it's just been two months since i
started this project so i've not had to
have enough time to work um to to
you know uh present what i've actually
done so what i've actually done
right now is basically kind of a
background study
on how um how we can use the
the magnetic proxies to kind of quantify
particulate matter so it's it's it's
something which is
still in development and i'm not
disagreeing that
something like this hasn't been done
it's just it's a preliminary work i've
done
for two three months so there isn't any
any personal work i've done on mosses or
religions that's that's something from
the literature
two or three months work that looks
pretty good to me okay
thanks very much