um our our next talk is going to be
uh from simon on the first
intensity data from neoproterozoid
implications
hi okay can everyone hear me
yeah i hope so
okay can anyone hear me yes there's no
problem
[Music]
yeah okay thanks so hi i'm simon lloyd
from the university of liverpool
and i'm presenting the first paleo
intensity data to come from the
cryogenian
and discussing their potential
implications for inner core nucleation
age
and so the aim of the study was to help
reduce the large uncertainty in the
estimates
for inner core nucleation age and we
want to do
this because not only is the formation
of the inner core
a significant event in earth history but
also knowledge of when it occurred
providing valuable constraints on models
which
aim to solve other deep earth problems
and so we can do this with paleo
intensity we believe because the
formation of the inner core brought
about two new power sources
to help drive the geodynamo
compositional convection
and the subsequent release of latent
heat and so we'd expect to see an
increase in
intensity observations at earth's
surface
and or a change in the time average
morphology of the field
and so if we look at models the most
recent models to
predict age estimates we've got
observational based models
such as those on the left and geodynamo
models on the right
and we can see that the age estimates
here span more than 500 million years
but that they all fall in or around the
neoproterozoic era
and so far it's been difficult to link
paleomagnetic observational data
and the outputs from geodynamo
simulations however this has been a key
aim of the deep group
at liverpool over the last few years and
there's some exciting new papers to come
out of this research
an important caveat though is that
despite significant advances in
geodynamo simulations
estimates remain based on uncertain
parameters such as thermal conductivity
and so this is why paleo intensity
observations are vital as a constraint
on these models and so if we look at the
neoproterozoic in more detail
this cartoon represents geological
history
from 4.6 billion years ago clockwise to
the present day
and we've highlighted the neoproterozoic
and if we now populate this with
all the current paleo intensity data we
have
we see that there's just four single
data points in almost 500 years
million years of earth history and for
context these have been
plotted in relation to the present air
field
where the surface of the earth there
would be no feel at all
but the takeaway message from this is
that the most recent age estimates
coincide
with the severe porosity of data in the
neoproterozoic
and so that's what this study aims to
help with
by looking at rocks from high up to
canada and greenland
so if we zoom in on that area
we've been looking at rocks from the
franklin large igneous province
an event which took place around 720
million years ago
and covered a vast area almost well over
two million
square kilometers including dikes sills
volcanics and intrusives however we're
focused mainly on
dikes from elsmere island devon island
and greenland
and this is based off previous work by
denis natal in 2009
who sampled almost 30 dollar eight dikes
and two sills
and they obtained uranium lead aegis
from the same rocks as they acquired
primary remnants from
and the directions of the franklin event
are well defined across an expansive
area
they include reverse polarity directions
and a positive bait contact test
and so this is all important
prerequisites to pay
intensity reliability and this study
focuses on 16 dollar 8 dikes and 1 sill
and we obtained 120 of the original
1-inch
samples which we then cut in half to
produce 240 half inch samples
so we started off by measuring the rock
magnetic properties of representative
samples from each of the sites
we measured hysteresis loops high
temperature susceptibility
magnetization saturation and isothermal
remnant magnetization
and we also did a viscous remnant
magnetization experiment
in which we oriented the samples in
different positions in the earth's field
and from that we were able to measure
the viscous component
and then we separated our sites
according to highly low viscous
component
we also did some limited scanning
electron microscopy
and here if we look at the top two
images we see
very fine low titanium titanium
magnetite grains which appear pristine
compared to the bottom two images where
we see much larger grains
with illuminate and low titanomagnetite
with evidence of alteration
and so if we look at the rock magnetic
results in the top left we have a day
plot where we can see that most of the
sites
fall in the psd or vortex above the main
state
region and next to that we see
our mst curves which we separated
according to
reversibility at room temperature
however these tell us that
we have a single curry temperature
ranging from 550 to 590 degrees celsius
which we interpret as low titanium
titanomagnetite
and we see a range of reversibility in
the kt curves
so the top row of kt curves are the more
reversible
and the bottom row are less reversible
and we also
see evidence of low temperature
inflections at around 300 degrees c
and so we took a multi-technique
approach to gathering paleo intensity
results we used three methods the
thermal talia method
the microwave method and the sure double
heating technique with and without
low temperature demagnetization and the
success rates are next to the methods
there and we see that the thermal
italian method didn't do so well
predominantly due to failure of ptrm
checks due to alteration
and so the big feature from our results
is that the
field was extremely weak at this time
almost an order of magnitude weaker than
today
and so we got we used we got results
from three methods
almost 40 results from 11 sites
however four of the sites had less than
three years so we don't use these
in our calculation of virtual dipole
moments
you also note we get a low sight mean
standard deviation in absolute terms of
less than three microteslas
and if we look at some of the array
plots
here each column represents a different
method
and each row is that is represents
uh the same site so in this way we're
able to compare
sister specimens across method and we
can see that we get consistent results
in absolute terms
within and between sites and from all
three methods
for example the bottom row site bp
we get 5.3 microteslas 6.7
and 7.4 each from a different method
and we can also see that there are some
two slope array plots
present however a change in slope
usually corresponds to a change in
direction
and that's most notable in the top
middle
array plot
so we also compare our rock magnetic
results on our paleo intensity results
and we found these in good agreement
because
all sites which show high viscous
components we get no paleo intensity
results for
and the less reversible kt caves and or
low temperature inflections we also get
no paleo intensity results for
and so the successful paleo intensity
results are associated with
sites displaying the highest quality
rock magnetic properties
we also look at the potential for
any bias from multi-domain effects and
we do this because of the two slope
array plots and also
the psd domain
state properties and so we do this by
comparing sure low temperature
demagnetization results with those that
did not
undergo any ltd and that's because ltd
is said to remove
preferentially remove md-like remnants
so if we look at the plot
in the bottom left we've got sister
samples from six different sites where
the
blue columns are the ltd and the orange
columns are no ltd
and we see that the results are almost
equivalent so this suggests that we
don't have any bias from md
effects we also
looked at the two slope array plots uh
particularly where a change in direction
was less obvious
and we changed the best line fit
considerably and we found that a large
change in slope
actually corresponds to a very small
absolute change in
intensity so if there is any effect from
md we think it's minimal
we also scored our results using the qpi
system
from biggin and patterson 2014 and our
site score between five and nine
and so if we look at our results and
compare them with
uh current global data our results are
in
are the uh green squares and we've
selected data here with a qpi score of
three or more
and an n of three or more and some
observations we can make from this
uh but firstly it's important to note
the precambrian studies may not be
representative of the very long term
average
because they may capture a temporarily
or spatially limited anomaly
however we've produced seven vdms
from four to nineteen zero meters
squared
which are consistent with an inner core
that had yet to form
however we know that severe porosity of
um intensity data remains
we can also see that our new data fit
well on the polynomial fit provided by
bono ital
in 2019 which is highlighted as the
dashed orange line
and we also noted that our data our
results support low field observations
prior to the onset of three phanerozoic
supercroms
suggesting a possible quasi periodicity
in dipole strength
and we can see that in this image
where you can you can see that there are
there are
lows preceding each of the three super
cons in the phanerozoic
and so in summary we've reported the
first paleo intensity results in a mid
neoproterosaric 300 million year gap
in global records and our results are
consistent
within and between site and method
ranging from one to ten microteslas
seven vdms are determined ranging from
four to nineteen zero meters squared
and that's compared to the presence
airfield of around 80 zero meters
squared
and they're associated with high qpi
scores between five and nine
and although many more reliable paleo
intensity data
are needed for a more meaningful
analysis these new data are consistent
with an inner core that had yet to form
that's it thanks it's probably quite
short
okay uh thanks very much for your talk
that was very interesting
uh oh my camera's up there there we go
um yeah that's great thanks very much uh
i i have a quick
i haven't seen if anyone else has any
questions i'll ask them in a minute but
i have a question for you
um have you compared the work you've
done
to or have you come across the work of
roman uh
velvsky in um
he's in moscow state in obviously in
russia
and he's been working on the on the cola
peninsula for the last several years
um and i know that the age range of
intrusions that he has quite a lot of
pmag data collected from covers the
interval that you're describing here
and it might be an interesting
comparison
yeah i mean it doesn't ring a bell to me
now because
the only data i know of that's published
is the stuff i've just
shown yeah like i'm not sure if it is
the exact
you know the exact same ages but it
certainly is
it certainly is flanking or the range
that he's working in is
beyond the rig you know covers the range
that you're in as well
so you might be um quite a friendly guy
like it might be a good idea to
see if you can touch base and i have
this presentation from egu
uh last year if you want to have a look
at it yeah later on i'll send it your
way
thanks bill um sorry i should have asked
does anyone else have any other
questions
no okay that's that's fair enough
um thank you very much ask the question
sorry
yeah richard go ahead yeah
so i was just wondering what the latest
uh state of play is on on whether or not
the formation of the inner core really
does increase the intensity
dramatically or does it you know to what
extent do we know for sure
that you will see a an increase in
intensity
of the field when the inner core starts
to form because i know that
you know the model is slightly unsure
which
you know some modelers say it goes one
way some say it goes the other way
yeah i i think it's still not um
100 certain because
i mean i think generally the consensus
is that you would see an increase in
intensity
certainly a change in the morphology of
the field um
yeah so it's it's not um
it's not been decided that one i don't
think
but you guess it's it's because it is
it's more certain is it that you would
you would see a low
field prior just prior to it is it
and that seems yeah yes
especially we're performing and in the
core form and so late
so the thermal strength has decreased so
much