okay excellent so um hi
i'm brendan i'm a phd student at the
university of california san diego
um and i'm going to give a talk on
something a bit different today
which is kind of looking at the
statistics of pillow intensity
and how to sort of perhaps we can we can
move forward with
um how we're analyzing paleo intensity
experiments i think a few of you may
have seen
a version of this presentation um sort
of an earlier
version of this method agu a year ago or
a couple years ago
and it's changed a fair bit since then
and
some of the sort of contribution from
that has come from my second author
matty mooresfeld
who is sort of a statistician um
predominantly and so um he's been
helping me out a lot with this method
um so um
so what we're looking at is we're
looking at atelier experiments
and i've just given two examples of sort
of ra plots from talia experiments so
the idea is
that um we are demagnetizing the
specimen by heating it to temperature
and cooling it in zero fields
and giving it a magnetization by heating
it and
cooling it in a known lab field and the
ratio of those two magnetizations
um should give us uh the ratio of the
two fields
um and you can see that it should obey
this linear relationship
um so i've given two examples here one
over sort of an experiment that's done
reasonably well
and one of an experiment that's uh not
done well at all
um and this is because probably in this
case um there's been an alteration of
the material
um but um
and so if you try to estimate using this
you'll get a very biased estimate of
paleo intensity another case where this
can happen
um is where you have um
what's known as sort of a curved or a
too slow-powered plot
um i think there's a lot of literature
now that looks at these and says that
sort of doing this kind of an estimate
where you're taking the sort of low
temperature slope of a plot that looks
like this
can cause you a biased estimate and
this this is a problem um because
you have uh sort of the whole point of
this plot is to be able to choose linear
segments
and so if you can't do that you're
you're in trouble
and so what we do is we use selection
criteria um which is sort of
statistics about these ri plot data and
other data to do with the experiment
to sort of exclude results that we
believe to be biased this could be a
result that gets
excluded um
but this is problematic because it's
sort of subjective so i'm going to show
you sort of the
three examples of plots like these and
these are all plots where this sort of
curvature
uh could be an issue and could lead to
sort of a
biased paleo intensity results um
and whether it's appropriate to sort of
select these parts of the ri plots to do
analysis is not always
clear and i think different labs using
different sets of criteria
might exclude or might accept these
specimens depending on sort of who you
ask
so where do we put the cut off is this
sort of very subjective uh
problem um and so this is something that
sort of
i was very frustrated by when i i've
been doing these experiments so
i wanted to i wanted to perhaps find
something that um
that did this in a slightly different
way so
sort of the main idea behind this is
that for any
specimen level uh estimate so that's
this b specimen
um you will have something that looks
like
the ancient fields plus some amount of
bias
and some amount of noise right and so if
we knew what this was then we could
always calculate the paleo intensity
right just by measuring
several specimens because then you know
this this would get averaged out
um but what we do is we use selection
criteria to kind of exclude things
except where this is close to zero
right and so then we don't really have
to worry about this term um
but by doing that we're kind of saying
that the selection criteria are sort of
a
predictor of what the bias will be right
so if you were doing this in a sort of
machine learning
type way you just take a load of
selection criteria
you'd model the bias as a function of
those selection criteria
and then you would um
use that to try and sort of find this
function and then you know correct back
to
the sort of good values of the selection
criteria
if that makes sense um but the issue
with that is that
we generally don't have very many
specimens at a site level
and we have a lot of selection criteria
that people use
and they're sort of mostly um
empirically based or
there's not sort of a really good
understanding of what that relationship
would be
so it's difficult to um come up with
something that wouldn't have sort of
very
big uncertainties associated with it
it's a bit too complicated for the
number of specimens that we have
but one predictor that i wanted to look
at was this sort of curvature
um and so the idea with this is that
these are data
where someone gave magnetite powders of
known grain sizes
that sort of increase in coarseness as
you go to the right
um and gave them a magnetization and
then did this experiment on them and you
can see that this sort of curvature
increases and also if you take sort of
what's what's to been done here is to
take the
sort of uh estimate just using all of
these
um points so it's not it's fitting a
line to everything but also the total
trm
does this as well you'll notice if you
look at the numbers here
that um your estimate effectively
becomes
um more biased as your curvature
increases right
um and the curvature criterion is sort
of a useful one because uh greg
patterson
in his 2011 paper um when he came up
with this kind of said that it has sort
of a reasonable correlation with the
grain size in these powders
so this is kind of an interesting thing
that we can maybe
use to predict things
so the way that i'm doing this is i'm
actually putting an uncertainty on it
so i use bayesian statistics to
calculate the curvature with uncertainty
i'm not going to go
really deep into the statistics today um
but
you can talk to me about that if you
want to um
basically the idea is that um we're
calculating so this is a circle fit to
the data
um and this is the curvature criterion
which is one over the radius with
direction
so if it's um curved this way if it's a
perfectly straight line at zero if it's
sort of curved this way it becomes a
higher curvature
so the k becomes more positive and if
it's curved this way
k becomes more negative and then to
calculate sort of a slope for a circle
the idea is that i actually sort of get
like
something that's in between the highest
slope and the lowest slope
um which is i use a tangent to the
circle
at the point that the line connecting
the origin and circle center intersects
and that seems like a really weird
um thing to use but it's actually quite
useful
uh as i'll demonstrate and it gives you
a slope in between the upper and lower
slopes and the idea there was
i was looking to see if that gave you
sort of a better or an unbiased estimate
and it doesn't
but um it's something that sort of
averages out so it's not
it's not using that sort of is it this
part or is it this part
so here's an example of not such a good
thing where potentially there's some
more stuff going wrong than curvature
but you can see that this sort of
average slope
is uh is well an example of that the
median value of that
looks like this and
the circle fit looks like this i should
mention that the
the circle fits are done by scaling the
data
first to avoid the issue
of if you have you know like a different
uh lab field used
um you would get a different curvature
so
uh they're scaled so that the it's
always
on the sort of zero one zero one scale
and then i unscale the slope of this
line so sort of some weird stuff going
there but you can see that in this case
you know you've got something that's
definitely not linear and there's no
overlap with linear here
in this probability distribution of the
curvature
um and then this is another example so
the thing about this one is that you can
also
you know take an interpretation where
you don't take the whole line
and the useful thing that's um that's
going on here is that because i've said
okay this thing has
thermo chemical alteration because this
uh
ptrm check which is a repeat of this
measurement
fails um what's going on here as i say
okay so you can only take this part of
the line and this part definitely isn't
giving us any useful information
and so what that does is it causes sort
of an uncertainty about
what the curvature of the rest of this
plot looks like
and so it sort of gives you a much
larger uncertainty in the curvature so
it sort of
helps with that idea we normally use you
know criteria that say well this line
has to be a certain length
but this sort of incorporates the
uncertainty by only picking a small part
of this line automatically
um just by just by doing this so this
kind of statist these kind of statistics
are quite useful in
their ability to calculate uncertainties
so then
you know at a site level how do we how
do we tie this all together so i'm just
going to show you a plot of what happens
if you calculate these curvatures versus
these uncertainties at a site level
you can see that um in this case the
the red line is the expected value of
the field at this site so these are all
specimens um from uh hawaiian lava flow
from i think it's the hawaii 1935 flow
and you can see that the things that
have low curvature um
as you'd expect have you know a sort of
an unbiased estimate of this
and then the things that have curvature
you know the that sort of average slope
that we calculate
is uh off um and you can see that
um probably the most appropriate model
to fit in this case to sort of these
data is you could you can sort of
imagine fitting a line through this
there's obviously this sort of outlier
here
um but you can sort of imagine doing
that right and
for the most part it would fit
reasonably well the majority of these
data so then instead of having that bias
term
you can say that you know this is sort
of a linear function of the curvature so
it's some constant
times the curvature plus noise the
specimen intensities
um and so i hope everyone
hope everyone kind of has kind of
understands this so basically applausing
curvature here
on this axis versus intensity on this
axis and so
things that have you know higher
curvature sort of becoming more biased
and we're fitting
fitting a linear fit to that and in that
case the
intercept basically the sort of
uncertainty on this intercepts
here um becomes the uncertainty on our
paleo intensity at the site
now there's no reason why this should be
linear
um it's completely empirical but for
whatever reason it does seem to hold
fairly well for a lot of sites that you
see this kind of linear trend
um in sort of intensity versus curvature
when you
when you measure it sort of the way that
i'm doing so i think this is this is
something very interesting why
why do you have this and you may say
okay well there's there's this here but
i'll kind of show you why
why this is not a problem in a second so
and
that's the reason why we're calculating
uncertainties on these things by the way
so um this is a complicated figure so
effectively what happens is when we fit
a line to these things
uh i fit both the sort of circle fits
and the line fits at the same time
and so what happens is that these
probability distributions
get modified so there's a sort of a
trade-off between
fitting the circle and fitting the line
here
um and so you can see that particularly
for
this specimen and e where we're fitting
a circle here
um the curvature gets modified to be
slightly less
and to be honest with you this specimen
is probably just altering so it's not
it's not really a curvature issue in
this case
but this really shouldn't be deciding
what our what our sort of
intensity looks like and so it's getting
modified because
these things have sort of more more
power here
so instead of you know selecting this
thing out
it's just not really uh informing
anything
when compared to sort of these data
which are really close to the intercepts
and also have smaller uncertainties
and you can see that sort of reflected
here that this thing with a linear
fit is pretty much unchanged um and so
basically there's there's this sort of
idea that um
that things that sort of fit this model
better will will be affecting
you know what what the answer looks like
better
when you have enough specimens so i'm
just going to give you some examples
of um plots where we've done this at a
site level and you can see that it's not
really linear for a lot of things but um
you know it is and and the red line in
all cases is the expected field value
for these historical flows
and you can see that um actually
probably one of the more interesting
ones here is this site where
we've got a pretty big uncertainty on
the slope here
um but you can see that um
these specimens here some of which are
sort of accepted
are biased low
um our method is less affected by this
than just putting a cut off sort of
somewhere here right depending on where
you put that cut off
um you're going to get sort of an answer
that might be
slightly biased low even even just by
these things so
um it's kind of interesting that this
this sort of works in cases where
even where you've got um you know
not not as many things that are really
close
um but these are the sort of um
probability distributions and i should
say these lines are also this is all
done through a sort of monte carlo
method so
these are all sampled from the
probability distribution and so
if you take enough samples you sort of
approximate this probability
distribution and that's what these
histograms are showing here um
and these black bars are 95 credible
intervals
um on this so they're sort of the 2.5
and 97.5
percentile of these uh samples
um so that's nice we can use this and
basically without
excluding these data we can we can get
these uh probability distributions
um that are sort of unbiased um
so to test this i applied this to a set
of specimens from sort of 30 sites where
the field was known
and as an analysis as sort of a very
broad thing i just used all the
temperature steps from every specimen so
i didn't i didn't choose things based on
that being
um you know alteration or something like
that i just did a very sort of
um naive kind of look at this
and i compared the results to secret
which is
defined in the paper that uh cromwell
paper
that i've been showing the data from and
uh greg patterson's modified version of
the picrit 03
selection criteria that don't include
this curvature parameter
um and so sites the the idea here is
that basically the number of specimens
in the site is increasing
from left to right so oh and i should
say that i did select out some specimens
where the demagnetization wasn't
completed there is sort of a
methodological reason for that but the
main reason i did that
um uh that i
had some uh stuff where the demand size
the experiments hadn't been completed
yet and i didn't want to include those
ones
so um i
didn't have those but that is very few
specimens that end up actually getting
selected out because mostly people
complete their experiments
um in these papers um so
sites with um sort of small number of
specimens in any case have
large uncertainties and that's because
there's sort of a lot of moving parts in
this model and so you need
about i would say five or six specimens
to start getting sort of a reasonable
um uncertainty in your results you can
see that this one has three and it has
an
okay uncertainty but it's probably you
know more than people would like
this is the normalized intensity i
should say so this is the expected value
is the red line and then this is sort of
the
ratio of the value to the expected value
and these are 95
confidence intervals so so for the
selection criteria it's just a two sigma
interval
and then for our method it's that 95
confidence interval what i was showing
you before um
and the shaded area is uh plus or minus
three microtesla
in all cases so you get an idea sort of
the absolute deviation as well
and you can see that sort of in most
cases we get a very similar result to
the secret
uh criteria and
you can see that um as you sort of
increase your number of specimens
actually um
my method starts to become more precise
than the secret method i think that
that's
um that's something to know and
basically the reason for that is that
it's like looking at a
uh standard error of the mean and these
are just sample standard deviations
um and you can see that for the pickered
stuff they
don't generally perform as well they're
generally you know more affected by
these biased results
so um i have another set from the other
15.
so in this case you can see that when we
get to sort of the high numbers of
specimens you'll notice that this high
precision thing
starts to get sort of more precise um in
some cases than we would expect so
the picture is not you know great
everywhere
um and the reason i think for this
is as i said before this is like a
standard error in the mean and so that
would also be
um inaccurate for these sites
um these three um in particular
these are yuji yamamoto papers where he
suggests that it's perhaps a tcrm
acquisition which causes a slight bias
in italian experiments and he says
that's why you should use his ltd sure
method
the other thing that he mentions in in
this paper in particular is actually
that there's there's an uncertainty in
the igrf field
um for some of these sites right which
is about to microtesla
and actually if you include that that
they do
you know sort of within confidence
overlap with our data so
sort of either of those could be invoked
here and you can see that there are sort
of some sites like this
msh site where um
we have sort of a lot of poor quality
data and it does sort of make
an inaccurate result in the end because
there's basically nothing good in there
and what's going on
wrong with this site is probably not
curvature
um but there's sort of a these are
imprecise with high numbers of specimens
so there's actually a way of sort of
telling that there's something wrong
with these sites
which i'm going to go into now so
basically the way that this looks this
is a plot of the sort of number of
specimens per site and then this is the
sort of width of that 95
credible interval as an estimate
uh of the paleo intensity and you can
see that um
basically this is this is a log scale so
these are like this is like 100
microtesla and this dashed line is 20
microtesla this is five specimens right
and so you can kind of see that as
things increase in their number of
specimens
they generally sort of get down to sort
of that full 95
confidence interval being uh less than
uh 10 microtesla which is you know if
you
if this was a normal distribution that
would be a standard deviation of 2.5
microtesla right for the sort of forward
the 95 confidence interval and these
the the coloration here i should say is
um
basically the the deviation from the
expected value
and so you can see that sort of these
things that despite having high numbers
of specimens
have a high deviation from the expected
value
also have high uncertainties with these
high numbers of specimens
sort of greater than 20 with more than
five which is sort of something that
i'm looking at some it's somewhere
around here right
and so this is kind of telling you that
there's something going wrong which is
that you keep measuring more things
but you're not really converging on a
very precise estimate
um so sort of the idea with the workflow
with this would be that you know you'd
start off here as you're measuring
specimens
and as you continue to measure more
things you get more precise until you
you know reach a sort of desired level
of precision
um and if you don't reach that desired
level of precision after a certain
number of specimens then you say well
there's something wrong with this site
um this this methodology isn't isn't
sort of what we need to do for this
um so sort of i guess the the advantages
of this is obviously you have this
workflow
uh where you could you don't need to
worry about sort of the numbers and
that the other thing is that it sort of
it propagates these uncertainties
um from the sort of um interpretations
that you make that are subjective
into um into your sort of site level
estimate
and so this means that it basically
accounts for sort of all those
selection criteria that are things that
are like
curvature obviously the curvature one
but also sort of length of line and sort
of scatter things
um it sort of incorporates that into the
the uncertainty of what the curvature
and therefore what the bias is
this method can't tell you which set of
temperature steps to use so sort of my
my suggestion there is that um you
shouldn't
pick your set of temperature steps based
on the sort of ra plot
in field zero field steps you can do it
based on things like ptrm checks which
are indicators of alteration
and you can probably do it based on um
direction um for this method because you
know if you have multiple components
then you should be able to
select things based on direction um
but uh you probably shouldn't do it just
based on what's curved or not because
then you
may be getting sort of you know your
uncertainty will blow up but you might
start to get things that are
that are biased in there um so sort of
the final part of this project is that
i'm sort of working on a
web-based dashboard that takes data sort
of formatted in
the magic format and you can process it
using this
method and so the aim is to make this uh
available sort of as the paper releases
um and then you can sort of just analyze
your data using this
um at this you know and so hopefully
this this will be going live you know
you i don't know exactly when but i want
to be submitting this
sort of within the next month sometime
so are there any questions
um imagine there will be
thank you very much yeah go ahead
hi brandon uh very nice talk and um the
yeah in principle this this sounds great
um i've got lots of questions about the
details of it but i'll try and restrict
it to
two so you mentioned overprints right at
the end there
or multiple components because i guess
you've only tested this on on zero age
rocks right which right yeah so not zero
yeah i tested this on historical things
yeah
there's there's a question of overprints
um
i just received um some data
that are um
that are archaea magnetic data that were
recorded in two different fields so i
think they're bricks that were fired
and then used in a furnace somewhere
else and so they they record two
different fields and so
i'm going to try this on those
but in theory because you can sort of
make that selection and you can make it
based on
direction right you you will still find
um an answer to that it's just that
because you've got a lower part of the
line your uncertainty blows up from that
so you you sort of with this method the
idea is that you want to make the best
interpretation of the data that you can
given the evidence you have but i would
argue that you probably don't want to do
that
on ri plot data alone unless they're
ptrm checks you want some sort of other
evidence that there's alteration or
there's another
another field now people might say that
um with vrm um
there is an issue because you know vrm
could be in a similar direction
and i guess i would argue there that you
could probably select out the
temperature steps according to sort of
the nail
theory of vrm if you have an idea about
how old these things are
um but you don't want to select things
out
um that have sort of a greater number of
temperature sets than that because then
what is that right if it's not if it's
not a nail theory there and then you're
getting into the realm of things that
you don't really understand and then
then there are some issues with that
sure okay but in principle you you
you'd expect this to be useful for much
older rocks as well
yes definitely yeah i have tested it on
some
of my results from hawaii which range
between sort of zero and five which are
not
you know that's old but they definitely
have over prints in some cases for the
or not overprints but vrms that are in a
different direction
um and um those
actually work um really well so
yeah all right so
can i follow up things sorry because you
mentioned ptrm checks there as well
the alteration so you're excluding parts
which you're saying are clearly
biased due to alteration um not in
the data that i've presented i just did
a really naive
uh fit to just the whole thing and it
still works right okay well
that's that's very boring for me because
um
because ptm checks can fail because of
md behavior right which is what you're
trying to
uh right yes something that
it's possible to look at and i don't
necessarily advocate for peter m checks
i mean you could you could look at you
know
something like uh bulk susceptibility um
after each measurement and stuff like
that and that might be a more
a more useful indicator i'm not i'm kind
of open to the idea of using other
things as an indicator for alteration
but i just think you need that evidence
of something being alteration
um and pcrm checks are probably more
likely to be that than
multi-domain effects i've got a couple
more questions
um who is that
sorry and win
like that's really nice talk brendan i
firstly i wouldn't get too hung up on
the mice and helen samples i know greg
will tell you that you know he
the success rate of those was pretty
close to zero so i you know
there's a lot of chemical alteration in
those samples
i was just kind of curious because i
know that andy and both greg have worked
on you know how many samples as a rule
of thumb should you be aiming to sample
in the field it's okay
you know coming back and saying you need
to keep measuring samples until
until you get to this optimum number or
behavior but when you're in the field
you don't know what you're going to get
so i mean how many
what would your sam what would you
suggest your sampling strategy in the
field should be for people how many
samples should they be collecting
per year right so so because um
yeah so so i guess for me this is not
this is not something that
i've been thinking about in that way
because it scripts what we do is we take
hand samples and then we use these small
chips to do
um hill intensity measurements so so
number of samples is not
really a field constraint that we have
to think about
um i mean i think as a general rule you
want to drill as many cores as you can
right um if you've got a good uh if
you've got a good sort of
uh set of measurements right it seems to
be that you know within about
i don't know less less than 10 right
um you seem to be able to get sort of a
reasonable uncertainty on this and
although this number is 20 right that's
the full width of the 95
confidence interval so that's that's not
actually
as large a number as you would think
when you compare it to sort of
what we normally look about with pale
intensity results which is where we we
often will say to the standard deviation
of five microteslas is what's acceptable
so you know maybe maybe drill sort of
you know
uh 10 10 would be great right if you can
get
uh six or seven might be more realistic
yeah
yeah okay so when
uh just a quick question i mean
obviously this depends upon the
linearity between your
um curvature um
and i just wondered uh you know have you
you know you showed up one graph i guess
that looked legally linear but
to have much confidence in this would be
nice to have some
sort of understanding of about why that
should be or if it
varies according to different mineralogy
or distribution
yeah i i have no idea why um
why that's the case so i didn't i didn't
show the data here but those crosser
data as well they also
obey this kind of they're actually
really highly linear
except for the single domain one but um
it doesn't it's not that far off the
line so
it doesn't it doesn't bias the result
that much so i called that site
synthetic 60 because it doesn't have a
name
and you can see that it's it's moved
slightly high but um
it still gives you sort of a reasonable
result um
but those that all the all the um
sort of non perfect sd things
lie on like an almost perfect line when
you use this method on them
so i do think that there's potentially
whatever this effect is there is
potentially some sort of relationship
there which
i you know it's interesting unless
unless that's just a fluke
um but i it does seem to keep coming up
in in sites where you know
you wouldn't expect it to where you know
you see
things that have you know very linear
looking um results which is which is
always interesting to me
i i have no idea why i did i did try um
because i was like okay well
you know there's no reason that it
should be a linear model i did try doing
this with um
higher order polynomial fits and um just
to see you know if something if
something like that would work or if
there's different models that would be
appropriate
and they're all worse basically because
the number of parameters increases and
the um
the sort of there's not a multi-demand
effect right because you'd see it in the
ptrm checks to certain degree
what do you mean the curvature
curvature's not a multiple yeah
well the linearity um
well okay so that's the linearity of the
curvature
with the specimen level intensity
i think comes from the fact that i'm
using that tangent
to fit things um i don't think you would
see that
as easily if you were just using
um like you know a best fitting line to
part the data or something like that
i think that's why this this hasn't been
observed so it's it's something to do
with like the aspect ratio of that
i i don't i honestly can't couldn't
comment on why
it's the case um but um i think it's i
think it's
interesting that it it's something that
i've observed um but yeah i did i did
try harder all the polynomial fits and
the the
precision blows up and the accuracy
doesn't get any better so
i thought that the linear fit is the
most appropriate thing to
to apply here yeah okay looks good
so we've got another question from greg
hi hi brendan um that's a really good
talk um
there's a ton of stuff to to for me to
think about and to
digest there but actually this the main
thing i'll
also make a comment on is um kind of
follows on from what you're just talking
about
um you know at first glance you might
think that
this method might depend a little bit on
um your choice of how you define your
tangent
um when you're um fitting your curves
but um i i i suspect that it probably
doesn't
um and this kind of comes back to some
of the data that that
we saw when we looked at the synthetic
samples in the original curvature paper
and i think the reason why you see such
a nice linear relationship between
curvature and
intensity so you know if you pick
you can actually pick a best fit line on
almost any segment
of um of the curved derived plot and
you'll find that there is a general
um linear relationship with that
intensity estimate
and the degree of curvature and and
that's just
it's a a geometric factor with how
a circle is fitted the curvature of a
circle basically is related
to its its slope um but i'd be
interested to see if you were to define
your tangent differently
um that make sure that you do get a
consistent linear behavior
um when you're comparing intensity to um
to the curvature and all it should
really do i suspect is change
the uh slope of that linear relationship
and that that would be a quite useful
thing to check that it's robust that
it's independent of how you define
your tangent fit and then there's a ton
of other questions and ideas and things
but i don't think we'll have time to
to yeah feel free discussing you know if
you want to talk about it sometimes
yeah cool thank you very much