okay is that visible
to people thumbs up right yep okay
excellent all right well thank you very
much uh for the kind introduction
will um and as first speaker um i will
say yeah very big thank you to
to will and lot and anybody else for
setting this up it's great to see so
many people um
uh here we're looking forward to this
okay so um
yeah i'm going for uh an award for the
most co-authors on a talk here
um but fully justified of course um
because this this talk is kind of a
quite high level
overview with kind of a trunk of a tree
i guess where it's kind of branching off
to
to uh other people's presentations and
recent recent papers
and so on um but there is a kind of
tight theme which is
integrating early magnetic data with
with numerical dynamo simulations and
that's
central to to what we're trying to do um
in liverpool
and was the topic of a workshop we had
about a year and a half ago
before all this covered nonsense started
um
in wales so that's where this photo is
from um here
okay so this is a very broad
introduction
so when paleomagnetists and this will be
a talk primarily
for paleomagnetism um when we talk about
models
uh more often than not we're referring
to to field models based on
spherical harmonic descriptions um uh
of the real field uh to some degree
um so these can be time varying like
these ones
this one over here figures this is ggf
100k so the longest time varying model
um that we have last hundred thousand
years
um or they can be statistical um
so uh no real times every draw from the
model is a single
instant snapshot uh in time and here
we're not looking for the time
series then we're looking at um mean
values
being paleomagnetic pole latitudes shown
up here here at the top
um and the shapes of distributions in in
this case for virtual geomagnetic
poles sampled different uh latitudes
uh now both these models um more
generally why models are so useful
is is um that they give global coverage
okay so they will
they're designed to match um
paleomagnetic data from from specific
places um
but the idea is they fill in the gaps
everywhere else on the surface of the
earth so you can go anywhere and ask
what the field was doing
[Music]
but something that is highly pertinent
to these sorts of models
is that they're not physics-based so
that's not to say that they're
unphysical uh physics uh creeps in there
from
from the rules that are associated with
the the how the spherical harmonics
uh relate uh to each other and the power
spectrum
um but that comes in from from
observations of the recent field not
from any um
uh physical uh processes um
but you know the first order of the
physics of what's producing the magnetic
field
is you know fairly well understood
so it's in dynamo theory so essentially
we have a rapidly rotating spherical
shell
the outer core filled with conductive
fluid
that is convecting and there's a dynamic
process going on that's generating
as it passes through the existing
magnetic field generating more magnetic
field so
this is more or less the entirety of the
equations that you have to solve
don't worry i'm not going to go through
them but just point out that
workstations or supercomputers you can
simultaneously solve
these equations and time step through
the dynamic process
producing as a result an output that is
a magnetic field as viewed at the
surface which is what of course is
paleomagnetism we're interested in
now any model has input parameters so
these are
kind of the tuning knobs i guess for um
for what you
you twiddle to get the model to behave
in a different way
and the primary ones for dynamo models
are these dimensional four dimensionless
numbers here i'll only mention two of
them briefly one of them the ekman
number
so this is the ratio of um viscous
coriolis forces and this is
extremely small in the earth like 10
to the minus 16. um in the models we
can't get down to
that such low values uh where um
11 or 12 volts of magnitude uh higher
than this so that means we're ramping up
the viscosity and
the reason for this is that that
suppresses all the small scale
um turbulence which we couldn't hope to
simulate even in our
fastest uh supercomputers the other one
i'll mention is the rayleigh number
so hopefully many of you familiar with
this already that describes the
um what defines the the bigger of the um
the convection
um in the system this we have to ramp up
artificially high to overcome this
this enhanced viscosity um now so that
means that we're not in the earth like
regime
in these um but there is a whole wealth
of literature out there and to kind of
sum up
i guess the state of the art as i
understand it we're more or less in a
place
now where the false balance um is
arguably
the same as in the earth uh and so for
all extents and purposes that we're
interested in the resource large scale
features of the field emerging at the
the surface
[Music]
yeah there's arguably realistic we are
uh we are generating an earth-like
process
okay so here's some some models here
shown on the left here we've got a
fairly recent one by julian ober
and co-authors high-resolution model
we're showing the
um velocity of the flow uh in the core
here and you
might be able to make out there's
different flow structures inside and
outside this
inner core tangent cylinder so that's
aligned
around the inner core in the direction
of the rotation
um axis and here we've got some some
outputs
and uh there's from paper from lulia in
and we've got a nice time series here
where we've got a reversal
shown in there a few things that kind of
look a bit like small excursions and
we've got the
dipole moment going uh up and down and
you know what could look like a
plausible manner
um so dynamic models produce time
varying
outputs are these time series but we of
course
these well apart from some things that
julian has done on the very recent field
of
um and others have worked on data
assimilation where
try to mimic the the very recent field
uh without exception
other time series that you'll see from
dynamic models are the ones that we're
using
they're not trying to replicate any
particular point in history
of um of the earth's magnetic field so
you
treat these time simulations as a dynamo
as the outputs of a dynamic process not
the geodynamo
and you look at them in a statistical
sense um but similar to the field models
they give
global coverage and now at least you
know
they are based in the physics rather
than just being you know geometrical
descriptions of the field okay so
we tend to use um as paleomagnetists you
know we we do use field models
particularly
uh archaeo magnets use time varying
field models
a lot and paleomagnetists use
statistical field models a lot so
to test whether there are directions of
average secular variation for example
um and to correct for inclination uh
shadowing using the
ei technique based on the tko3 model
but we don't tend to use dynamo models
okay and
we're looking to to try and maybe change
that uh because there's some good
reasons why we should be using
uh diamond models so as i've said you
know the outputs the
physics-based dynamically
self-consistent uh we have the potential
for extremely long time series
so time varying models you know i got to
100 000 years
at the most you know we can produce
things that are tens hundreds of
millions of years
um long and um
i guess the the big cell for dynamo
models is that because it's related to
the physics of
of the the core and the deep earth we
have the potential to recover
information then about what saying what
our results mean
uh not only for the field but also for
um for article dynamics
and mental forcing and core evolution
and so on um
but there are some uh some negatives as
well that have to bear in mind with
dynamic models first is that these
they're all
dimensionless essentially so that's fine
for directions and directions that's all
that's all okay um but for intensities
and for time
um these need to be scaled so the models
need to be calibrated and
there are some uncertainties associated
with that with that calibration
um they're very computationally
expensive to run
and that said what you emerged that
we're mostly interested in is time
series of gauss coefficients it's
exactly the same as you'd have from
a time bearing model so you can then
play around with the outputs of them in
the same way as you would
with a time varying model you'll need to
run them uh actually once
uh and then this final point that i
think gets to the nub of why
we don't use them more is that yeah
perimeters dynamic modelers
you know just don't talk to each other
um very much there's some notable
exceptions in the past so
um mcfadden michael hinney and merrell
um did some good work great work in the
90s and
um robco and gary glatzmeyer they've
done some work in the
uh and the naughties more recently um
but other than that
generally there's been a there's been a
gap between um
these two communities that we're trying
to trying to bridge
because there's some some really good
reasons to do that um
because over here we've got
paleomagnetic measurements so clearly
observations
of the real world but they have the
problems that
they're especially temporarily
restricted
and where the data can come from and
we've got the
error and bias associated with with the
measurement processes themselves and
recording processes
and over here geodynamic model outputs
so yep the
the you know predictions from a
simulated
um geodynamic process uh they give
you know perfect coverage so complete
global and
get them we tend to use one through the
time step of around 65 years
so that's a pretty high resolution
temporal resolution
um but of course we require constraints
and observations
so how can um these two areas help each
other well i've
kind of noted that down as a series of
research questions that are going to be
covered in the rest of this talk so
we have we can ask how realistic
these models are and what input
parameters
best produces realism and going the
other way what can the
how can the models help um our
measurements uh they can tell us about
the
ancient us um the magnetic field give us
more information than just our
measurements do
and about the uh the source of that as
well
okay so um
first question how realistic are the
models so when we first came to this we
thought this you know we're not the
first to think about this and we thought
this problem was solved
um because there are already criteria
out there um
so notably other christians criteria
from 2010 and these certainly there's a
whole bunch of models and they are
earth-like and they're all good but then
we looked at them
details started comparing them to
paleomagnetic datasets rather than just
stuff from the the recent field
and we found that there's a whole host
of problems which um
i've kind of listed here and i'll give
you some examples down here from one of
the early models we looked at so this
one you know it reverses
um great um this inclination normally is
huge you know 16 degrees
inclination anomaly so that would be a
real problem for uh plate tectonic
reconstructions there's no evidence of
sport
at least in the last 10 million years or
so and the other big problem we found
was that paleosecular variation was
often very
unearth-like so we'd expect vgp
dispersion angular dispersion to be
about
11 degrees or something that's what we
see for the last 10 million years and
here it's up in the
you know the mid-20s or something at low
latitude and
increasing with latitude as we do see so
we had this whole bunch of problems
uh with all our simulations so we built
up 46
and we wanted some way to say okay which
ones are more accurate than the others
and
how are they um inaccurate uh so
this was worked by um by courtney sprain
um she published this paper in 2009
on the qpm criteria so set of five
criteria i'm not going to go through
them all
um just to say you can see from this bar
chart over here
um that we've got a lot of big red
columns so
most of the models failed most of the
criteria
so you can have a maximum qpm score of
five if you're meeting all five but we
don't even go up to that on the scale
because none of them went above
three okay and the other question is is
this misfit so this is based on the
normalization
uh of the um the discrepancy in
uh the simulated and the reference
values but also taking into account the
uncertainties
as well and what we found
uh for these um is that we never got
below
this magic number of five which means
that we
yeah five is is a good number because
that means on average then
all of our criteria are within um errors
of one another uh so we scratched our
heads a little bit
and um went to work on this and
domenico midori uh liverpool
did some great work on this and the
first thing he found was
that we have this nice we tended when
you plot the models together you tend to
get this nice parabola shape
in this space where you've got the qpm
misfit here with five as magic number
down here uh against the die polarity so
how much does a dipole dominate at the
core mantle boundary
and where these things dipped uh to
their lowest misfit to the most
realistic models was also
a roundabout within areas of where
earth-like models were predicting
uh of where sorry um descriptive field
models were predicting the dipolarity
uh to be as well but a lot of models
never really got
never got close to this this um this
magic line of
five um and what we actually found was
that it
it required then to go to chemical
chemically forced models so models
purely driven
by the growth of the inner core and the
release of light elements there rather
than by thermal convection
um but once we did that then we did find
some models that did dip in
into this area um we didn't find
anything that was absolutely perfect
with a qpm of five but we did get to a
misfit of about two and a half
um so this is our model with the lowest
misfit
and where it falls down um in terms of
failing criteria is it doesn't reverse
quite enough so you can see it's got a
nice earth like
reversal in there and excursions but
they're just not frequent enough to
uh to represent the last 10 million
years
okay now an interesting we've got a nice
dipolar shape and we've got this
variability in
dipole moment that appears earth
uh now an interesting observation to
make from this is that if you take
th this model and you just you you
change nothing about it apart from the
rayleigh number you force it a little
bit harder you change the rayleigh
number 4.6 to 1.8 times 10 to the 7 so
that's
just sucking the heat out of the core a
little bit faster allowing the unicorn
to grow a bit faster
and suddenly you've got a completely
different model that's now got reversal
hyperactivity
uh in there it's looking a lot less
dipolar and it's looking a lot weaker as
well so this is really
supporting that you don't need to do
much to the geodynamo to make it
change its behavior quite radically um
okay so we got to uh to near enough our
most earth-like model um but that's not
to say that all the ones that weren't
earth-like weren't also really useful
for us
um so one thing that richard bono
um worked on was looking at all the
models and finding
that they all contained um or a large
number of them contain
systematic um covariance between
different
spherical harmonic terms within them so
for example this first what this first
column is showing is that to increase g1
you also tend to increase g30 the axial
octopole goes with the axial dipole now
the reason this was interesting is
because our statistical field models at
the moment
from something called a giant gaussian
process where all these terms
act completely independently of each
other and the dynamo models were saying
well
you know that's actually not what's
happening in at least you know
in these simulations uh so what richard
did then was try to incorporate this
this covariance into a giant gaussian
process model and what he found was that
the resulting uh
um fit to data improved
quite markedly so what are our
measurements telling us
well perhaps that the um the earth also
has this covariance between these
different terms and that's telling us
something about the structures
um of the that are generating the
magnetic field
so another aspect that was really useful
it's up there andy you're
you're a good you're a few couple of
minutes left there
couple of minutes left okay i'll i'll
wrap up so this is just pointing another
paper that's very recently
um accepted um which was
yeah linking um the shape of the field
to its variability
um so what we found was that as you you
vary the field
um as sorry as the field becomes more
variable
then you see that it's it becomes less
uh dominated by an axial dipole it looks
less
like a bar magnet and this was really
interesting because
we don't have any measurements of axial
dipole dominance from before um a few
million years ago whereas we have
measurements of paleosecular variation
back to billions of years ago and got a
nice
power law predictive power law that came
out from all our simulations and from
field models as well uh so we're able to
say something about the
um about how dipole uh axial dipole
dominance
has uh has changed through geological
history and
uh the big um uh the key point to emerge
from that is not very much
so the field didn't often look like this
or like this
in actual fact it spent most of its time
looking like this which is igrf all
right which is today's field
okay so something else that's told us so
just a quick future application
um so just to point out that we've been
also been doing a huge amount of work at
liverpool on
measuring um the properties of the
paleomagnetic field back through
geological time
and uh these yellow points show our
efforts at
um increasing the number of estimates of
dipole moment through geological time in
the last five years
and uh what we've outlined are um yeah
it's two periods in particular where the
field was
appears to be radically different in
that is much weaker um
than today um so you know a big question
of how we go forward
uh with with dynamo models is can we
capture this behavior like we have done
for the last 10 million years as well
okay and if we can then knowing how we
have to perturb our present day model
to um to simulate a field looking like
these we might be able to say something
about how the physical properties
of the deep earth have um have changed
over time
okay so i'm out of time so i'll just
leave my summary slide up there thank
you
oh