great uh next talk uh
coming from yale and yale n
bears uh uh on recurring magnetic field
anomalies in the south atlantic and the
first paleo intensities are from saint
helena
yeah let me just share my screen
can everybody hear me yeah and we can
see your screen as well
awesome and my pointer
everything ready um so thank you my name
is yael ingers
and i want to discuss um the south
atlantic anomaly or the recurrence
of south of irregular behavior in the
field in the south atlantic
and with that the first paleo intensity
is coming from saint elena which is the
blue star
on this global field strength uh figure
um see so first a little
recap of today's magnetic field which is
not a perfect dipole
in this figure you can see the field
strength from igrf-12 from 2015
where you can clearly see a weakness in
the south atlantic which we
call the south atlantic anomaly and
this anomaly leads to irregular uh
behavior at st helena which is this blue
star where for instance the declination
is almost 17 degrees off
and the intensity is 29 micro tesla
where we would expect
almost 34 micro tests left for a gad
field
so a dipole field
why is this uh anomalous feature so
important
and talked about so often uh well for
instance our satellites get
um get damaged because the magnetic
field doesn't protect them
as well as they should in the south
atlantic but for us geophysicists and
geologists it's more important to
discuss the link between the anomalous
behavior of the field
and the lower most mental features uh
which was done by
john tradino in 2015 uh tardino and
others
published data and new data from south
africa saying that the south atlantic
anomaly was longer lived
than thought before and they linked it
to
the steep edge of this uh large low
shear velocity province or lsvp
under south under africa which they
say causes this the first flux patch in
the
field on the core mental boundary then
causing the south atlantic anomaly or
anomalous features in the field
other study studies suggest that the
southland anomaly and the overall
weakening of the field might
be a precursor of the whole field
reversing which obviously is also very
interesting
to all geologists and especially
paleomontists
um and if this atlantic
uh irregular behavior is actually very
long-lived feature does it
interfere with the hypothesis hypothesis
of a geocentral actual dipole
um these are some reasons of the many
publications that came out in the last
couple of years
uh showing here with for my personal
highlight
our paper this summer uh in pnas with
the directional data from saint elena
uh saying that in fact there was
irregular behavior in the south atlantic
on a million-year time scale when
looking at directions from saint helena
so why do we look at saint-elaine now
all these other studies that i showed in
the previous slide
talk about last 300 000 years maximum
but when we talk about timer rich field
we
preferably want to look at at least 10
million years
which is also why we looked at this data
set
that was published by cromwell and
others um in 2018
discussing all the paleo secular
variation data from the past 10 million
years
which we used to compare our direction
from
directions from saint-elaina with uh and
saint-elaine is
a volcanic island that has rocks
from between the ages of eight and a
half and 11 million years old
so a quick recap of uh the directional
study that we published this summer
um we performed directional uh
paleo directions on about 50 sites and
here are all the results in this equal
area plot
which we then turned into virtual
geomagnetic poles
and those virtual geometric pools were
uh quite scattered even though they
averaged out
to this uh pool that comes quite close
to the geographical the dispersion is
very high
which is 21.9 degrees which we then
compared to all the other data
in this plot in from psv10 so that's 10
million year old
at 10 million year database and where
this red star
is our dispersion from saint elena which
clearly is an outlier and doesn't follow
this
beautiful trend that shows the
latitudinal dependence of the dispersion
so with that we said the irregular field
in the south atlantic
is actually occurring on a million-year
time scale
based on these directions um but now we
want to talk about the paleo intensities
from the same island
so first we go back to this island where
we went on field work
andy bigen and i in january 2018.
uh it's beautiful island which is
circled here on this map it's about 2
000 kilometers west of africa
about 122 square kilometers in surface
the geology of st lane is rather
straightforward it's a volcanic island
that consists of two shield volcanoes
the red and orange in this little plot
uh show the older northeast volcano
and the blue purple colors showed a
younger southwest volcano
that consists of three different shields
a lower shield
middle shield and an upper shield and
which we all sampled
in all these yellow spots where we
gathered
lava flows we sampled over 50 sites
uh usually about five to ten samples per
site
and the flow thickness varied from about
20 centimeters to 10 meters
and where possible we sampled the bottom
middle and top of the flow
so before we dove into the paleo
intensity experiments we performed rock
magnetic experiments
we created susceptibility curves uh on
the copper bridge
we performed experiments on the vfdb
creating hysteresis loops
and irm plots and we perform vrm
experiments
here i'm showing uh the susceptibility
curves from all the
successful sites and you can see that
even within all these
sites that actually gave more than three
uh
three or more petty intensity results
the susceptibility
curves give very varying uh
ideas of the rock mag within
saint helena
yeah that already gave us not the best
hope
for paleo intensity results and they are
actually quite hard to get
so we so far only performed pillion
intensity experiments on two localities
one from the mid shield of the younger
volcano ladder hill
uh and one from the older volcano banks
valley
that's the abbreviations are lh and pv
which is handy for the
upcoming slides and we performed uh
thermal izzy talia and microwave is
italian
and here's an overview of the selection
criteria that i use
for the brilliant intensity experiments
um
that we can that uh i'm showing later on
as well
so let's start with the good results or
okayish results here already arrived
plots from samples that
uh passed quite clearly our
selection criteria some are very
straight lines beautiful right plots
no viscous overprint and no alteration
or hardly any alteration
um then there are some plots with a
little bit of a too sloppy behavior but
from the zeitgeist plots it becomes
quite obvious that it is
uh this is a viscous overprint that
we're dealing with
um so yeah there's definitely some
results that i'm happy with
and when you look at the actual
intensities that they produce they are
all relatively low or very very low like
this five micro tesla
eight micro tesla and the highest in
this plot
and you know uh most of them is 23 micro
tesla where the field at saint elena
today
is 29 micro tesla
so we also have a lot of very bad
results that i thought i would throw in
there
uh yeah almost laughable
sad but let's move on quickly to the
more interesting results
or the ugly results as michael
introduced them
these are results that
look like they shouldn't pass selection
criteria but they do
like this ladder hill 10 site which
shows very zigzagged results
but does pass all the selection criteria
in this case we think that this is due
to the big difference between the lab
field
of 20 micro tesla and the ancient field
that is producing
4.7 micro tesla and we were right when
we
reproduced the same uh experiments but
with a lower lap field of 10 micro tesla
we got the same results
but with a more beautiful um
beside a right plot which is shown in
this
figure two slides back um
but the most problematic sites
are lh6 and lh13 which show very
two-slope
uh behavior very strong to slow behavior
and for instance in this case you could
argue
because of the zeita felt plot that this
is due to a viscous overprint
but in some cases the actual steep slope
passes the selection criteria like here
on the right
and which produces a field of 87
microtesla
which is problematic to say the least
considering the others
samples produce a field of 10 or 20
micro tesla
um so yeah this is the case for lh6 and
lh-13
and uh we're wondering if this is due to
md particles multi-domain particles um
order because of uh viscous overprints
so
we need to do more experiments and add
ptrm tilt checks
to our experiments uh the microwave
samples also don't show this
uh so hopefully we can also create some
more microwave experiments however the
microwave is broken
at the moment um so for now i've chosen
to
include all the all the samples all the
results
that pass the selection criteria if i
make the selection criteria
stricter i don't actually lose these and
i do lose some of the values that i do
trust
so that is not a solution unfortunately
um here is an overview of the eight
sites that we have so far that have
uh paleo intensities with an n
of three or higher and then you can
immediately see that there's
two sites with the too slow behavior
that
sometimes give a very high intensity and
sometimes very low have a
incredibly high um standard deviation
that is almost as high as the as the
pain intensity itself
um so yeah we need to look into that
where where that comes from
and do more experiments but when looking
at the other results
except for the oldest 1bv1 which is 27
microtesla
all the results are very low 15
microseconds
or lower um which is interesting uh
and which could suggest that not only
were the directions irregular
in the south atlantic but also the field
was
maybe weaker or recurringly weak um a
few things to note is that none of these
sites show
transitional directions in the
directional study that we published
even though the intensities are so low
that you could
suggest or think that these are in
transitional times
another thing is that these three sites
give quite similar
uh paleo intensities and we're also
in directions so similar and that we
tested for serial correlation
and they were used as one directional
group
um yeah again we need more experiments
with ptrm steel checks to
test for md behavior um and i have more
sites that i can
perform plenty intensity experiments on
yeah what does this mean for the field
in the south atlantic
um if we do include these very high
intensities from
ladder hill 6 and ladder hill 13 with
the too slow behavior
that could mean that the field strength
is varying highly
um which would agree with the high
dispersion in directions
that we published in pnes um
but if these insanely high intensities
of like 80 micro tesla are due to
multi-domain behavior or overprints and
we would exclude them
all the intensities that we're left with
are overall very weak
uh which could suggest that the
anomalous behavior in the south atlantic
is actually
caused by referring uh recurring from
the first flux patch
um specifically on the chromatic
boundary
our conclusions uh is that saint elena
lab flows are not great
for poly intensity experiments but it is
possible
uh in the flows that we do get good
results for we see
very low intensities down to five micro
tesla
and some flows we see extreme too slow
behavior that can be interpreted as very
low or very high intensities with the
current set of selection criteria
this could mean either very varying
intensities were present
or if we wouldn't exclude these two
slope behavior uh
sites we mainly see very low value
intensities for saint elena
either way the existence of the
extremely weak piling intensities give
more evidence of the recurrent anomalous
behavior of the magnetic field
in the south atlantic on a million year
time scale
thank you
cool excellent nice talk thanks very
much for that
um i have a question but i think i'll be
the good convener and ask does anyone
else have a question first before
i uh right okay
that's it everyone else had a chance i'm
jumping in um
it's just a curiosity uh bv 1-1
the sample the the temperature versus
susceptibility curve for that looks
funky it's like there's
at least what three different minerals
it does look funky and we have a lot of
these funky susceptibility
uh curves with a lot of phases a lot of
titanium but then even faces with
different amounts of titanium and
i i do not have enough knowledge to
interpret these
in detail uh i tried i made like little
prints of
all the different susceptibility results
that i had and tried to group
them together and it was almost
impossible we have so many different
uh behaviors even within one site
that yeah it's just uh yeah on mixing
the kind of temperature versus the
susceptibility cars and there's more
than one phase and there is is kind of
tricky it's one of the things that guys
up here are working on they're building
they're just running loads of loads and
loads of minerals to try and make a
library of them
but but pv one one is is like what
there's like definitely three different
phases in there and
you could kind of say maybe tighten the
magnetite for a couple of them but is it
really that you have that many different
phases of the same
oxide in there probably not but but yet
you're getting good data out of it
yeah which is interesting
is actually carrying that signal for you
sorry
which of these phases do you think
carrying the signal
um for bb1 i would have to dive into the
actual
right plots i don't think i have
any of them in here but i should have
them in a later
oh we can talk about it later i mean i
would have to look at which
component uh i used to interpret it
obviously but
um yeah i i don't know but from memory
which
component i guess um uh
does uh perhaps professor williams do
you have a question for us
i do yeah i'm about to expose my
ignorance of the geology really so i it
was a really nice
talk actually but i i didn't quite uh
get the ultimate conclusion in terms of
um
the prevalence of these uh low shear
velocity provinces
or these reverse flux patch patches and
actually if
are they inconsistent with each other
those two conclusions um
not necessarily no it's just that based
on my previous
uh study of the directions all we could
say was
there is some behavior on the core
mental boundary either
reverse flux patches and normal flux
patches on
alternating or there's something going
on but if it was
a weak field constantly and not
an unstable field that is sometimes high
and sometimes weak and averages out
as uh gad uh if it's mainly weak then
that would
suggest a reverse flux patch is
dominantly causing it
okay yeah and what is your what what is
your best guess
to be honest i do um i obviously think
about this a lot but i'm not sure if
i can use paleo intensities for this
best guess yet because i would
need to convince myself a little bit
more of these weak intensities first
um but i i think there's a combination
going on between the
uh the llsvp causing versus flux patches
um but maybe also something within the
core
in in the circulation there which ober
talks about
uh there's yeah i think there's way more
than one
situation causing all this uh
anomalous behavior in south atlantic
okay more complicated than maybe we
yeah i think so all right that's great
thank you very much
excellent and i think eduardo had a
question
what took his hand down oh it's been
answered already thanks
maybe do you have also like some thermal
magnetic remnants
measurement yes no okay
did i see the weather in the talk maybe
i missed them okay
yeah i focused it was already so obvious
to me anyway
that the rock mag didn't necessarily
show which we're going to get
good video intensities that i stay stuck
to susceptibility but um usually
because i did both for one sample i
usually put like the same material
in the coverage and then sister sample
in the vftb and it would be
very similar plots perfect thanks