a combined ams and geochronological
study to provide new
temporal constraints on late caledonian
transparent
tectonism so when you're ready there
will
okay uh can you guys
hear me and can you see a screen that
has a poster on us yeah
cool um just before i kick off uh
just to follow on from ollie's chat
there i i hope you can all see the
utility and what he's attempting to do
here but uh
unfortunately my piggy bank has not yet
stretched
to purchasing a a proper working
vsm or vtfb so i may knock
or ollie may knock on your doors for
assistance with that
obviously that sort of machinery is
what's required to generate the volume
of data that he needs
um okay so uh this is the wee picture
that i took on my way in this morning we
got lots of nice snow
um uh in san andreas there overnight
um yeah this this talk is is
uh zooming out a little bit um and and
what we're attempting to do is add a
little bit of clarity
to the timing of uh transitions between
tectonic stress fields
during orogenesis um just as a bit of
context
this is a very simple uh diagram of
of what we kind of envisage um the
iapetus ocean to have looked at
in or around let's say 600 million years
500 million years ago
we have the acadian laurentian balkan
supercontinents
in kind of three separate corners of the
iapetus prior to the access ocean
closing
um and we we know that the closing of
of that ocean involves multiple orogenic
events such as the
grampian event where we have an island
arc colliding um
onto the margin of laurentia through the
penis scotian
and turneth closing of the turn-esque
sea uh
in the version of of of of miles and
woodcock
the acadian is the closure of this rick
ocean down here
but uh if if you go by the original
definition of the acadian actually
that's to do with
closure of the diopters ocean um
so we know that this closure event
occurred and we know that this closure
event brought
the the northern part of scotland into
contact with the
with the rest of the of the uk and and
we also understand that this
closure culminated in a period of trans
current tectonics initially
transpression
and later on transtension
the evidence for these transpressive and
transtensive events
and and indeed the closure of the hiatus
is evidence that most of us i think are
familiar with
that there's a wealth of paleontological
evidence to show the continents coming
together and closing
that there's a reasonable amount of
paleomagnetic data
there's a there's a huge amount of
evidence from sedimentary basins that
tell us
uh when regimes were in convergent
phases versus transtensive phases and of
course
there's structural evidence from things
like accretionary prisons
or fold and trust spells the issue with
all of this is that even with
these multiple sources of data that are
summarized here in a diagram from sopra
and woodcock
is is that there remains a discrepancy
of
somewhere anywhere from 10 to 15 maybe
even 20 million years
in when this final phase of closing and
transpression
translated into a period of trans
tension
um to try and close this gap that a
range of approaches
have been taken one very nice piece of
work done here by
miles in 2016 compiles quite a large
volume of
geochronological data and what you can
see
um of course these geochronological data
points are taken from a host of
late caledonian intrusions that occur
across
britain ireland and what we see of
course are
our spikes and troughs and spikes and
troughs
in the rate and volume of magma that's
being produced
at different times and and these uh
spikes and troughs
are correlated in a way with the
perceived
tectonic events so we have iapetus
subduction occurring over
here from in around 440 to in around
something like
you know 225 we have late transpression
in this model extending to 420 we have
transtension in this model onsetting at
420 extending down to something like 405
and then we have this acadian event
which in in
this model is closure of the rio ocean
not the attitudes occurring sometime
between four or five into
something like three three nine five um
and one of the nice things about these
data is that it gives you
absolute time stamps to say right at
this time
a certain volume of magma of a certain
chemistry was produced
um and and that's useful
and and in many instances the isotopic
and geochemical data arising
linked to those time stamps is tied to
tectonic
processes igneous petrogenic processes
and those petrogenic processes
are hung off the perceived tectonic
stress conditions but the problem of
course
is that the geochronology in itself
doesn't actually tell you
what the stress condition was and nor
this
really the isotopic data and the the the
tectonic framework
is is basically interpreted off this
but it's not a real direct reflection of
it
um and this results in ambiguity and two
very good examples of this two papers
published
one after another in the same year by
four people who are really leaders
in the geo caledonian geological world
so from woodcock versus dewey and
striking and they both conclude
differences of about 10 to 15 million
years between when this tectonic
framework changed from net
compression or transpression to net
trans tension um and the problem
really seems to be that there's a lack
of um there's a lack of
strain markers that can be temporarily
constrained
so it would be wonderful if we could
take things like little reduction spots
or imagine that the crust was full of
sponges
and we could see when the sponges were
being compressed or when the sponges
were being extended
um so with this in mind
i thought that perhaps we could use ams
to do this
there's nothing really new about
suggesting that ams can record tectonic
strain
people have been doing this for for many
years
one study that comes to mind is the ross
of mold in scotland where patronus at
hal
argued that the ams fabric was partly an
emplacement fabric but partly a tectonic
overprint
and and built a model around that um
but but what we decided to do was to
select a suite
of intrusions and our suite of
intrusions is in connemara on the west
coast of
ireland and these intrusions of course
are located right in the middle
of all this late caledonian tectonics
and this suite of intrusions should have
a
fairly tight constraint with regard to
their age so good good age
determinations
we need to collect ams data from each of
those intrusions which intrude
at different times and we want to
compare
the evidence that we see in those
intrusions to determine if we can pick
up differences in the strain history at
different times
during late stage or a genesis and after
we've done all that
we can rejoice and say we found
temporary constrained strain markers in
orogenic settings
or we can be bitterly disappointed when
we discover that the ams is just
recording magnaflow and not straight at
all
so let's see what happened so uh this is
a map
of connemara um
[Music]
i know a limited number of you will be
familiar with this or sorry
and many of you will be unfamiliar with
this um
it's located in in the middle part of
ireland on the west coast
uh it's one of the largest caledonian
complexes in britain ireland as it turns
out by square
kilometers and it's composed of a
central uh
large battlefield called kilkiren
batholith
and then several smaller intrusions one
is called karna pluton
out here to the west the main batholith
there's the round stone intrusion here
and the ome intrusion up to the
northwest
um now we went ahead and did some
geochronology on this and put it
together with
existing geochronology from people like
martin feely and quentin crowley
and you can show quite nicely basically
that these intrusions smaller intrusions
to the northwest are significantly older
um in and around 422 423 that's quite
nice because by dewey or viceracken's
model
or sopra's model and this should be
during transpression or should have
intruded sometimes during transgression
uh the kernel pluton in and around 14 to
409 m
a and nice that should be by
one model uh post transpression but by
the alternative model
it should be during trans tension and
then the main baffle which is in
are around 403
ish m a all the way down to successively
younger intrusions which cross cut the
kilk here and battle it down here and
these younger intrusions are
as young as 380 million years so that's
definitely the latest that transgression
could have been around 400
ma and 380 extends well into post
caledonian tectonics
so this suite of intrusions is quite
nicely placed spatially
in that it's right in the middle of the
tectonic framework for the late
caledonian
and temporally because it captures um
timings
in early well during transpression right
through that transtensive process
so we're going to show you some data
from roundstone
from omi from karna and from the main
batholith
and i'm going to blast through it
because i certainly don't want to run
over time
and the first part in our investigation
of course is through a nice
fairly robust rock magnetic
characterization so
building on from what tobias was talking
about earlier on
of course ams isn't as simple as just
taking a measurement and presuming that
the measurement reflects
what you think it should reflect and
we collected over 500 sample sites
across these intrusions an average of 12
sub-specimens per site
statistically quite robust and we've
characterized the magnetic mineralogy of
more than 80 of these samples
we've used temperature versus
susceptibility we've used irm
acquisition and birm fields
we use larry fuller test we use three
component demagnetization test
all with a view of constraining exactly
what the magnetic carriers are in here
and so that we can distinguish let's say
normal fabrics from inverse fabrics or
hydrothermal fabrics
and we could strip away fabrics that we
feel
are associated with post and placement
solid state processes
or hydrothermal alteration so this gives
us the best chance of
capturing let's say that the tectonic or
strain that occurred as consequences
tectonic strain
so this is an example of some of our um
temperature versus susceptibility
results and as you can see
uh fairly boring stuff um
temperature on the increase here in red
among cooling in blue and you can see
that
effectively all of these results just go
all the way up to almost 580 degrees
celsius
and then drop straight down to
paramagnetic behavior past security
temperature so this is you know very
very straightforward
near stoichiometric very very low
titanium uh
magnetite uh we went on and took
many of those samples and did some irm
and birm tests and again you can see
you know the samples reaching
saturations in very very low
irm fields again inferring that there's
magnetically very very soft magnetite
and we went ahead and did three
component tests on these again just to
check and see if
let's say there were um anomalous
proportions of things like hematite in
there or features that could be a
consequence of things like weathering
and things like that
and in the vast majority of samples as
expected of course
it is you know multi-domain or
fine-grained multi-domain
magnetite um expected to give you
you know normal ams fabrics
and in some of the samples however we
did find
a quite large proportion of sulfides for
example in this one g15
we've got a nice big peak here at about
300 degrees on the heating curve
pointing strongly towards the presence
of some sulfide minerals another
lump here occurring about 520 to me this
looks like magnetite that's actually
growing
as the sample has been heated and then
of course the cooling curve is
completely irreversible
and this is telling us that the magnetic
mineralogy of the sample is quite
different
from what is characteristic around the
other intrusions
um when we do our birm irm fields we can
see that the coercivity of these
minerals
are much higher as well um and in some
cases need fields of
greater than you know one to 1.2 teslas
or more to fully saturate pointing
towards
the presence of very high porosity
minerals that's atypical of the rest of
the intrusion
as it turns out many of these samples
have been
collected near a known porphyry that
occurs
in the center of the omi pluton in the
center of the kernel pluton and on the
side of the karna pluton
and in some instances this is very
obvious and you can see it in a field
like this where you get
very nice filler alteration mineral
molybdenite mineralization
chalcopyrite things like that but in
some samples you don't necessarily see
this very obviously in the field but you
do see it in the ams
or in the rock magnetic data and we were
able to strip
these samples away allowing us to again
focus on fabrics that are more closely
related or more
definitively related to uh tectonic
strain
during the original crystallization of
the magma
so jumping into some data um this is
some data from the round stone pluton
again about 423
mma um
the geological context for this is is
fairly tightly constrained people have
mapped this for the last 40
50 years quite simple really you have
some metagable in the country rock you
have dalaranian
supergroup sediments in the country rock
which are intruded by that metagabro
and all of this is understood to be in
the hanging wall to a regional thrust
which the foot wall is exposed through
this tectonic window
over here so in cross section the
geological setting looks a little bit
like this you the delaney dorm it's it's
a rhyolite in that in the in the
football
in the hanging wall you have the
metamorphic complex in connemara which
is
medicabro and radiant supergroups and
into that we have the
the round stone granite uh intruded
um now ams data on the left here we have
a contour plot
of shape and isosceles tj
just just contoured one of the very
striking things that you see
here is that all of the linear
uh or prolate fabrics tend to occur
along the near the center of this
intrusion and certainly along the sort
of north west southeast
um sort of axis
and one of the other very interesting
things we see is when we
kind of make detailed field maps in here
detailed field observations
is that where we see injections of
different
granuloid fascists but the contacts
between these fasces
are low bait or they are diffuse
inferring that um these are certainly
magma magma
interactions there's no evidence for any
solid-state deformation in here
so we can conclude that the fabrics
being recorded
are magmatic state fabrics
time there will how much
you've gone over so what yeah okay
cool um okay so i'll cut to the chase
when we
model that ams data up onto a stereo net
we see that the k3 axes
and to these ams data are sub horizontal
and orientated in the northeast and the
southwest of the stereo net
if i jump ahead because i'm out of time
now to the omi pluton
again we get a very similar structural
signature in our ams data again with a
sub-horizontal
are gently inclined k3 axes along the
northwest
um so it's sort of uh or sorry north
south west northeast axis
um again in the karna pluton
we have a very very similar structural
signature
and at this point we're quite young
we're down to about 410
million uh years and again we very
compelling evidence to show that these
fabrics have been imparted
during the magmatic state samples taken
from this locality
with this biotite modal layering which
is very clearly a magmatic state fabric
still returns these steeply inclined
magmatic foliations
and the last sample site then is across
the main
battle across to cook here in baffleuf
along
this blue box this this blue
traverse here um and
long story short what we see is a pure
shear flattening fabric
to the north and as you traverse down to
the center of this intrusion
the fabrics change to become prolate
and critically the k3
axis rotates to become vertical
which is telling us that the sigma 1 has
now
flipped and is now in a vertical
position
so putting this together what we see is
that
about 420 and right down to 410 million
years
we have a sigma 3 that is sub horizontal
inferring that
magma is in a compressive uh field
but by the time we get to about 402
sigma 3 is vertical telling us that
sigma 1 is now vertical
and that is consistent with a trans
uh well what an extensional environment
i.e trans
uh tension so the
final model that we've come up with is
where we have
the tectonic framework of connemara the
square roots faulted
south highland boundary falls to the
north during regional sinister
transpression sigma one of course
is on the horizontal uh plane
um promoting anti-clockwise block
rotation
as the only pluton and round stone
pluton
intrude and by the time we get to 410
the karna pluton
is intruding still within this net
compressive
stress field um imparting steep
uh kind of a steeper structural fabric
within that intrusion and by the time we
get to
400 ma the stress field has evolved to
be
transtensive allowing larger volumes of
magma to intrude
and the structural fabric recorded in
magmas that cool
at that time and are provided basically
sub-horizontal magnetic fabric
and a sub-horizontal magnetic
lining so
that's just the summary there based off
these data it would
indicate the transtension in this part
of the origin belt
didn't really onset until after 410
and we feel that this provide this is
the potential to provide a nice new
tool that allows us to provide temporal
valley constrained strain markers in
origin in general
it's worth noting that we've tried this
and done it all and had to go at it and
mull
and edit and we're getting similar
results at similar times
so it suggests that this works not just
in connemara but
across origin in general thank you
um thanks for that will um adrian you
said your talk's not that long
so if you're willing then we can have
one very quick question
if that's okay with you adrian
yes
oh so yep yep go first
so which of the two models was correct
can i tell nigel woodcock he's right or
wrong
i'd prefer to tell him myself uh for
fear that you just dropped me in
and i'll make an enemy forever but in
in in in my base of the data that i can
see there
i can see trans tension on the setting
after 410 because i have an intrusion
that is 410 million years old
and there are steep fabrics in it and
that's
consistent with all the intrusions that
we have data from
that we know intruded during
transgression
so
that's presuming that you accept that
the ams fabric is in fact
another process but i evidence for that
which i think works okay uh
yeah colonel's hand is up there so we'll
just one quickly
so so your transition from transgression
to trans tension you've modeled
with anti-clockwise rotation in in the
area of the main granite
every published study of rocks ranging
in age from ordovician right the way
through to silurian in that area
are all clockwise
and there's a study by robertson on the
connemara gabbro which is
in the south western corner uh there's
two papers by mark smithers
on silurian rocks that actually range
right the way along
the northern part of that area and and
every single published rotation is
clockwise
yeah fair enough uh i think you find
dewey jakes and reevy as well
also have a have the opposite block
rotation model
um and well the truth be told
if that block is rotating one way or the
other doesn't necessarily
change the broader model i just have to
have a rotation going one way or the
other
but if you if you take a wee ice cube
and put a sinister strike slip across
top well that's the direction it goes so
it depends which side you pin it on well
it does yes yeah
well yeah yeah so i have a very
it's sort of a quick follow-up question
but have you measured the
um remnants on any of these samples
um i have yes
off the top of my head but yes we did
all that as a as part of the
the first step of the rock car rockman
characterization
yeah yeah but but you haven't done you
haven't d-magged any of them
uh we did yeah well we de-magnet afd mag
did those directions show anything
uh i not off-hand
but what are you alluding towards those
i can check
well well well well you know very simple
test would be if you've got any coherent
remnants and there are any coherent
remnants directions you could
see are they rotated or not your block
rotation
yeah so so actually for at the only
intrusion i i
attempted to do that because there's a
well i
hypothesize you got two shear zones
bounding a block of granite in the
middle which we have data and remnants
data from
but in my opinion i didn't really see
i didn't think the data looked
particularly good weren't particularly
reliable uh
mike petronas agreed and i just thought
okay fair enough and i left it at that
um
[Music]
but i suppose it's not the you wouldn't
necessarily expect
the granite futons themselves to be
rotating you're expecting the blocks
adjacent to them to rotate so i suppose
if you wanted to test that you want to
have a look at the dikes that are cross
cutting
maybe the earlier dikes or perhaps even
the um some of the
earlier grampian intrusions
because they would have been obviously
pre onset of transgression
and yeah but the grampian ones are
clockwise rotated this is the
this is the problem yeah um
okay yeah yeah maybe we should chat
maybe we should chat about this but
there's some more i i
collected a whole lot of samples from
their donkeys years ago and we measured
fabrics we went for all the mafic
enclaves oh cool yeah um
and i'm trying to remember there was
there was some coherence in that in the
fabric data but the remnants data was
just
shied yeah mike had me treat because i i
mean i did the
mag experiments as a phd student uh so
he was just basically telling me what to
do and i did what i was told for the
most part sometimes
um but yeah we treated them with you
know low temperature cryogenic before we
d
magnum and stuff and i mean it's such
coarse-grained multi-domain stuff
that
was a bit iffy and so i didn't dig into
it too much
yeah i'd be useful to chat with you
afterwards about it
let's do it let's do that i'll i'll drag
stuff from
the bottom drawer somewhere