um yeah so for something completely
different now
um hello my name is anna and i am a
pediatrician at the university of oxford
and um i am going to present some work
on tetrathenai specifically its
identification with various
um microscopy and magnetic methods um
this is not a complete study so um if
anyone has any feedback on where to go
next what method supply will um
how to improve existing methods i'll be
very helpful
just going to find the pointer oh yeah
um tetrodinai is a
mineral which has received a lot of
interest from the magnetic from the
meteorite
magnesium community in particular
meteorites have been used for
monthly studies because they contain um
abundant metal and usually
um usually oxides and really interesting
microstructures so they're very
interesting
targets for magnetic studies in
particular they've been used for
the identification of ancient magnetic
fields
and the reason for that is that we can
use
magnetic studies to get insight into
the structure of terrestrial bodies like
ancient virtual bodies we can get a lot
of information like
the timing of their creation whether
they differentiated whether they
um formed them in a core um the
that whether they formulate in the core
and how they form their size of parent
body
um and a lot of basically really
fascinating information about the early
solar system with
implications to um service evolution and
early monthly fields and
earth's magnetic field through
comparisons
and that's all great but there is of
course about um
meteorites have incredibly complex
history sometimes they combine
um impacts that of what they combine
impacts
acres alteration metamorphism and so
what we need
in order to get all of this really cool
information is um
very um
very reliable magnets one such magnet
has been identified as the japanite um
so this
is the ordered um
ordered form of fahrenheit which is
ionical
um with high nickel so detroit is
generally between 50 and 55 percent
nicole
and it forms through very slow cooling
through the ordering temperature of
tetrathena
so um 310 degrees
um importantly it's been identified to
have incredibly high co-activity so
after two
tesla and all of these meteorites are
ones where tetrotini has been identified
as
a reliable carrier
now one meteorite that one meteorite
group which is known to contain abundant
tetradi which is not on this list is
um the mesosiderides so mesothelioids
are stained iron meteorites with
approximately
equal parts metal and silica they're
generally considered to be mixtures of
core material and crystal or mantle
material
so they probably involved some kind of
impact at some point in their history
but this is all not very well understood
in any case crucially they are known to
have
an extremely slow cooling rate the
slower skill in the raymond
of any rock um so that's less than one
degree per million years
so at that slower cooling rate tetradi
is present in
quite large amounts um so because they
have a
relatively poorly understood history and
because there's vegetanite present
we thought we would apply um several
um experimental techniques to
compare them and see how like which one
is best for identified single domain
tetrathenite um so here here are the
methods that were used so far
um we use scanning electron microscopy
with eds and ebsd
as well as some limited chemical
analysis with the electron microprobe
which i will mention briefly but not
dwell on um and
here are um some vault magnetic
measurements um
that were done so far
uh the sample used was estevel it was a
class
out of so esther villa zabrachia
my sample is one class of the
spreadsheet on
a loan from the oxford museum of natural
history
and i've separated well i've cut off
three chips of this main mass
which the measurements are done on um
very briefly um a tour on
the petrology of this so as i mentioned
it's almost equal parts metal
so that's represented by camera sight
hair with some internal
variation which i'm going to talk about
in a minute and
silicon so this is a metamorphosed
vessels assemblage with
plagioclase and pyroxenes with some
accessory minerals
and then there's also sulfide and some
phosphate
well no one phosphate um
two identified identified tetrathena
what we are looking for first
is just high nickel metal so this is
present
first and foremost within the camera
side which is lower nickel so
as part of for example the cloudy zone
now meteorologists are so slowly cool
that the cloud design actually grew
um the the the tetrahedral islands in
the clouds and actually grew too large
so they are in multi-domain state
um which is why they were not the focus
of the study we actually looked at the
silicates
because um multi-domain digital dna is
um
is not particularly helpful so focusing
on the silicate instead
um it turns out that metal grains within
the silicon matrix are actually
fairly common so they um come together
with either sulfide
um which is trolite or camosite um
and they are quite abundant and they
don't seem to have very much
microstructure
um all of these were identified with
both um
eds and electron probe as high nickel so
about 54 percent nickel generally
but this is not actually enough to
identify the tethering eye because
there's compositional overlap between
um detroit and tennis so then we've
applied
ebsd to get structural information on
the crystal
and they were all identified
successfully as digital
which was great um this is a tiny
absd map for timing constraints of one
of these grains
but then of course these grains are a
few tens of microns across generally
they are still not
um small enough so i've gone
even smaller so um it turns out
there are some nanometric inclusion
inclusions of sulfide and
metal in some silica crystals
so here is um a mineral intergroup
between chromite and tridomide in an
encephalitis host this is all this is
really interesting
but i don't have time to talk about it
uh what i'm going to talk about is these
inclusion trails here
majority of these are sulfide but some
of them are metal
and some of them are small enough and
highlightable enough to be
um uh
to be to have the potential to beat the
training there we go
i don't know if you can see it um there
there's a very very tiny about 70
nanometers that's your 29 grain
well um high nickel grain so then i've
gone and i've tried to
uh do bsd on this and i've run into a
lot of resolution issues
um it is the at least the way i did that
didn't really cope with that
like that that level of small sizes so
that wasn't great because i couldn't
establish that this was
detroit night now given that it was
present in the rest of the sample then
it's a fair assumption that well
i hope it's a fair assumption that the
whole sample did not get reheated above
the ordering temperature
for long enough for that today night to
go back to the night
um but still it couldn't be established
[Music]
confidently one final thing i would say
on this
if we zoom out it turns out these
um inclusions are actually quite common
so they continue around here and this
crystal is actually
about twice the size that is shown here
and there is another one of it in the
sample
so this so these are quite common these
um nanometric
inclusions so i thought barring the fact
that i couldn't
um identify statute and i they would
still be quite interesting for some kind
of
localized magnetic study um i started
the magnetic part of the study with
um just bulk measurements
and i got this now i do apologize if my
xylites trigger some kind of
fight or flight response um i'm told
well i hope that these are quite common
in
meteoric studies um what we see here
in both samples um is a low cost of the
component which demonizes by 12 to 15
milli tesla and there is no
stable high quality component on top of
this
the low cost of the component actually
contains most of the nrm
so essentially the high quality spectrum
just doesn't really have any helpful
information
so i've gone and i've
[Music]
done some irm acquisition experiments to
find out what is present in the sample
according to magnetism as opposed to
microscopy
and the first one is not particularly
interesting so here we have
the iron acquisition curve and the
differential
and we just see uh what is
representative for multi-domain camosite
with a
peak there at low fields
but if we go to
the next sample some extra picks show up
in
in here in the collectivity spectrum and
there is again the peak for um
molten main hemocyte now another peak
has appeared for multiple domain
digester night
which has been identified as such before
in a few papers
there is also a tiny pig here 500 milli
tesla which i'm not entirely sure how to
identify
but it is based on just the one um data
point
so i would actually like to go and do
this experiment again and get more
um get high resolution in the higher
fields
to see exactly what this is and if if
the peak stays there
in any case um there is
no or very limited tetragona here
because for
reference here's what um the curve would
look like if there was single domain
tetrathena presence so it starts
jumping up at 600 millivessler mine if
anything saturates the 600
so um conclusion here is that
we have little or no single dimensional
present
um which is a bit strange because
well it was unclear from the nanometric
um
inclusions that those high nickel grains
were technical but it was likely
from magnetism i found that there is no
well
very little single the main
tetrathermite so
um essentially the only reasonable
conclusion here is um
in magnets with dress when it comes to
pleasure fahrenheit
um and very briefly i want to talk about
implications for the parent body
um there is no stable high quality
signal
this means either there was nothing to
record so that could be because the
mystery
and the parent body never had the monkey
field perhaps it didn't differentiate
completely
or perhaps the magnetic field shut off
too early so either because of cooling
and the shot of the dynamo or perhaps
because of a
impact as i mentioned before and impact
has been hypothesized
to be part of the mises reformation
history
so perhaps a destructive impact shot of
the dynamo
it is also possible that the field was
in fact too low intensity
um to be recorded so if the fidelity
if the sample fidelity of vestable is
not high enough
so because of their steamy your next
step is to go and do some air and
fidelity experiments
i was going to do this in march and then
there was a pandemic
so this is this is happening as soon as
i can get back into a lab
and in longer term i would like to get
high resolution ubsd maps of
metals and higher resolution
well look at the microstructure as well
higher resolution are in my position as
i mentioned before and
i am curious about applying in-situ
magnetic techniques to those inclusions
but at the same time i am aware that
misused rights are just
not very good for magnetic studies it
turns out so
maybe this is a little bit of a dead end
but i'm very interested in hearing
opinions
thank you
thank you so do you have any questions
yeah let's talk um i was gonna ask about
your your ebsd
so you were able to identify tetratenite
in your ebsd
was that based on uh you had enough
resolution to detect
the tetragonal distortion of the
tetratenite or were you able to pick up
the the the extra diffraction peaks that
you get because of the ironical ordering
um so it identified the tetragonal
structure of the jotani
all of these grains in the matrix were
remarkably homogeneous
there wasn't really anything going on in
them um but no it didn't really identify
peaks about
um on distortion or anything like that
but that'll be really interesting the
distortion's enough
you can confidently distinguish the
cubic from the tetragonal
yeah uh this was based on the um on a
tetrahedron reference file from the uh
american okay
that's good yeah
it may be nice to try that on the we we
did try
wanted to try that on the cloudy zone in
the mesa ciderise to see if you could
identify the differently oriented
uh variants within the cloudies i think
that would be
that would be very interesting it's
looking like you're getting very nice
data uh so that would be an interesting
yeah i was um tentatively pointing the
uh pointing the gun at the cloudy zone
um
with um with ebsd but i was actually
getting really really messy
patterns i'm guessing either the the
the length scale of the microstructures
were smaller than the resolution
that absd had about that particular
moment but yeah i think that'll be
interesting
yeah it's not easy no imagine this
thank you yeah any more questions
uh i'll just ask a quick question just
uh on the
in-situ magnetic techniques that you
plan to use um
so what specifically are you thinking
and you know do you think you can you
can get to the resolution that you need
um so i was tentatively thinking about
squid microscopy or maybe
um quantum down on microscopy this was
also to
put on hold by covert because we
realized we need to go abroad to do
these things
um so i have not thought about them in
detail but i think the resolution is
possible