perfect all right so i'm allison klein
and i'm from
imperial college london and this is my
first magnetic interactions conference
so i'm very happy to be here
and so i'm going to talk you through my
poster which is on magnetic recording of
earth's history
which describes a 3d nanoscale method
for characterization
of a single crystal which was collected
at glenn mountain
so by using practical and theoretical
approaches it allows us to accurately
determine the behavior of natural
samples which will lead to more accurate
paleo intensity estimates
so the key to predicting the magnetic
response of a sample
is in the detailed morphology
distributions and these can contain
distributions of millions of particles
in this case magnetite and these all
have different shapes and sizes
which defines their unique magnetic
behavior and recording fidelity
so how do we measure these green sizes
is we use a technique called slice and
view
and we do this on an instrument fib sem
and what we do is we use the focused
iron beam to mill a slice
and then we image the corresponding
slice with the sem
so what we can do is process these sem
images
and realign them to produce a 3d
reconstruction
like what we see here where we can
undertake some quantitative particle
metrics
so what we're seeing here is quite
interesting distribution so we are
seeing a number of grains with a variety
of different sizes
so we are seeing more of the regular
simple ellipsoids that we would expect
to see but we're also seeing these
uh non-interacting highly elongated
particles
that run pretty much the full size
thickness which is nearly 2.5 microns
um which yeah but which is interesting
um so the combination of this a
nanometer a tomography and the
micromagnetic simulations here on the
right
allows us to better understand the link
between the morphologies and the
magnetic
properties so the resulting remnant
states is what we see here
and this includes a single domain and
single vortex
which are the two domain states that we
would expect to dominate
the remnant magnetization in the vast
majority of samples
but what's interesting here is that
we're also seeing a
some multi-domain for these larger
elongated particles
and so this is just a quick summary of
what we've been working on at the moment
there's quite a lot today still to do
melee simulation work which includes
hysteresis forks uh relaxation times
um but that's what we've been working on
at the moment um
yeah if anyone has any questions i would
love to speak to you i've recently
transferred from physics to
paleomagnetism so i would be lovely to
speak to you
and yeah that's pretty much it thank you
okay
so anybody else want to jump in there
okay maybe i'll start to share my screen
yeah yeah
okay
[Music]
okay do you see my screen
yeah okay in the poster i would like to
present some work that i done last year
when i was on my thursday in cambridge
and um the motivation
to this study uh
was a great concern about environmental
protections and
uh rehabilitation of the environment
especially after
running exploration and knowing that
heavy metals that are one of the major
pollution pollutants
in soils are
associated with magnetic particles
i thought that it might be a good idea
to
check how those particles
uh behave in source if there are any
trends
uh with time and so on so
uh three former mining areas uh that are
located here
uh were sampled and sourced from that
area was sampled
to characterize magnetic meteorology and
find this correlation
is there any actually between magnetic
properties
magnetic finger fingerprints and
ores that was exploited actually
uh we sampled mainly soils uh
surrounding spoiled hips and mine waste
but also soils developed on
those ways called tecnosols
and what can be seen from the results
from thermal magnetic curves
the mineralogy is quite well diversified
with
magnetite and hematite that are main
magnetic phases but also iron sulfides
and
probably machiamite is also present here
and unfortunately si
um and x-ray diffraction was much
helpful
in disentangling this mineralogy however
using fork pca we can observe that there
is
a diversification in terms of grain size
of those
magnetic phases however there is a
common
thing that is shown here so
in both technology
and source surrounding mine waste
we observed uh quite
distinct particles not interacting spsd
particles with varying coercivity
that most likely is of anthropogenic
origin
and it could be also divided as
separate end members in a particular
sites actually and what is
more important this particle seems to be
quite persistent as they
are present in a relatively unchanged
form
in source uh that were developed 50
years and 400 years ago
so if you're interested in if sorry if
you're interested please join me in the
poster hall
i'll be happy to answer all questions
thanks
okay who's next in line and you want to
shout
is that handle from ursula there
whenever you're ready
can you see that yeah
um so this project it's i'm a fourth
year
earth sciences student supervised by
rich harrison
as well and uh
and this this project is
part of an ongoing masters project so
i'm really just presenting the
uh like an overview and preliminary
results
um so it's characterizing
broadly speaking the remnant
magnetic carriers in quadratic
meteorites
and one of the main ways
that we're doing this or at least it's
an emphasis for the project
is using micromagnetic modeling
techniques
and um it is basically applying the same
methods as
alison cohen's group on the glenn
mountain
crystal we're using focused iron beam
3d tomography methods and
merrell code for the micromagnetic
simulations
and
yeah with our case study sample
is a c2 meteorite this one
um something which james bryson has
recently done
a bit of work on and last time i checked
he's he's here so
um we did some we had a brief sem
session
and this this is some backscatter images
which i've pulled
and put on here because they're some of
the the more
unusual and interesting they show
some of the the more interesting spatial
distributions of
iron-rich phases and
i haven't i haven't really yet looked
beyond a few papers
into this exactly how they relate to
how they're formed and how they relate
to some of the larger morphologies that
the project is focused on
i'm not not sure at all so that that's
if anyone
has any ideas or wants to pass comment
on that
um come and find me i'm also looking for
phd opportunities
so uh that's that's the scope of the
project
so yeah i'll be in the poster hall after
this
so anybody else want to jump in thanks
for that ursula and
anybody want to shout
i'll go but i want to wait a little
second because there's some chickens in
the garden that are shouting very loud
so i don't want to bother anyone but
um here's my poster
um essentially i've been looking at a
series of mesoproterozoic giant dykes in
southern greenland and i've particularly
tried been trying to figure out their
emplacement history and post and
placement mechanisms that have occurred
by using rock magnetics and so i titled
it trying to
try and decipher the primary flow from
interstitial mouth migration
so i went out to to grain into map
collect samples and then
did a bunch of photography and rock
magnetics
and i've been trying to
trying to integrate a a model
or try to produce a petrogenic model of
the system
where we can
sorry i've got lost my train of thought
so
i've been trying to integrate the
in-phase ams and outfit ams
using other rock magnetic techniques
such as susceptibility experiments
and arm to try and figure out what
um magnetic clusters that the
these different experiments are
measuring
and ultimately what we've what i've gone
into so far
is that it seems like these giant dike
systems which
reach up to 800 meters wide probably
didn't intrude as a classic
penny shaped crack dike but more as a
series of fingered loaves
intruding and coalescing in an
extensional regime
um and what i'm trying to do following
that now
is to try and see we've found some
evidence that there's potentially some
compaction occurring and there's
evidence of melt segregation and so we
think that maybe
the finer grain rock magnetic
uh clusters are recording these later
stage migrations
um and we have some exciting clues that
that does seem to be the case and that
the
out of phase and the arn are indicating
a
a secondary fabric that isn't recorded
in phase ams
um and ultimately the current
interpretations that i have
are that these systems are intruding
in a series of convective loads that are
later than
um post-deposition and crystallization
the last gasps are these interstitial
amounts that are almost built to press
down
but if you're interested in anything
that we've been talking about in
particular if anyone has any ideas as to
how
i can further test um what out of phase
ams is recording please do
come around
cool thanks lot uh is there anybody else
who wants to pipe up or shout
i see a handle from rory there yeah sure
i'll go next
um since i'm also looking at the younger
giant dykes
of greenland
there we go can you see my screen
cool so uh yes i'm also looking at the
same area
that lots looking at at lots areas down
in this blue bit here called cesarotoc
and i'm looking at an area just
to the north at sorotit so um
basically this is part of the gardar
province of
southern greenland and these are um
neoproterozoic dikes which were
in place during failed intercontinental
rift environment and they reach
up to 800 meters wide and the
interesting thing about these dikes are
that they have these
discrete domains within them of
different either compositions or
layering differences um or both in some
cases
and so i've been looking at places where
the composition changes
into these these pods of more evolved
composition
and so i've been doing an ams study i've
done
three transects across this pod where we
have tropical light at the margins
going through sinogabro to port cyanide
at the center
and um preliminary results that i've
found so far
is that um so these between these two
pods we have a numbering here
and this looks like the pods are
representing
fingers which are inflating and pressing
up against um
walls between the the pods and then
forming almost broken bridge structures
um as these uh dykes coalesce and um
and meet up the as these lobes meet up
um
and uh also the lineations generally are
pointing towards the
north east and
just to try and put this into a bit of
context with this
area on the in figure a we have
essentially the area that lots looking
at which is
structurally deeper within the dike and
um
we're seeing that the formation of
layering and
what i'm proposing is that this
formation of layering and foliation
we have an interstitial melt formation
which then is migrating upwards in the
dike
um and forming these um zones of more
evolved composition
and so these pods um are formed through
the the secondary placement of material
which is formed
from within this dike complex and is
migrating upwards within it
um and so yeah i encourage any of you to
come and check out my
poster very kindly put it right at the
front
and yeah please come and chat to me this
is my
this is for my mgl undergraduate
dissertation and
it's very much still a work in progress
so i'd love to chat to
anyone about my ams data and tx results
and these amazing giant bikes
okay is there anybody else
so um actually i have a poster as well
so i just want to very quickly go
through it myself so i'll just share my
own screen
if you don't mind um
so can you guys see that all right two
seconds
so are you can you guys see that yeah
sure
cool so just in case um you for anybody
who doesn't know me
my own name is vincent toomey um i'm a
final year phd student
here in the university of saint andrews
working with will
and as part of my phd here i'm trying
this new project
so i'm trying to couple
detailed structural mapping of a
magmatic body
and linking it with paleomagnetic
analysis
so effectively just to kind of give you
a quick update that when you know
when a magma intrudes into a host rock
structure forcefully intrudes into it
and can buckle and bend the the
surrounding hose rack around it and
could ultimately
produce these intrusion-induced
forcefolds
which obviously form synchronously with
the intrusion of the the body
so um i the aim is to actually test this
hypothesis
where the so the premise behind this
hypothesis to
um is that the paleomagnetic analysis
and that the thermal remnant
magnetization
could be expected to successfully
overprint the host rock
primary remnant magnetization as the hot
magma from the body
increment like incrementally injects and
displaces that host rock
so like effectively as the plutonium
places
the whole structure like it the
plutonium will in place and inflate
and so the the trm could be expected
like
the paleo the subsequent magnetic
vectors could be expected to change over
that
so ultimately the the goal is is to see
that can the pmag
help like record this progressive and
or even stepwise or punctuated host rock
deformation
during this informational lack of
construction and in turn can it actually
constrain the rate and duration of
cooling
particularly in rapidly in place bodies
in the shallow crust
so some of me are familiar with this
area in eastern iceland
sand fell so this is my study area so
basically this is just the preliminary
analysis so basically i collected a
suite of pmax samples along the
structural oriole and the reason why we
went to sandfell is that the actual
exposure is very good so you got these
very well exposed intrusion and juice
forceful and you can actually see that
the actual dip value of these
uh lava of the neogene lava piles in
eastern iceland actually
changes and actually steepens away from
the contact
and so this is just the initial analysis
that the next step for me which is i'm
effectively jumping into now
is do the pca analysis and actually see
if this um pmag data is actually worthy
now the initial
like there are some little kinks in the
data so this actually could be showing
the the switch or an influence from
the magma body so if anybody has any
any kind of input on you know any
caveats or any advice or
seen some similar project come to my
poster
um now i'm kind of abusing my power now
as convening this session
and instead of you know being at the pub
last night i actually kind of put
together a very quick poster
that's not in the abstract but it's
actually from another part of my phd
that um that
that i've actually submitted to the gel
sock before christmas so fingers crossed
but
i just put this together quickly last
night just to kind of show you what the
work is
so as will mentioned in his talk
and that you know the ams has been used
for decades now to constrain
magma flow dynamics and then placement
mechanisms
and however a lot of the times it just
it comes up with the actual internal
dynamics of a magmatic body
and it doesn't give much constraints in
terms of what the
the implications of these emplacement
mechanisms actually have
on subsequent or associated volcanism
with these intrusive bodies
so again similarly enough i use detailed
you know like you know by combining
structural mapping
drone work with ams as a complement
i actually map out this another
very well exposed um subvolcanic
silicic body in iceland and actually map
and do a pretty comprehensive ams
analysis with detailed structural
mapping
around its associated structural oriole
now
the results i came out with with the ams
suite in the main body of the lacklus
again is this kind of classic
low bait structures where effectively
the k1s
are orientated along this northeast
north east southwest axis which actually
is quite comparable with the regional
trend of the faults and fractures
across within and beyond the structural
orioles
now and so the lobes are actually
based on the wrapping around of the
magnetic foliation
uh along the actual the the
the pretty pervasive northeast southwest
trend of the k1 values which
you know which actually show a range of
inclinations
now this is not new and this has been
published for again decades going back
to even
carl stevens and johnny hutton all those
guys both
both using rock magnetics and
geophysical techniques
but because they're copying the ams with
the whole strap deformation
the i've actually managed to map out
some
inclined sheets which are directly
offset from the lack of it
and doing an ams suite within
our around these um these incline sheets
we actually can we actually show how the
how the magma true ams now truly ams
data set how the magma actually migrates
from this laterally flowing low bait
structures
that you see here so this is a and how
these actual so these incline sheets
which are actually paralleling the
regional
fall fracture trend so in
actually on the lateral flanks
peripheral flanks are these low bait
structures which propagate out towards
the west southwest of the area
the magma is it's shown to actually flow
upwards through
the classic implication model which
simon talked on yesterday
and also just true and like you know
just truly
the paralleling are being sub parallel
to the actual
um wall structure of these intrusions so
this
this is implications for volcanism in
terms of you know how
this this actually compares with
geophysical observations where
volcanic eruptions are actually
laterally offset from the main magma
body to which it is associated with
but again this is another poster which i
just cheaply put up last night so
thanks very much everyone